<page>

    <title>Frank John Hughes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8141737</id>
    <revision>
      <id>541993334</id>
      <parentid>540417049</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-04T03:43:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>71.105.92.93</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4394">{{Other people2|Frank Hughes (disambiguation)}}
{{BLP sources|date=February 2010}}
{{Infobox person
| name          = Frank John Hughes
| birthname     = 
| birth_date     = {{birth date and age|1967|11|11}}
| birth_place = [[The Bronx, New York]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| occupation = Actor
| years_active = 1990–present
}}

'''Frank John Hughes''' (born November 11, 1967) is an [[United States|American]] [[film]] and [[television]] [[actor]] best known for his portrayal of [[William Guarnere|&quot;Wild Bill&quot; Guarnere]] in the [[HBO]] miniseries ''[[Band of Brothers (TV miniseries)|Band of Brothers]]'', Tom Fox in ''[[Catch Me If You Can]]'', Tim Woods in ''[[24 (TV series)|24]]'', and [[Walden_Belfiore#Walden_Belfiore|Walden Belfiore]] in ''[[The Sopranos]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=TV Review: 'Sopranos' trails off with a tease |first=Rob |last=Owen |url=http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/tv/tv-review-sopranos-trails-off-with-a-tease-488812/#ixzz2FbNwxry1 |newspaper=[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]] |date=10 June 2007 |accessdate=20 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Early life and career==
A native of the [[South Bronx]], Hughes studied jazz composition at the [[Berklee College of Music]] in [[Boston, Massachusetts|Boston]]. At the age of nineteen he became one of the youngest members ever to be given lifetime membership in [[The Actor's Studio]]. He also studied with acting teacher Sonia Moore. After numerous stage productions [[Off-Broadway]], Hughes made  his feature film debut in [[Robert Celestino]]'s ''True Convictions'' (1991).

Since then he has starred in such films as: ''[[Bad Boys (1995 film)|Bad Boys]]'' (1995) opposite [[Will Smith]], ''Lonely in America'' (1991), ''[[The Funeral (1996 film)|The Funeral]]'' (1996) opposite [[Benicio del Toro]] and [[Christopher Walken]], ''Layin' Low'' (1996), ''[[Mr. Vincent]]'' (1997) (for which he won mass critical acclaim at the [[Sundance Film Festival]] for his role as John Vincent), ''Urban Jungle'' (1999), ''Robbers'' (2000), ''[[Anacardium (film)|Anacardium]]'' (2001) (for which he won BEST ACTOR at the New York Independent Film Festival), and [[Steven Spielberg]]'s ''[[Catch Me If You Can]]'' (2002). He also appeared in Robert Celestino's ''Yonkers Joe'' opposite [[Chazz Palminteri]] and [[Christine Lahti]] and in [[Jon Avnet]]'s ''[[Righteous Kill]]'' opposite [[Robert De Niro]] and [[Al Pacino]].

==Television==
Hughes is a veteran of television. He had recurring roles in the series:
* [[HBO]]'s ''[[The Sopranos]]'' as [[Walden Belfiore]], a soldier in the [[Soprano crime family]], who committed the last murder in the series when he killed [[Lupertazzi crime family]] boss, [[Phil Leotardo]]. 
* HBO's mini-series, ''[[Band of Brothers (TV miniseries)|Band of Brothers]]'' (2001) as &quot;[[William Guarnere|&quot;Wild Bill&quot; Guarnere]]
* The [[Dick Wolf]] series ''[[Players (1997 TV series)|Players]]'' (1997) 
* [[NBC]]'s series ''[[LAX (TV series)|LAX]]'' 

Other appearances include: ''[[Cover Me: Based on the True Life of an FBI Family|Cover Me]]'', ''[[Law &amp; Order]]'', ''[[Homicide: Life on the Street]]'', ''[[Feds]]'', ''[[Without a Trace]]'', ''[[Monk (TV series)|Monk]]'', ''[[Boomtown (2002 TV series)|Boomtown]]'', ''[[Kings of South Beach]]'', ''[[Curb Your Enthusiasm]]'', ''[[JAG (TV series)|JAG]]'', ''[[The Path to 9/11]]'', ''[[Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent]]'', ''[[NCIS (TV series)|NCIS]]'', and ''[[Criminal Minds]]''.

==Video game work==
* He provides voiceovers in the video game ''[[Call of Duty 2: Big Red One]]''.{{cn|date=November 2012}}

==Latest works==
In 2009, Hughes joined the cast of the series ''[[24 (TV series)|24]]'' as Secretary of Homeland Security, Tim Woods. He returned to that role in 2010.
==References==
{{Reflist}}
==External links==
* {{IMDb name|400606|Frank John Hughes}}
* {{ymovies name|1800396979}}

{{Authority control|VIAF=39674059}}
{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Hughes, Frank John
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = November 11, 1967
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[The Bronx, New York]], U.S.
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Hughes, Frank John}}
[[Category:1967 births]]
[[Category:Actors from New York City]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from the Bronx]]</text>
      <sha1>s8rlhqnfxmrijww000omcw8ahnecu7s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Sam Cooper Boulevard</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20145234</id>
    <revision>
      <id>507790026</id>
      <parentid>507542782</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-17T04:40:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Eboulanger</username>
        <id>4487786</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20506">{{Infobox street
|marker_image=
|name=Sam Cooper Boulevard
|maint=City of [[Memphis, Tennessee|Memphis]] and [[Tennessee Department of Transportation|TDOT]]
|image=Sam Cooper Blvd E 4.jpg
|caption=
|length_mi=5.8
|length_round=1
|length_ref=&lt;ref name=SCRouting/&gt;
|length_notes=
|established=
|decommissioned=
|direction_a=West
|terminus_a={{jct|state=TN|US|70|US|79|name2=[[East Parkway (Memphis, Tennessee)|East Parkway N]]}}
|junction=
|direction_b=East
|terminus_b={{jct|state=TN|I|40|I|240}} interchange
}}
'''Sam Cooper Boulevard''' is a six-lane controlled-access parkway/expressway in [[Memphis, Tennessee|Memphis]], [[Tennessee]], [[United States|U.S.A.]]. The more recent western segment of the road follows a parkway design, the older eastern portion which was proposed and constructed as a segment of [[Interstate 40 in Tennessee|Interstate 40]] (I-40) is built as an expressway, without at-grade intersections and traffic lights. The western terminus of Sam Cooper Boulevard is at [[East Parkway (Memphis, Tennessee)|East Parkway North]]. At the western termination point of the road there is a short concurrency of East Parkway North with [[U.S. Route 70]], [[U.S. Route 79]].&lt;ref name=GoogleEP&gt;{{cite web | title=East Parkway Memphis, Tennessee | url=http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=east+parkway+memphis&amp;sll=35.141669,-89.982147&amp;sspn=0.041621,0.090981&amp;gl=us&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=35.139371,-89.983692&amp;spn=0.010405,0.022745&amp;z=16 | publisher=Google Maps | accessdate=2009-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; From its western end, Sam Cooper Boulevard continues east for {{convert|5.8|mi|km|1}} to reach its eastern terminus at the [[Interstate 40]]/[[Interstate 240 (Tennessee)|Interstate 240]] interchange.&lt;ref name=SCRouting&gt;{{cite web | title=Sam Cooper Boulevard from East Parkway to Interstate-40/Interstate-240 Interchange | url=http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&amp;source=s_d&amp;saddr=Sam+Cooper+Blvd&amp;daddr=35.152881,-89.882884&amp;geocode=FSRTGAIdgv6i-g%3B&amp;hl=en&amp;mra=dme&amp;mrcr=0&amp;mrsp=1&amp;sz=16&amp;sll=35.150021,-89.892626&amp;sspn=0.010878,0.022745&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=h&amp;ll=35.150021,-89.892626&amp;spn=0.087022,0.181961&amp;z=13 | publisher=Google Maps | accessdate=2009-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The road was originally planned in the 1950s. It was proposed as a segment of I-40 that would intersect the center of Memphis and continue west to [[Arkansas]]. The proposed route would have cut through [[Overton Park]], an old forest public park in Memphis. Following a [[United States Supreme Court]] decision in 1971 the route was revised, I-40 was routed around Memphis in the north and plans of routing an Interstate highway through the city were abandoned. Ownership of the completed segments of the highway was transferred to the City of Memphis.&lt;ref name=SupCourt&gt;{{cite web | title=Citizens to Preserve Overton Park v. Volpe | url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=401&amp;page=402 | work=U.S. Supreme Court, 401 U.S. 402 | publisher=FindLaw.com | date=March 2, 1971 | accessdate=2009-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a road that is owned and maintained by the City of Memphis, no route number is assigned to Sam Cooper Boulevard.&lt;ref name=ISG40&gt;{{cite web | title=Interstate Business Routes - Business Route 40 | url=http://www.interstate-guide.com/business-routes/bus40.html | publisher=Interstate-Guide.com | date=2008-10-08 | accessdate=2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{TOCLimit}}

==History==

===Proposed route===
[[File:Memphis, Tennessee 1955 Yellow Book.jpg|thumb|[[Interstate 40 in Tennessee|I-40]]/[[Interstate 240 (Tennessee)|I-240]] planned routes (1955)]]
In the 1950s, [[Interstate 240 (Tennessee)|Interstate 240]] (I-240) was planned as a complete loop around Memphis, consisting of a southern leg and a northern leg. [[Interstate 40 in Tennessee|Interstate 40]] (I-40) was proposed to be routed through the center of the City of Memphis and to continue west into [[Arkansas]] over the [[Hernando de Soto Bridge]], which was opened in 1973 and carries the traffic on modern I-40 over the [[Mississippi River]]. The I-240 loop was planned to route traffic not destined for Memphis around the city and to improve the flow of increasing traffic. The proposed I-240 loop would connect westbound and eastbound traffic to I-40 and southbound and northbound traffic to [[Interstate 55]] (I-55).&lt;ref name=ShellMap/&gt;&lt;ref name=1stNatBankMap&gt;{{Cite document
  | title = Memphis and Vicinity Map by First National Bank of Memphis
  | place = Memphis, Tennessee
  | publisher = Graphic Publications, a Division of General Publishing Co., Inc.
  | year = 1971
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

What is now known as Sam Cooper Boulevard was planned as an extension of I-40, intersecting Memphis and distributing eastbound and westbound traffic with a destination in Memphis within the city.&lt;ref name=ShellMap/&gt;&lt;ref name=1stNatBankMap/&gt; After a U.S. Supreme Court ruling stopped the plans to complete the section of I-40 cutting through Memphis in 1971, I-40 was re-routed.&lt;ref name=SupCourt/&gt; The routing of modern I-40 coincides with the proposed routing of the northern leg of I-240.&lt;ref name=ShellMap/&gt;&lt;ref name=1stNatBankMap/&gt;&lt;ref name=McNally/&gt; Instead of the proposed I-240 loop around Memphis, the modern routing designates I-240 as the southern leg of the loop and I-40 as the northern leg of the loop.&lt;ref name=McNally/&gt;

From the west to the east, the proposed routing of Sam Cooper Boulevard coincides with the route of modern I-40 from the Hernando de Soto Bridge in [[Downtown Memphis, Tennessee|downtown Memphis]] to the modern I-40/I-240 interchange west of North Bellevue Boulevard in [[Midtown, Memphis|midtown Memphis]]. East of the I-40/I-240 interchange, the proposed route of Sam Cooper Boulevard would have been routed almost due east for circa {{convert|1.2|mi|km|0}}, parallel to and south of Overton Avenue and north of Peach Avenue until it reached Evergreen Street. From there, it would have continued northeast for about {{convert|0.5|mi|m|-1}} to reach the intersection of Galloway Avenue and North Mc Lean Boulevard. From there, the route would have continued roughly to the east, parallel to and about {{convert|.2|mi|m|-1}} south of North Parkway, just south of the [[Memphis Zoo]] and cutting through the northern portion of [[Overton Park]], to connect to the western terminus of modern Sam Cooper Boulevard at East Parkway North.&lt;ref name=ShellMap&gt;{{Cite document
  | title = Shell - Street Guide and Metropolitan Map of Memphis
  | place = [[Chicago, Illinois|Chicago]], [[Illinois]]
  | publisher = The H. M. Gousha Company
  | year = 1963
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=1stNatBankMap/&gt; At the western terminus of Sam Cooper Boulevard there is a concurrency of East Parkway North with [[U.S. Route 70]], [[U.S. Route 79]] for {{convert|1.2|mi|km|0}} south of Summer Avenue and north of Union Avenue. East Parkway North also concurs with [[List of state routes in Tennessee|Tennessee State Route 277]].&lt;ref name=GoogleEP/&gt;

===Namesake===
In 1968, the road was named after Sam Cooper, a Memphis businessman and longtime president of the Humko Corporation, a refinery of vegetable oils. He also was the vice president of the [[Federal Reserve Bank]] of Memphis. Cooper used his wealth to support [[St. Jude Children's Research Hospital]] and the [[University of Tennessee Health Science Center|University of Tennessee Medical School]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=ISJL: Digital Archive - Memphis | url=http://www.isjl.org/history/archive/tn/memphis.html | publisher=The Goldring/Woldenberg Institute of Southern Jewish Life | year=2006 | accessdate=2009-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=A Biblical People in the Bible Belt: The Jewish Community of Memphis, Tennessee |last=Lewis |first=Selma S. |year=1998 |publisher=Mercer University Press |location=[[Macon, Georgia|Macon]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] |isbn=0-86554-602-9 |page=130}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Citizen protests===
{{wide image|Sam Cooper Blvd USGS 1986 Topo map panorama 2.png|2300px|Proposed route of Sam Cooper Blvd. through Memphis (Source: [[United States Geological Survey|USGS]])|400px|right}}
In 1971, a [[United States Supreme Court]] ruling stopped an extension of I-40 through Overton Park.&lt;ref name=SupCourt/&gt; Sam Cooper Boulevard was originally planned as an extension of I-40 to intersect the City of Memphis.&lt;ref name=ShellMap/&gt;&lt;ref name=1stNatBankMap/&gt; The proposed route was completed as proposed east of North Highland Street and west of I-240 in [[Berclair, Memphis|Berclair]], in the northeastern quadrant of Memphis. The portion of Sam Cooper Boulevard west of North Highland Street was never built as planned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Interstate 240 Tennessee | url=http://www.interstate-guide.com/i-240_tn.html | publisher=Interstate-Guide.com | accessdate=2009-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The unbuilt portion west of East Parkway North was not completed because it was proposed to go through Overton Park, the Memphis Zoo, and several historic neighborhoods of Memphis. Citizens residing in the neighborhoods of midtown Memphis along the route of the proposed highway were able to stop the route cutting through the old forest of Overton Park in the lawsuit [[Citizens to Preserve Overton Park v. Volpe]].&lt;ref name=SupCourt/&gt;

Once the case was decided by the United States Supreme Court, the ownership of the completed segments of Sam Cooper Boulevard was given to the City of Memphis.&lt;ref name=SupCourt/&gt; Instead of following the planned route cutting through the center of Memphis, I-40 was routed around Memphis in the north. The new routing of I-40 to the north of Memphis follows the proposed northern leg of the I-240 loop.&lt;ref name=ShellMap/&gt;&lt;ref name=1stNatBankMap/&gt;&lt;ref name=McNally/&gt;

Construction of the route segment of Sam Cooper Boulevard west of North Highland Street and east of East Parkway North began in 2001 and was completed in 2003. The construction did not follow the originally proposed expressway design for the road but implemented a parkway design with at-grade intersections, a raised median, traffic lights and sidewalks for pedestrians.

===21st century===

====Extension to East Parkway====
[[File:Sam Cooper Blvd Tillman W.jpg|thumb|Tillman St intersection (2009)]]
In 2001, the City of Memphis began construction on an extension of Sam Cooper Boulevard west of the North Highland Street exit. After completion of the first phase of construction, Sam Cooper Boulevard transitioned into Broad Avenue between North Holmes Street and Vandalia Street, about {{convert|.4|mi|m|-1}} west of North Highland Street.&lt;ref name=McNally&gt;{{Cite book
  | title = Memphis, Tennessee City Map
  | place = [[Skokie, Illinois|Skokie]], [[Illinois]]
  | publisher = [[Rand McNally]]
  | year = 2003
  | isbn = 0-528-97484-X
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The route coinciding with Broad Avenue had several intersections with traffic signals and two major railroad crossings, creating traffic congestion at peak times. The extension of Sam Cooper Boulevard was routed about {{convert|300|to(-)|400|ft|m|-1|lk=on}} south of Broad Avenue. Several of the intersections were eliminated, a viaduct was constructed to avoid the railroad crossings and the route was extended to East Parkway North.

The original route east of North Highland Street, was designed as a six-lane expressway without intersections, traffic signals and without sidewalks for pedestrians, allowing only motorized traffic on the road. The extension of Sam Cooper Boulevard west of the North Highland Street exit was constructed as a six-lane controlled-access parkway. Pedestrians are allowed on the route on sidewalks installed on both sides of the parkway west of Vandalia Street, located about {{convert|1400|ft|m}} west of North Highland Street. The median is raised and there are at-grade intersections present equipped with traffic signals and pedestrian crossings.&lt;ref name=SCRouting/&gt; The segment of Sam Cooper Boulevard west of North Highland Street and east of East Parkway North was completed in 2003.

====Random shootings at cars====
In 2004, it was reported by local newsmedia that several cars driving on Sam Cooper Boulevard had been shot at randomly in the section west of Tillman Street and east of North Hollywood Street in the [[Binghampton, Memphis|Binghampton]] neighborhood. The [[Memphis Police Department]] (MPD) reported 13 shootings between August and October of that year. A spokesman of the MPD stated that only vehicle damage had occurred and that no persons were hurt in the shootings.&lt;ref name=WMC13&gt;{{cite web | title=And then there were 13 | url=http://www.wmcstations.com/Global/story.asp?S=2437557 | work= | publisher=WMC-TV, Action News 5 | date=2004-10-15 | accessdate=2009-05-18}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police recovered a nine millimeter bullet from the front door of one vehicle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Four new reports about vehicles being shot at on Sam Cooper Boulevard | url=http://www.wmctv.com/Global/story.asp?S=2426650 | publisher=WMC-TV, Action News 5 | date=2004-10-13 | accessdate=2009-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; A special police task force was assigned to the case.&lt;ref name=WMC13/&gt; It is not known if the shooter was caught.

====Revitalization attempts====
[[File:Broad Ave Binghampton Memphis TN 3.jpg|thumb|Broad Avenue (2010)]]
In 2006, citizens from the Binghampton neighborhood of Memphis voiced concerns about negative effects that the completion of the western portion of Sam Cooper Boulevard has had on the community. Claims were made that construction of the road between North Highland Street and East Parkway North cut the Binghampton area in half by creating &quot;high-speed traffic&quot; and &quot;confusing traffic patterns&quot;. It was mentioned that the routing of Sam Cooper Boulevard to the south of Broad Avenue had &quot;effectively made&quot; the circa {{convert|1.4|mi|km}} long stretch of Broad Avenue a &quot;ghost town&quot;, creating vacant lots in the partly industrial area and an unsafe neighborhood.&lt;ref name=MemFlyer&gt;{{cite web | title=Bringing Back Binghamton | url=http://www.memphisflyer.com/memphis/Content?oid=oid%3A12031 | author=Mary Cashiola | publisher=Memphis Flyer | date= 2006-02-10 | accessdate=2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Memphis Flyer]] cites Robert Montague, executive director of the Binghampton Development Corporation: &quot;When they built Sam Cooper, this area really got buried&quot;. Citizens suggested changes in the zoning and a re-design of the Broad Avenue area north of Sam Cooper Boulevard and south of Summer Avenue to re-vitalize that part of the neighborhood and attract business and residents.&lt;ref name=MemFlyer/&gt; The following year, trees and shrubs were planted alongside Sam Cooper Boulevard and in the median west of North Highland Street. A few decorative flowerbeds were also installed in the median of the road to enhance the parkway design of the road.

==Exit list==

===Proposed exits===
[[File:Sam Cooper Blvd Ped E Exit Graham.jpg|thumb|Exit #8 at N Graham St (2009)]]
Sam Cooper Boulevard is owned and maintained by the City of Memphis.&lt;ref name=SupCourt/&gt; No route number is assigned to Sam Cooper Boulevard and it is not a designated [[business route]] for interstate traffic headed for Memphis.&lt;ref name=ISG40/&gt; The [[exit number]]ing system on Sam Cooper Boulevard has not been changed since the route was planned. The exits are still numbered as if I-40 ran along Sam Cooper Boulevard as it was proposed to be built straight through Memphis to connect to Arkansas over the Hernando de Soto Bridge.

The exits for I-40 along the proposed route segment through the center of Memphis, west of East Parkway North, that was never completed were planned in downtown Memphis (planned as exit&amp;nbsp;1), at Danny Thomas Boulevard (planned as exit&amp;nbsp;2), west of North Bellevue Boulevard as an interchange with modern day I-240 (planned as exit&amp;nbsp;3) and at Stonewall Street in the [[Evergreen, Memphis|Evergreen District]] of midtown Memphis (planned as exit&amp;nbsp;4). I-40 exits were proposed at East Parkway North (planned as exit&amp;nbsp;5) and Tillman Street (planned as exit&amp;nbsp;6).&lt;ref name=1stNatBankMap/&gt;

The planned exit&amp;nbsp;1 along Sam Cooper Boulevard exists as exit&amp;nbsp;1 and exit&amp;nbsp;1A of modern day I-40 in downtown Memphis just south of the [[Pyramid Arena]]. Exit&amp;nbsp;1 serves traffic to and from North Riverside Drive and Front Street; at exit&amp;nbsp;1A westbound traffic exits to North 2nd Street and eastbound traffic enters I-40 from North 3rd Street. Planned exit&amp;nbsp;2 coincides with modern exits&amp;nbsp;1B–D on I-40 at Danny Thomas Boulevard. Planned exit&amp;nbsp;3 exists as exit&amp;nbsp;1E on modern I-40 at the I-40/I-240 interchange west of North Bellevue Boulevard in the [[Medical District, Memphis|Medical district]] of Memphis. Planned exit&amp;nbsp;4 at Stonewall Street was never constructed. Planned exit&amp;nbsp;5 is an at-grade intersection with traffic signals at the western terminus of Sam Cooper Boulevard at East Parkway North, and planned exit&amp;nbsp;6 is an at-grade intersection with traffic lights at Tillman Street. Exits&amp;nbsp;7–9 and Exits&amp;nbsp;10A and 10B were constructed as proposed.&lt;ref name=McNally/&gt;

===Existing exits===
[[File:Overton Park Billboard Sam Cooper at E Parkway Memphis TN 5.jpg|thumb|Western terminus (2010)]]
The following table lists the existing exits and intersections of Sam Cooper Boulevard as of 2003 from west to east.&lt;ref name=SCRouting/&gt; {{jcttop|exit|state=TN|county=Shelby}}
{{jctint|exit
|state=TN
|location_special=[[Midtown, Memphis|Midtown]]
|mile=0.0
|exit=
|road={{jct|state=TN|US|70|US|79|SR|277|name3=[[East Parkway (Memphis, Tennessee)|East Parkway North]]}}
|notes=Western terminus; at-grade intersection with traffic signal; planned as exit&amp;nbsp;5}}
{{jctint|exit
|state=TN
|location_special=[[Binghampton, Memphis|Binghampton]]
|lspan=3
|mile=0.2
|exit=
|road=North Hollywood Street
|notes=At-grade intersection with traffic signal}}
{{jctint|exit
|mile=0.4
|exit=
|road=North Bingham Street
|notes=At-grade intersection with traffic signal}}
{{jctint|exit
|mile=1.2
|exit=
|road=Tillman Street
|notes=At-grade intersection with traffic signal; planned as exit&amp;nbsp;6}}
{{jctint|exit
|state=TN
|location_special=[[Highland Heights, Memphis|Highland Heights]]
|lspan=2
|mile=2.1
|exit=7
|road=North Highland Street
|notes=}}
{{jctint|exit
|mile=3.1
|exit=8
|road=North Graham Street
|notes=}}
{{jctint|exit
|state=TN
|location_special=[[Berclair, Memphis|Berclair]]
|lspan=3
|mile=4.2
|exit=9
|road=North Perkins Road
|notes=}}
{{jctint|exit
|mile=5.5
|exit=10A
|road={{jct|state=TN|I|240|dir1=south|locatoin1=[[Jackson, Mississippi|Jackson]]}}
|notes=}}
{{jctint|exit
|mile=5.8
|exit=10B
|road={{jct|state=TN|I|40|dir1=west|location1= [[Little Rock, Arkansas|Little Rock]]}}
|notes=Eastern terminus at I-40/I- 240 interchange}}
{{jctbtm}}

==Points of interest==
{{wide image|Sam Cooper Blvd Broad Ave USGS 1986 DOQ.png|750px|Sam Cooper Blvd. transition into Broad Ave. (Source: [[United States Geological Survey|USGS]], 1986)|500px|right}}
Points of interest along Sam Cooper Boulevard (west to east).

* [[Memphis Zoo]], {{convert|.5|mi|m|-1}} west of the western terminus
* [[Memphis Brooks Museum of Art]], {{convert|.5|mi|m|-1}} west of the western terminus
* [[Overton Park]] at the western terminus
* [[Memphis National Cemetery]], {{convert|2|mi|km|0}} north of Highland Street exit
* Site of the first [[Berclair, Memphis#First Holiday Inn hotel|Holiday Inn]] hotel, {{convert|.5|mi|m|-1}} east of Perkins Road exit
* [[Wolf River (Tennessee)|Wolf River]] at the eastern terminus
* [[Shelby Farms|Shelby Farms Park]], {{convert|2|mi|km|0}} east of the eastern terminus

==See also==
* [[Interstate 40 in Tennessee]]
* [[Interstate 240 (Tennessee)]]

==References==
{{Commons category}}
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://ww2.tdot.state.tn.us/tsw/smartmap.htm?city=Memphis TDOT smartway Information System]
* [http://www.tdot.state.tn.us/cctv/cctvmemp/CCTV_65.asp TDOT smartway traffic camera at Sam Cooper Boulevard and Perkins Street]
* [http://www.tdot.state.tn.us/cctv/cctvmemp/CCTV_64.asp TDOT smartway traffic camera at Sam Cooper Boulevard and Graham Street]
* [http://www.tdot.state.tn.us/cctv/cctvmemp/CCTV_63.asp TDOT smartway traffic camera at Sam Cooper Boulevard and High Point Terrace]
* [http://www.tdot.state.tn.us/cctv/cctvmemp/CCTV_62.asp TDOT smartway traffic camera at Sam Cooper Boulevard and Highland Street]

{{Memphis, Tennessee}}

{{Roads of Memphis}}

[[Category:Transportation in Memphis, Tennessee]]</text>
      <sha1>pxbnb02pqkk7k4ppd6kku9av3eik89k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Symphonic Fantasies</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35321177</id>
    <revision>
      <id>543297703</id>
      <parentid>543292252</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-10T23:13:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GA bot</username>
        <id>11344024</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Adding Good Article icon</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37628">{{good article}}
{{Infobox orchestra concert
| concert_name = Symphonic Fantasies: Music from Square Enix
| image        = SymphonicFantasies-banner.png
| orchestra    = [[WDR Symphony Orchestra Cologne]]
| choir        = WDR Radio Choir Cologne
| conductor    = [[Arnie Roth]]
| composer     = [[Jonne Valtonen]], [[Nobuo Uematsu]], [[Hiroki Kikuta]], [[Yoko Shimomura]], [[Yasunori Mitsuda]]
| arranger     = Jonne Valtonen, Roger Wanamo
| support_act  = [[Benyamin Nuss]], [[Rony Barrak]]
| venue        = [[Cologne]] ([[Germany]]), Cologne Philharmonic Hall
| date         = September 11~12, 2009&lt;br/&gt;January 7~8, 2012&lt;br/&gt;June 9, 2012&lt;br /&gt;July 6~7, 2012
| producer     = [[Thomas Böcker]] ([[Merregnon Studios]])
| album        = ''Symphonic Fantasies'' (2010)&lt;br /&gt;''Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo'' (2012)
| last_concert = [[Symphonic Shades - Hülsbeck in Concert|Symphonic Shades]]&lt;br&gt;(August 23, 2008)
| this_concert = Symphonic Fantasies&lt;br&gt;(September 12, 2009)
| next_concert = [[Symphonic Legends - Music from Nintendo|Symphonic Legends]]&lt;br&gt;(September 23, 2010)
}}

'''''Symphonic Fantasies: Music from Square Enix''''' was an award winning symphonic tribute concert held in Cologne, Germany on the September 12, 2009 featuring [[video game music]] from Japanese game developer [[Square Enix]]. The concert featured symphonic movements based on the ''[[Kingdom Hearts]]'' series, ''[[Secret of Mana]]'', the ''[[Chrono (series)|Chrono]]'' series, and the ''[[Final Fantasy]]'' series. The concert was produced and directed by [[Thomas Böcker]], with arrangements provided by Finnish composer and musician [[Jonne Valtonen]] with assistance by Roger Wanamo. Due to overwhelming demand, a second concert was necessitated at the König-Pilsener-Arena in [[Oberhausen]], on September 11, 2009. The concert was performed by The WDR Radio Orchestra Cologne and the WDR Radio Choir Cologne under conduction from Arnie Roth, with guest performers [[Rony Barrak]] and [[Benyamin Nuss]] joining the orchestra. ''Symphonic Fantasies'' was broadcasted over radio on the WDR4 station and streamed live video online.

In 2012, four new performances were scheduled, taking stage in Tokyo, Stockholm, and a reprise in Cologne. These performances featured slightly modified versions of the original arrangements, and like the original concerts, were sold out. The original concert and the Tokyo concert both sparked the release of an album. These albums, along with the concerts themselves, were heavily praised, both for the quality of the performance and for the quality of Valtonen's arrangements, which overlaid themes from multiple pieces rather than relying on a traditional medley.

==Concerts==

===Production===
[[Thomas Böcker]] and then [[WDR Symphony Orchestra Cologne]] director Winfried Fechner began collaborating on orchestrated video game concerts in 2007, after Fechner had attended the ''[[Symphonic Game Music Concerts|Fifth Symphonic Game Music Concert]]'' held in Leipzig.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOfechnerint&quot;/&gt; As their ideas and plans materialized, three projects were set in motion to determine the interest of a younger audience in classical music performance and the aptitude of the WDR orchestra in focusing on a new source of compositions. The first project was ''PROMS: That's Sound, That's Rhythm'', held in early 2008, featuring a mixture of classical works and video game music, ranging from works by [[Ralph Vaughan Williams]] and [[Morton Gould]] as well as arrangements of music from video games such as ''[[Shenmue]]'' and ''[[Castlevania]]'' previously featured in the ''Symphonic Game Music Concerts''. The second project, held in August 2008, was a composer specific concert titled ''[[Symphonic Shades - Hülsbeck in Concert]]'', focusing entirely on the works of German video game composer [[Chris Hülsbeck]].&lt;ref name=&quot;semojan09&quot;/&gt; After the concert, Fechner revealed in an interview the existence of the third project, saying that he and Böcker would be involved in another concert of video game music the following September.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fechner08int&quot;/&gt; The third project was to be a concert of music from one game company, focusing on multiple titles released by the same developer.&lt;ref name=&quot;semojan09&quot;/&gt; This company was later confirmed to be [[Square Enix]] when Fechner announced ''Symphonic Fantasies'' as a video game music concert to take place on September 12, 2009. A website was set up for announcements, interviews and other concert information.&lt;ref name=&quot;OffSiteApr09&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Thomas Boecker.jpg|thumb|150px|Producer [[Thomas Böcker]] in 2010]]
Böcker later explained that the decision to focus on Square Enix was made due to the large library of games to choose from, all of which he felt had a distinct sound, and many of which were very well known in Germany. An emphasis was put on balancing out the concert program and the arrangements, so that the music would appeal to first-time listeners, classical music fans, and longtime gamers. The titles chosen to be featured in the concert were ''[[Kingdom Hearts (video game)|Kingdom Hearts]]'' and ''[[Kingdom Hearts II]]'' from the ''[[Kingdom Hearts]]'' series, ''[[Secret of Mana]]'', ''[[Chrono Trigger]]'' and ''[[Chrono Cross]]'' from the ''[[Chrono (series)|Chrono]]'' series, and the ''[[Final Fantasy]]'' series. In order to select the pieces presented, the original composers were consulted to assemble a list of their personal favorites.&lt;ref name=&quot;semojan09&quot;/&gt; The composers were [[Yoko Shimomura]] for the [[music of Kingdom Hearts|music of ''Kingdom Hearts'']], [[Hiroki Kikuta]] for the [[music of the Mana series|music of ''Secret of Mana'']], [[Yasunori Mitsuda]] for the [[music of Chrono Trigger|music of ''Chrono Trigger'']] and [[music of Chrono Cross|''Cross'']], and [[Nobuo Uematsu]] for the [[music of the Final Fantasy series|music of the ''Final Fantasy'' series]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OffSiteJul09&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Jonne Valtonen Official.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Arranger [[Jonne Valtonen]] in 2010]]
For the concert, [[Jonne Valtonen]] returned as the lead arranger; he had previously been the arranger for video game music concerts since 2005, including ''Symphonic Shades''. He was given complete freedom to arrange the music based on the general outline given to him by Böcker. Valtonen spent six months on the arrangements, during which Valtonen studied each song and referred to the composer's original intended expression.&lt;ref name=&quot;semojan09&quot;/&gt; No Japanese guest arrangers were used for this concert in order to maintain a unique European take on the source material, but Valtonen brought in former classmate and close friend Roger Wanamo to assist on the arrangement of the music from the ''Chrono'' games.&lt;ref name=&quot;semojan09&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;semoWanamoint&quot;/&gt; This was Wanamo's first time arranging video game music.&lt;ref name=&quot;semoWanamoint&quot;/&gt; On March 9, 2009 It was also announced that Valtonen had additionally been commissioned to compose an original fanfare to be played at the start of the concert, and with a video preview of his composition was released.&lt;ref name=&quot;OffSiteApr09&quot;/&gt;

The arrangements in the concert were structured as suites, dubbed &quot;Fantasies&quot;, with multiple songs from each game series positioned and arranged together to tell melodic stories rather than using the conventional medley structure more commonly heard in video game music arrangements.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;/&gt; The fanfare, titled ''Fanfare Overture'', was done in a style of traditional fanfares with some accentuated textures in order to introduce all the elements of the orchestra. The ''Kingdom Hearts'' suite featured seven songs from the two titles, and was arranged as a romantic piano concerto.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;osvfantasies&quot;/&gt; ''Secret of Mana'' featured six songs featured in the original game.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;/&gt; The arrangement made use of notable unique techniques in order to replicate the atmosphere found in the original game; for example, the choir was used to create &quot;sound effects&quot; such as floor vibration by foot stomping and simulating distant rain with their voices.&lt;ref name=&quot;osvfantasies&quot;/&gt; The ''Chrono'' suite featured ten songs from ''Chrono Trigger'' and ''Chrono Cross''.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;/&gt; The suite featured a &quot;crossing&quot; of melodies, in which multiple melodies would be layered on top of one another, resulting in different well-known themes performed simultaneously in harmony.&lt;ref name=&quot;osvfantasies&quot;/&gt; The ''Final Fantasy'' suite contained eight songs from the first seven titles in the series. Unlike the other suites, it featured a simpler structure, focusing more on each individual theme rather than overlapping multiple pieces.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;/&gt;

===Original performance===
[[Image:Symphonicfantasies.jpg|thumb|250px|''Symphonic Fantasies'' performers at the end of the September 12, 2009 concert]]
The orchestra received about two weeks of rehearsal time prior to their performances, more than any other game concert before.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOdec09&quot;/&gt; The concert was originally scheduled to be performed on September 12, 2009 in the Cologne Philharmonic Hall in [[Cologne]], but once the tickets were sold out, a second performance was added for September 11, 2009 at the [[König Pilsener Arena]] in [[Oberhausen]]. Ticket sales for the initial concert began on January 17, and half of them were sold within a week, with the remainder sold by April 2, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;OffSiteApr09&quot;/&gt; The concert was preceded by a Meet and Greet session that included the original composers as well as the arrangement team and guest artists for the show. The concerts were performed by the WDR Symphony Orchestra Cologne and WDR Radio Choir Cologne, conducted by [[Arnie Roth]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OffSiteJul09&quot;/&gt;

{{listen
| filename    = Symphonic Fantasies - Kingdom Hearts Suite sample.ogg
| title       = Kingdom Hearts suite sample
| description = Sample of the introduction of the ''Kingdom Hearts'' suite, featuring [[Benyamin Nuss]] on the piano.
| format      = [[Ogg]]
| pos         = left
}}
Before each suite, the moderator would introduce the upcoming musical piece, as well as introduce the composer in attendance. Each &quot;Fantasy&quot; lasted for more than 15 minutes each. The ''Kingdom Hearts'' suite featured solo pianist [[Benyamin Nuss]]. For the ''Chrono'' suite, [[Rony Barrak]] joined the orchestra and performed on his signature [[darbuka]]. A surprise encore was performed after the final suite, which took the form of a medley of the final boss themes from each game. Rony Barrak returned on stage as a soloist for the encore.&lt;ref name=&quot;osvfantasies&quot;/&gt; No video screens or other form of tools were used during the concert, with only minimal lighting effects at certain parts for atmosphere being employed. The event was broadcast live on the WDR4 radio station, as well as through an online video stream, enabling a worldwide audience to watch the concert.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;/&gt;

===2012 performances===
Three years after the original performance, on September 14, 2011, during the [[Tokyo Game Show]], Square Enix Japan announced on their website that the ''Symphonic Fantasies'' concert would be performed in Tokyo on January 7 and 8, 2012. They also announced that Benyamin Nuss, Rony Barrak, Jonne Valtonen, Roger Wanamo and Thomas Böcker would be in attendance. Böcker returned to produce the event, and Nuss and Barrak returned as soloists.&lt;ref name=&quot;JapanAnnounce&quot;/&gt;

The concerts were held at the [[Tokyo Bunka Kaikan]] Main Hall, and were performed by the [[Tokyo Philharmonic Orchestra]] and the Tokyo Philharmonic Chorus. The concerts were conducted by Eckehard Stier. In addition to the originally announced attendees, in attendance were guest of honors Hiroki Kikuta, Yoko Shimomura, and Yasunori Mitsuda, as well as guests such as video game composers [[Takenobu Mitsuyoshi]], [[Yuzo Koshiro]], [[Masashi Hamauzu]], and [[Mahito Yokota]]. The concerts were featured extensively in the February issue of ''[[Famitsu]]'' as well as on their official website.&lt;ref name=&quot;Famitsureport&quot;/&gt; ''Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo'' was the first all-European video game concert production to take place in Japan. More than 4600 fans were in attendance, and the concerts sold out within days.&lt;ref name=&quot;JPGreview&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOBokint12&quot;/&gt; The arrangements and tempo were slightly modified from the original concert, and the encore was changed to add elements from an additional ''Final Fantasy'' song.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFjapanreview&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MAZjapan&quot;/&gt;

At the conclusion of the ''[[Symphonic Odysseys - Tribute to Nobuo Uematsu|Symphonic Odysseys]]'' concert in Cologne by Merregnon Studios on July 9, 2011, the WDR announced that ''Symphonic Fantasies'' would return to Germany in 2012. The concerts were held on July 6 and 7, 2012 at the Cologne Philharmonic Hall. The concert was again performed by the WDR Radio Orchestra Cologne and WDR Radio Choir Cologne, conducted by Niklas Wíllen. On March 26, 2012, Merregnon Studios announced that ''Symphonic Fantasies'' would also be performed at the [[Stockholm Concert Hall]] on June 9, 2012. The concert was performed by [[Royal Stockholm Philharmonic Orchestra]] and Katarina Choir, conducted by Andreas Hanson.&lt;ref name=&quot;osvfantasies2012&quot;/&gt; Like the other concerts, the 2012 European concerts were sold out.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOBokint12&quot;/&gt;

===Set List===
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot;
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|#
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Suite
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Original pieces&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;/&gt;
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1.
| &quot;Fanfare Overture&quot;
| 
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 2.
| &quot;Fantasy I: Kingdom Hearts&quot;
| &quot;Dearly Beloved&quot;, &quot;Sora&quot;, &quot;Hand in Hand&quot;, &quot;Kairi&quot;, &quot;The Other Promise&quot;, &quot;Happy Holidays!&quot;, and &quot;A Fight to the Death&quot;
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 3.
| &quot;Fantasy II: Secret of Mana&quot;
| &quot;Fear of the Heavens&quot;, &quot;Into the Thick of it&quot;, &quot;Eternal Recurrence&quot;, &quot;The Oracle&quot;, &quot;Prophecy&quot;, and &quot;Phantom and... A Rose...&quot;
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 4.
| &quot;Fantasy III: Chrono Trigger/Chrono Cross&quot;
| &quot;A Premonition&quot;, &quot;Scars of Time&quot;, &quot;Chrono Trigger&quot;, &quot;Battle with Magus&quot;, &quot;Peaceful Days&quot;, &quot;Gale&quot;, &quot;Brink of Death&quot;, &quot;Prisoners of Fate&quot;, &quot;Outskirts of Time&quot;, and &quot;Frog's Theme&quot;
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 5.
| &quot;Fantasy IV: Final Fantasy&quot;
| &quot;Prelude&quot;, &quot;Fighting&quot;, &quot;One-Winged Angel&quot;, &quot;Swing de Chocobo&quot;, &quot;Phantom Forest&quot;, &quot;Battle at the Big Bridge&quot;, &quot;Final Fantasy&quot;, and &quot;Bombing Mission&quot;
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 6.
| &quot;Encore&quot;
| &quot;Destati&quot;, &quot;Meridian Dance&quot;, &quot;Lavos's Theme&quot;, and &quot;One-Winged Angel&quot; (and &quot;Dancing Mad&quot; in 2012 concerts)
|}

==Albums==
{{Infobox album
| Name        = Symphonic Fantasies
| Type        = Live
| Artist      = WDR Radio Orchestra Cologne, WDR Radio Choir Cologne, [[Rony Barrak]], [[Benyamin Nuss]]
| Cover       = Cover_art_for_Symphonic_Fantasies.jpg
| Released    = September 17, 2010
| Recorded    = September 12, 2009
| Genre       = [[Classical music|Classical]], [[Video game music]]
| Length      = 1:12:30
| Label       = [[Decca Records|Decca]] (Universal Music)
| Producer    = [[Thomas Böcker]]
}}
The September 12, 2009 concert in Cologne was recorded and released as an album titled ''Symphonic Fantasies''. It was announced to be in production on April 15, 2010, and made available for pre-order.&lt;!--noref--&gt; In an interview, Fechner stated the album was being mixed and edited at a &quot;prestigious European studio&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOfechnerint2&quot;/&gt; This was later revealed to be [[Abbey Road Studios]] in London.&lt;ref name=maz/&gt; The album was first released in Japan on September 15, 2010, published by Square Enix Japan's own label under the auspices of [[Sony Music Entertainment Japan|Sony Music Distribution]]. The album was released in Europe on September 17, 2010, published by [[Decca Records]]. Both album versions feature identical track listings and production, with the only differences being the artwork and provided booklet. The artwork for the European album was designed by the German design house, schech, and features a cross between a violin and a game controller, while the Japanese cover has an image of a white book.&lt;ref name=maz /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFreview&quot;/&gt; Böcker produced the European album, and was a consultant for the production of the Japanese release.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFboeckerint&quot;/&gt;

The album does not contain the encore suite, which was released as a single on [[iTunes]] on December 14, 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFreview&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;itunesencore&quot;/&gt; The album's five tracks have a duration of 1:12:30, with the encore track bringing it to 1:20:56.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFreview&quot;/&gt; Upon release, it reach position #13 on the German classical [[Media Control Charts]] for sales in September 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;MCCsales&quot;/&gt; The Japanese release reached position #102 on the [[Oricon]] charts and stayed on the charts for one week.&lt;ref name=&quot;ORI&quot;/&gt; After the concert in Tokyo, a second album was released. Titled ''Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo'', the two-disc album is a recording of that performance, including the encore.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFjapanreview&quot;/&gt; The album, produced by Merregnon Studios and mixed by a team of sound engineers from Japan and Germany, was released on June 11, 2012. Its cover is a modified version of the original European album with a large red circle, and it includes a twenty-page booklet with comments from the original composers. The album's six tracks have a length of 1:20:50.&lt;ref name=&quot;MAZjapan&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot;
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|#
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Track name
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Performer
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Arranger
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Composer
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Length (Tokyo album)
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1.
| &quot;Fanfare Overture&quot;
| WDR Symphony Orchestra
| Jonne Valtonen
| Jonne Valtonen
| 3:12 (3:09)
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 2.
| &quot;Fantasy I: Kingdom Hearts&quot;
| WDR&amp;nbsp;Symphony&amp;nbsp;Orchestra&lt;br/&gt;Benyamin Nuss
| Jonne Valtonen
| Yoko Shimomura
| 15:28 (15:53)
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 3.
| &quot;Fantasy II: Secret of Mana&quot;
| WDR Symphony Orchestra&lt;br/&gt;WDR Radio Choir
| Jonne Valtonen
| Hiroki Kikuta
| 17:42 (18:54)
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 4.
| &quot;Fantasy III: Chrono&amp;nbsp;Trigger/Chrono&amp;nbsp;Cross&quot;
| WDR Symphony Orchestra&lt;br/&gt;Rony Barrak
| Jonne Valtonen&lt;br/&gt;Roger&amp;nbsp;Wanamo
| Yasunori Mitsuda
| 17:39 (16:36)
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 5.
| &quot;Fantasy IV: Final Fantasy&quot;
| WDR Symphony Orchestra&lt;br/&gt;WDR Radio Choir
| Jonne Valtonen
| Nobuo Uematsu
| 18:29 (18:37)
|-
!scope=&quot;row&quot; | 6.
| &quot;Encore: Final Boss Suite&quot;
| WDR Symphony Orchestra&lt;br/&gt;WDR Radio Choir&lt;br/&gt;Rony Barrak
| Jonne Valtonen
| Yoko Shimomura, Hiroki Kikuta, Yasunori Mitsuda, and Nobuo Uematsu
| 8:26 (7:41)
|}

==Reception==
The initial event received widespread critical acclaim, with much praise given to the focused presentation, deeply developed arrangements and evolution of the concept. Audun Sorlie of Original Sound Version stated that the concert &quot;exceeded all expectations&quot; and further added that the event was &quot;absolutely amazing&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;osvfantasies&quot;/&gt; Chris Greening of Square Enix Music Online concluded in his report that &quot;''Symphonic Fantasies'' ranks among the greatest musical and social experiences of my life. Each arrangement took listeners on an extended journey through the atmospheres, emotions, and melodies of their respective series.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;/&gt; Polish site GameMusic.net's Kamil Rojek said in his report that &quot;''Symphonic Fantasies'' is a significant turning point in the history of video game music concerts. It was a remarkable event that made great progress in breaking the boundaries between game music and traditional classical works.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GMreview&quot;/&gt;

The composers themselves expressed great regard for the concert and the arrangement. Yoko Shimomura noted she was extremely pleased with Valtonen's arrangement of Kingdom Hearts, feeling it &quot;very colorful and beautiful, just superb really&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOshimint&quot;/&gt; Hiroki Kikuta stated that Valtonen's arrangement &quot;defied the framework of regular orchestra and was a very experimental attempt,&quot; resulting in &quot;free and unbound expression&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOkikutaint&quot;/&gt; Yasunori Mitsuda expressed that he was &quot;really amazed by its fantastic quality&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOmitsint&quot;/&gt; and Nobuo Uematsu said that it was &quot;an exceptionally well-produced concert compared to most game concerts.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOuemint&quot;/&gt; The composers also voiced their desire to bring the concert to Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOdec09&quot;/&gt;

The ''Symphonic Fantasies'' album garnered universal praise upon its release. Patrick Gann of RPGFan said that it was &quot;the best game music arranged album of 2010. It may be the best in years, with the only things rivaling it being other recordings from the WDR.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFreview&quot;/&gt; Audun Sorlie of Original Sound Version called it &quot;the best symphonic game arrangement CD you can get your hands on,&quot; and further added &quot;for every game music fan out there, especially the ones with a taste for Square Enix, this is the definitive pick for you.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;OSValbumreview&quot;/&gt; Chris Greening of Square Enix Music Online gave the album the score of 10 out of 10, and stated that it &quot;offers a definitive tribute to Square Enix&quot; and &quot;certainly deserves a perfect score and an unconditional recommendation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOalbumreview&quot;/&gt; Benjamin Schmädig of the German site 4players.de said of the album &quot;''Symphonic Fantasies'' represents memories of great emotional moments. The orchestra and choir put in all their strength, all their subtlety in these moments.&quot; He further complimented Jonne Valtonen, saying that he &quot;knows exactly how to arrange the known motifs in such an imaginative way that they tell the familiar stories from scratch.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;4Plreview&quot;/&gt; Denis Brown of the German site OnlineWelten said that for Square Enix fans, it is an obligatory purchase.&lt;ref name=&quot;OWalbumreview&quot;/&gt;

''Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo'' was also praised upon release. Jayson Napolitano of [[Destructoid]] said that the &quot;arrangements are brilliant and are some of the best in the business,&quot; and that the addition of the encore was an improvement over the physical version of the original album, though he felt that the sound quality &quot;lacks some of the dynamics of the original release&quot; in the bass regions.&lt;ref name=&quot;DESjalbumreview&quot;/&gt; Joe Hammond of Square Enix Music Online found the opposite difference in the sound quality, finding that the deep drum sounds had more impact than in the first album.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOjalbumreview&quot;/&gt; Stephen Meyerink of RPGFan felt that &quot;the production and mastering on the album is stellar&quot;, and was pleased by the modifications to the arrangements between the original concert and the Tokyo concert, especially the slight increase in tempo.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFjapanreview&quot;/&gt; Audun Sorlie of Original Sound Version also praised the changes, not only in the tempo but also in the arrangements, noting the more integrated piano in the ''Kingdom Hearts'' suite and the more impressive brass section in the opening fanfare. He also noted that, unlike the original performance and album, the recording of live audience did not include any laughter when the chocobo theme interrupted &quot;One Winged Angel&quot; in the ''Final Fantasy'' suite. He concluded that the album was worth purchasing even for owners of the first album.&lt;ref name=&quot;OSVjalbumreview&quot;/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOfechnerint&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with WDR Radio Orchestra Manager Winfried Fechner |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/winfriedfechner.shtml |date=March 2010 |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120920100204/http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/winfriedfechner.shtml |archivedate=2012-09-20 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fechner08int&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Fünf (weitere) Fragen an: Winfried Fechner |url=http://www.symphonicshades.com/?p=84 |work=Symphonic Shades |publisher=[[Merregnon Studios]] |last=Fechner |first=Winfried |language=German |date=2008-09-09 |accessdate=2008-09-12 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080922051326/http://www.symphonicshades.com/?p=84 |archivedate=2008-09-22 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;OffSiteApr09&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Symphonic Fantasies |url=http://www.symphonicfantasies.com/ |publisher=Merregnon Studios |date=2009-04-02 |accessdate=2012-09-08 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090407002613/http://www.symphonicfantasies.com/ |archivedate=2009-04-07 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;semojan09&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Symphonic Fantasies Producer (January 2009) |url=http://squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/symphonicfantasiesboecker.shtml |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=January 2009 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120309022255/http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/symphonicfantasiesboecker.shtml |archivedate=2012-03-09 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;OffSiteJul09&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Symphonic Fantasies |url=http://www.symphonicfantasies.com/ |publisher=[[Merregnon Studios]] |date=2009-07-23 |accessdate=2012-09-08 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090729022629/http://www.symphonicfantasies.com/ |archivedate=2009-07-29 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;semoWanamoint&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Roger Wanamo (July 2011) |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/rogerwanamo.shtml |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=July 2011 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6Ebh5uWHK |archivedate=2013-02-21 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;osvfantasies&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Feels Like A Dream: Symphonic Fantasies Report |url=http://www.originalsoundversion.com/feels-like-a-dream-symphonic-fantasies-report/ |first=Audun |last=Sorlie |publisher=Original Sound Version |date=2009-09-17 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120723034742/http://www.originalsoundversion.com/feels-like-a-dream-symphonic-fantasies-report/ |archivedate=2012-07-23 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOreport&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/reports/symphonicfantasies.shtml |title=Symphonic Fantasies - Music from Square Enix :: Report by Chris |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=September 2009 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120417230938/http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/reports/symphonicfantasies.shtml |archivedate=2012-04-17 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOdec09&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Thomas Boecker of Symphonic Fantasies (December 2009) |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/thomasboecker5.shtml |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=December 2009 |accessdate=2012-04-03 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120919010418/http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/thomasboecker5.shtml |archivedate=2012-09-19 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;JapanAnnounce&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.square-enix.co.jp/music/sem/page/symphonic_fantasies/ |title=Symphonic Fantasies - Music from Square Enix |language=Japanese |date=September 2011 |publisher=[[Square Enix]] |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20121018201645/http://www.square-enix.co.jp/music/sem/page/symphonic_fantasies/ |archivedate=2012-10-18 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Famitsureport&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.famitsu.com/news/201201/08008116.html |title=『キングダム』、『聖剣2』、『クロノ』、『FF』……数々の名曲の調べがここに！　&quot;Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo&quot;開催 |date=January 2012 |language=Japanese |publisher=''[[Famitsu]]'' |accessdate=2012-04-03 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120324170658/http://www.famitsu.com/news/201201/08008116.html |archivedate=2012-03-24 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;JPGreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Reingehört! Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo |url=http://jpgames.de/2012/07/reingehort-symphonic-fantasies-tokyo/ |language=German |date=2012-07-09 |publisher=JPGames |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6EbknSm8N |archivedate=2013-02-21 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;osvfantasies2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Symphonic Fantasies Returns In Summer Of 2012! |url=http://www.originalsoundversion.com/16182/ |first=Audun |last=Sorlie |publisher=Original Sound Version |date=2012-03-27 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120718060209/http://www.originalsoundversion.com/16182/ |archivedate=2012-07-18 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOfechnerint2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with WDR Radio Orchestra Manager Winfried Fechner Part 2 |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/winfriedfechner2.shtml |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=March 2010 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120920095723/http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/winfriedfechner2.shtml |archivedate=2012-09-20 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=maz&gt;{{cite web |title=The CD: Symphonic Fantasies - music from Square Enix |url=http://www.maz-sound.com/Symphonic-Fantasies/en/The-CD/ |publisher=Maz Sound Tools |date=September 2010 |accessdate=2012-04-03 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100917021435/http://www.maz-sound.com/Symphonic-Fantasies/en/The-CD |archivedate=2010-09-17 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFboeckerint&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Thomas Boecker, Producer, WDR Orchestra Concerts |url=http://www.rpgfan.com/features/Symphonic_Fantasies_Interview/ |first=Patrick |last=Gann |publisher=RPGFan |date=2010-08-03 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100905091712/http://www.rpgfan.com/features/Symphonic_Fantasies_Interview/ |archivedate=2010-09-05 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rpgfan.com/soundtracks/symphonicfantasies/index.html |title=Symphonic Fantasies - music from Square Enix |publisher=RPGFan |last=Gann |first=Patrick |date=2010-09-10 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20130201062648/http://rpgfan.com/soundtracks/symphonicfantasies/index.html |archivedate=2013-02-01 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;itunesencore&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://itunes.apple.com/de/album/encore-final-boss-suite/id406330190?i=406330191 |title=Symphonic Fantasies: Encore (Final Boss Suite) - Single |date=2010-12-14 |publisher=[[iTunes]] |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6EcB3PMmU |archivedate=2013-02-21 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;MCCsales&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://magazin.klassik.com/charts/media-control.cfm?JAHR=2010&amp;MONAT=10 |title=Media Control Verkaufscharts |date=2010-10-19 |publisher=[[Media Control Charts]] |accessdate=2010-10-19 |deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ORI&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Symphonic Fantasies-music from Square Enix |url=http://www.oricon.co.jp/prof/artist/67810/products/music/880649/1/ |publisher=[[Oricon]] |accessdate=2013-03-10 |language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFjapanreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rpgfan.com/soundtracks/symphonicfantasies-tokyo/index.html |title=Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo |publisher=RPGFan |last=Meyerink |first=Stephen |date=2012-07-30 |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20130201053817/http://rpgfan.com/soundtracks/symphonicfantasies-tokyo/index.html |archivedate=2013-02-01 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;MAZjapan&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.maz-sound.com/Symphonic-Fantasies/en/The-CD/ |title=The CD: Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo - music from Square Enix |publisher=MAZ Sound Tools |accessdate=2013-02-21 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6EcCrdPmr |archivedate=2013-02-21 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOBokint12&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/thomasboecker9.shtml |title=Interview with Thomas Boecker: Going Universal (June 2012) |date=June 2012 |last=Greening |first=Chris |accessdate=2013-02-28 |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6EmC7ZMgh |archivedate=2013-02-28 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;4Plreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Special: Symphonic Fantasies |url=http://www.4players.de/4players.php/dispbericht/360/Special/14773/69653/0/Symphonic_Fantasies.html |first=Benjamin |last=Schmädig |language=German |publisher=4players.de |date=2010-03-10 |accessdate=2013-02-26 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110830064543/http://www.4players.de/4players.php/dispbericht/360/Special/14773/69653/0/Symphonic_Fantasies.html |archivedate=2011-08-30 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;GMreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Report: Symphonic Fantasies |url=http://www.gamemusic.net/article.php?id=470 |first=Kamil |last=Rojek |publisher=GameMusic.net |date=2009-09-12 |accessdate=2013-02-26 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20111217062853/http://www.gamemusic.net/article.php?id=470 |archivedate=2011-12-17 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOshimint&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Yoko Shimomura (September 2009) |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/yokoshimomura.shtml |first=Don |last=Kotowski |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=September 2009 |accessdate=2013-02-26 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120701151121/http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/yokoshimomura.shtml |archivedate=2012-07-01 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOkikutaint&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Hiroki Kikuta (November 2009) |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/hirokikikuta.shtml |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=November 2009 |accessdate=2013-02-26 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6EjI3XyBg |archivedate=2013-02-26 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOmitsint&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Yasunori Mitsuda (October 2009) |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/yasunorimitsuda2.shtml |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=October 2009 |accessdate=2013-02-26 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6EjI2S6Yo |archivedate=2013-02-26 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOuemint&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Nobuo Uematsu (December 2009) |url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/nobuouematsu.shtml |first=Don |last=Kotowski |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=December 2009 |accessdate=2013-02-26 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6EjI345mQ |archivedate=2013-02-26 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;OSValbumreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Fantastic Achievements: Symphonic Fantasies Review |url=http://www.originalsoundversion.com/fantastic-achievements-symphonic-fantasies-review/ |first=Audun |last=Sorlie |publisher=Original Sound Version |date=2010-09-15 |accessdate=2013-02-28 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120816061850/http://www.originalsoundversion.com/fantastic-achievements-symphonic-fantasies-review/ |archivedate=2012-08-16 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOalbumreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Symphonic Fantasies - Music from Square Enix :: Review by Chris |url=http://squareenixmusic.com/reviews/chris/symphonicfantasies.shtml |first=Chris |last=Greening |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |date=September 2010 |accessdate=2013-02-28 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100903152045/http://www.squareenixmusic.com/reviews/chris/symphonicfantasies.shtml |archivedate=2010-09-03 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;OWalbumreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Symphonic Fantasies &amp; Benyamin-Nuss-Album erschienen |url=http://www.onlinewelten.com/games/allgemeine-news/news/symphonic-fantasies-benyamin-nuss-album-erschienen-89473/ |first=Denis |last=Brown |publisher=OnlineWelten |language=German |date=2010-09-17 |accessdate=2013-02-28 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100920040619/http://www.onlinewelten.com/games/allgemeine-news/news/symphonic-fantasies-benyamin-nuss-album-erschienen-89473/ |archivedate=2010-09-20 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DESjalbumreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Napolitano |first=Jayson |title=Note Worthy 004: Anarchy Reigns and Unchained Blades |url=http://www.destructoid.com/note-worthy-004-anarchy-reigns-and-unchained-blades-231008.phtml |publisher=[[Destructoid]] |accessdate=2013-02-28 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20130120035657/http://www.destructoid.com/note-worthy-004-anarchy-reigns-and-unchained-blades-231008.phtml |archivedate=2013-01-20 |date=2012-07-16 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOjalbumreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Hammond |first=Joe |title=Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo :: Review by Joe Hammond |url=http://squareenixmusic.com/reviews/joehammond/symphonicfantasiestokyo.shtml |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |accessdate=2013-02-28 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6EmBotZnm |archivedate=2013-02-28 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

&lt;ref name=&quot;OSVjalbumreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Sorlie |first=Audun |title=Returning To Perfection: Symphonic Fantasies Tokyo (Review) |url=http://www.originalsoundversion.com/returning-to-perfection-symphonic-fantasies-tokyo-review/ |publisher=Original Sound Version |accessdate=2013-02-28 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120628215204/http://www.originalsoundversion.com/returning-to-perfection-symphonic-fantasies-tokyo-review/ |archivedate=2012-06-28 |date=2012-06-22 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
}}

==External links==
*[http://www.symphonicfantasies.com Symphonic Fantasies]
*[http://www.maz-sound.com/Symphonic-Fantasies/en/The-CD/ MAZ Sound Tools]
*[http://www.square-enix.com/ Square Enix's Official Website]
*[http://www.merregnon-studios.com Personal website of Thomas Böcker]

{{Merregnon Studios}}
{{Video game music concert series}}

[[Category:2010 live albums]]
[[Category:Concerts]]
[[Category:Square Enix]]
[[Category:Video game music]]</text>
      <sha1>7spmk1224gxntnpwreqzr87yhu1pjgc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Vitamin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32512</id>
    <revision>
      <id>543726567</id>
      <parentid>543724938</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-13T00:03:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/50.29.132.64|50.29.132.64]] ([[User talk:50.29.132.64|talk]]) to last version by Addbot</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44357">[[File:B vitamin supplement tablets.jpg|thumb|300px|A bottle of high potency B-complex vitamin supplement pills.]]
A '''vitamin''' ({{IPAc-en|US|ˈ|v|aɪ|t|əm|ɪ|n}} or {{IPAc-en|UK|ˈ|v|ɪ|t|əm|ɪ|n}}) is an [[organic compound]] required by an [[organism]] as a vital [[nutrient]] in limited amounts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lieberman&quot;&gt;Lieberman, S, Bruning, N (1990). The Real Vitamin &amp; Mineral Book. NY: Avery Group, 3, ISBN 0-89529-769-8&lt;/ref&gt; An organic chemical compound (or related set of compounds) is called a vitamin when it cannot be [[biosynthesis|synthesized]] in sufficient quantities by an organism, and must be obtained from the diet. Thus, the term is conditional both on the circumstances and on the particular organism. For example, [[ascorbic acid]] ([[vitamin C]]) is a vitamin for humans, but not for most other animals, and [[biotin]] and [[vitamin D]] are required in the human diet only in certain circumstances.

By convention, the term ''vitamin'' includes neither other [[essential nutrient]]s, such as [[dietary minerals]], [[essential fatty acid]]s, or [[essential amino acid]]s (which are needed in larger amounts than vitamins) nor  the large number of other nutrients that promote health but are otherwise required less often.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |last = Maton
 |first = Anthea
 |coauthors = Jean Hopkins, Charles William McLaughlin, Susan Johnson, Maryanna Quon Warner, David LaHart, Jill D. Wright
 |title = Human Biology and Health
 |publisher = Prentice Hall
 |year = 1993
 |location = Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey, USA
 |isbn = 0-13-981176-1
 |oclc = 32308337}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thirteen vitamins are universally recognized at present.

Vitamins are classified by their biological and chemical activity, not their structure. Thus, each &quot;vitamin&quot; refers to a number of ''[[vitamer]]'' compounds that all show the biological activity associated with a particular vitamin. Such a set of chemicals is grouped under an alphabetized vitamin &quot;generic descriptor&quot; title, such as &quot;[[vitamin A]]&quot;, which includes the compounds [[retinal]], [[retinol]], and four known [[carotenoid]]s. Vitamers by definition are convertible to the active form of the vitamin in the body, and are sometimes inter-convertible to one another, as well.

Vitamins have diverse biochemical functions. Some have hormone-like functions as regulators of mineral metabolism (such as vitamin D), or regulators of cell and tissue growth and differentiation (such as some forms of [[vitamin A]]). Others function as [[antioxidants]] (e.g., [[vitamin E]] and sometimes [[vitamin C]]).&lt;ref name= Bender&gt;{{Cite book |last1 = Bender|first1 = David A.|title = Nutritional biochemistry of the vitamins|year = 2003|publisher = Cambridge University Press|location = Cambridge, U.K. |isbn = 978-0-521-80388-5|pages =}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest number of vitamins (such as [[B complex]] vitamins) function as precursors for enzyme [[cofactor (biochemistry)|cofactor]]s, that help enzymes in their work as [[catalyst]]s in [[metabolism]]. In this role, vitamins may be tightly bound to [[enzyme]]s as part of [[prosthetic group]]s: For example, [[biotin]] is part of enzymes involved in making [[fatty acid]]s.

Vitamins may also be less tightly bound to enzyme catalysts as [[coenzyme]]s, detachable molecules that function to carry [[functional group|chemical groups]] or electrons between molecules. For example, [[folic acid]] may carry [[methyl group|methyl]], [[formyl]], and [[methylene group|methylene]] groups in the cell. Although these roles in assisting enzyme-substrate reactions are vitamins' best-known function, the other vitamin functions are equally important.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Bolander FF |title=Vitamins: not just for enzymes |journal=Curr Opin Investig Drugs |volume=7 |issue=10 |pages=912–5 |year=2006 |pmid=17086936}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Until the mid-1930s, when the first commercial yeast-extract vitamin B complex and semi-synthetic vitamin C supplement tablets were sold, vitamins were obtained solely through food intake, and changes in diet (which, for example, could occur during a particular growing season) usually greatly altered the types and amounts of vitamins ingested. However, vitamins have been produced as commodity [[chemicals]] and made widely available as inexpensive semisynthetic and synthetic-source [[multivitamin]] dietary and food supplements and additives, since the middle of the 20th century.

The term ''vitamin'' was derived from &quot;vitamine,&quot; a [[compound (linguistics)|compound word]] coined in 1912 by the Polish [[biochemist]] [[Kazimierz Funk]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Dzieje nauki polskiej|last= Iłowiecki|first=Maciej|year=1981|publisher=Wydawnictwo Interpress|location= Warszawa|page= 177|isbn=83-223-1876-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; when working at the [[Lister Institute of Preventive Medicine]]. The name is from ''vital'' and ''amine,'' meaning [[amine]] of life, because it was suggested in 1912 that the organic micronutrient food factors that prevent [[beriberi]] and perhaps other similar dietary-deficiency diseases might be chemical amines. This proved incorrect for the micronutrient class, and the word was shortened to vitamin.

==History==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style = &quot;float:right; font-size:90%; margin-left:15px&quot;
|+ The discovery dates of the vitamins and their sources
|- class=&quot;hintergrundfarbe6&quot;
! Year of discovery !! Vitamin !! Food source
|-
| 1913 || Vitamin A ([[Retinol]]) || [[Cod liver oil]]
|-
| 1910 || Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; ([[Thiamine]]) || [[Rice bran]]
|-
| 1920 || Vitamin C ([[Ascorbic acid]]) || [[Citrus]], most fresh foods
|-
| 1920 || Vitamin D ([[Calciferol]]) || [[Cod liver oil]]
|-
| 1920 || Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ([[Riboflavin]]) || [[Meat]], [[Egg (food)|egg]]s
|-
| 1922 || ([[Vitamin E]]) ([[Tocopherol]])|| [[Wheat germ oil]], unrefined vegetable oils
|-
| 1926 || [[Vitamin B12|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;]] (Cobalamins) || [[Liver (food)|liver]], [[Egg (food)|egg]]s, animal products
|-
| 1929 || Vitamin K&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; ([[Phylloquinone]]) || [[Leafy green vegetables]]
 |-
| 1931 || Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; ([[Pantothenic acid]]) || [[Meat]], [[whole grain]]s, &lt;br&gt; in many foods
|-
| 1931 || Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; ([[Biotin]]) || [[Meat]], [[dairy products]], [[Egg (food)|egg]]s
|-
| 1934 || Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; ([[Pyridoxine]]) || [[Meat]], [[dairy products]]
|-
| 1936 || Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; ([[Niacin]]) || [[Meat]], [[Egg (food)|egg]]s, [[grain]]s
|-
| 1941 || Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;9&lt;/sub&gt; ([[Folic acid]]) || [[Leafy green vegetables]]
|}

The value of eating a certain food to maintain health was recognized long before vitamins were identified. The ancient [[Egypt]]ians knew that feeding [[liver (food)|liver]] to a person would help cure [[night blindness]], an illness now known to be caused by a [[vitamin A]] deficiency.&lt;ref name=&quot;Challem&quot;/&gt; The advancement of ocean voyages during the [[Renaissance]] resulted in prolonged periods without access to fresh fruits and vegetables, and made illnesses from vitamin deficiency common among ships' crews.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1 = Jacob|first1 = RA.|title = Three eras of vitamin C discovery|journal = Subcell Biochem|volume = 25|pages = 1–16|year = 1996|pmid = 8821966}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1747, the [[Scotland|Scottish]] [[surgeon]] [[James Lind (physician)|James Lind]] discovered that [[citrus]] foods helped prevent [[scurvy]], a particularly deadly disease in which [[collagen]] is not properly formed, causing poor wound healing, bleeding of the [[gingiva|gums]], severe pain, and death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Challem&quot;&gt;Jack Challem (1997). [http://web.archive.org/web/20051130103653/http://www.thenutritionreporter.com/history_of_vitamins.html &quot;The Past, Present and Future of Vitamins&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1753, Lind published his ''Treatise on the Scurvy'', which recommended using [[lemon]]s and [[Lime (fruit)|lime]]s to avoid [[scurvy]], which was adopted by the British [[Royal Navy]]. This led to the nickname [[Limey]] for sailors of that organization. Lind's discovery, however, was not widely accepted by individuals in the Royal Navy's [[Arctic]] expeditions in the 19th century, where it was widely believed that scurvy could be prevented by practicing good [[hygiene]], regular exercise, and maintaining the [[morale]] of the crew while on board, rather than by a diet of fresh food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Challem&quot;/&gt; As a result, Arctic expeditions continued to be plagued by scurvy and other [[deficiency disease]]s. In the early 20th century, when [[Robert Falcon Scott]] made his two expeditions to the [[Antarctic]], the prevailing medical theory was that scurvy was caused by &quot;tainted&quot; [[canning|canned food]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Challem&quot;/&gt;

During the late 18th and early 19th centuries, the use of deprivation studies allowed scientists to isolate and identify a number of vitamins. Lipid from [[fish oil]] was used to cure [[rickets]] in [[rat]]s, and the fat-soluble nutrient was called &quot;antirachitic A&quot;. Thus, the first &quot;vitamin&quot; bioactivity ever isolated, which cured rickets, was initially called &quot;vitamin A&quot;; however, the bioactivity of this compound is now called [[vitamin D]].&lt;ref&gt;Bellis, Mary. [http://inventors.about.com/library/inventors/bl_vitamins.htm Vitamins&amp;nbsp;– Production Methods The History of the Vitamins]. Retrieved 1 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1881, [[Russia]]n surgeon Nikolai Lunin studied the effects of scurvy while at the [[University of Tartu]] in present-day Estonia.&lt;ref name=&quot;nobel&quot;&gt;[http://nobelprize.org/medicine/laureates/1929/hopkins-lecture.html 1929 Nobel lecture]&lt;/ref&gt; He fed [[mouse|mice]] an artificial mixture of all the separate constituents of [[milk]] known at that time, namely the [[protein]]s, [[fat]]s, [[carbohydrate]]s, and [[salt]]s. The mice that received only the individual constituents died, while the mice fed by milk itself developed normally. He made a conclusion that &quot;a natural food such as milk must therefore contain, besides these known principal ingredients, small quantities of unknown substances essential to life.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nobel&quot;/&gt; However, his conclusions were rejected by other researchers when they were unable to reproduce his results. One difference was that he had used table sugar ([[sucrose]]), while other researchers had used milk sugar ([[lactose]]) that still contained small amounts of [[vitamin B]].{{Citation needed|reason=please give a reliable source for this assertion. Lactose itself can not be the source of vitamin B|date=July 2010}}

[[File:ARS copper rich foods.jpg|thumb|left|350px|alt= Image illustrating rich and good nutritional sources of copper including: oysters, beef or lamb liver, Brazil nuts, blackstrap molasses, cocoa, and black pepper, lobster, nuts and sunflower seeds, green olives, and wheat bran.| The [[Ancient Egyptians]] knew that feeding a person [[liver (food)|liver]] (back, right) would help cure [[Nyctalopia|night blindness]].]]

In [[east Asia]], where polished [[white rice]] was the common staple food of the middle class, [[beriberi]] resulting from lack of vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; was [[Endemic (epidemiology)|endemic]]. In 1884, [[Takaki Kanehiro]], a British trained medical doctor of the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]], observed that [[beriberi]] was [[Endemic (epidemiology)|endemic]] among low-ranking crew who often ate nothing but rice, but not among officers who consumed a Western-style diet. With the support of the Japanese navy, he experimented using crews of two [[battleship]]s; one crew was fed only white rice, while the other was fed a diet of meat, fish, barley, rice, and beans. The group that ate only white rice documented 161 crew members with beriberi and 25 deaths, while the latter group had only 14 cases of beriberi and no deaths. This convinced Takaki and the Japanese Navy that diet was the cause of beriberi, but mistakenly believed that sufficient amounts of protein prevented it.&lt;ref name=Rosenfeld&gt;{{Cite journal |last1 = Rosenfeld|first1 = L.|title = Vitamine—vitamin. The early years of discovery|journal = Clin Chem|volume = 43|issue = 4|pages = 680–5|year = 1997|pmid = 9105273}}&lt;/ref&gt; That diseases could result from some dietary deficiencies was further investigated by [[Christiaan Eijkman]], who in 1897 discovered that feeding unpolished [[rice]] instead of the polished variety to chickens helped to prevent beriberi in the chickens. The following year, [[Frederick Hopkins]] postulated that some foods contained &quot;accessory factors&quot;&amp;nbsp;— in addition to proteins, carbohydrates, fats ''etc.''&amp;nbsp;— that are necessary for the functions of the human body.&lt;ref name=&quot;Challem&quot;/&gt; Hopkins and Eijkman were awarded the [[Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine]] in 1929 for their discovery of several vitamins.&lt;ref name= Carpenter&gt;{{cite web |last = Carpenter|first = Kenneth|title = The Nobel Prize and the Discovery of Vitamins|url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/articles/carpenter/index.html|publisher = Nobelprize.org|date = 22 June 2004|accessdate = 5 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1910, the first vitamin complex was isolated by Japanese scientist [[Umetaro Suzuki]], who succeeded in extracting a water-soluble complex of micronutrients from rice bran and named it [[aberic acid]] (later ''Orizanin''). He published this discovery in a Japanese scientific journal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.journalarchive.jst.go.jp/english/jnlabstract_en.php?cdjournal=nikkashi1880&amp;cdvol=32&amp;noissue=1&amp;startpage=4 Tokyo Kagaku Kaishi: (1911)]&lt;/ref&gt; When the article was translated into German, the translation failed to state that it was a newly discovered nutrient, a claim made in the original Japanese article, and hence his discovery failed to gain publicity. In 1912 Polish biochemist [[Casimir Funk]] isolated the same complex of micronutrients and proposed the complex be named &quot;vitamine&quot; (a [[portmanteau]] of &quot;vital amine&quot; reportedly suggested by [[Maximilian Nierenstein|Max Nierenstein]] a friend and reader of Biochemistry at Bristol University&lt;ref name= Nierenstein&gt;{{cite book |last = Combs|first = Gerald|title = The vitamins: fundamental aspects in nutrition and health|url = http://books.google.com/?id=1CMHiWum0Y4C&amp;pg=PA16&amp;lpg=PA16&amp;dq=max+nierenstein+vitamin#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |isbn = 9780121834937 |year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;).&lt;ref&gt;Funk, C. and H. E. Dubin. The Vitamines. Baltimore: Williams and Wilkins Company, 1922.&lt;/ref&gt; The name soon became synonymous with Hopkins' &quot;accessory factors&quot;, and, by the time it was shown that not all vitamins are [[amine]]s, the word was already ubiquitous. In 1920, [[Jack Cecil Drummond]] proposed that the final &quot;e&quot; be dropped to deemphasize the &quot;amine&quot; reference, after researchers began to suspect that not all &quot;vitamines&quot; (in particular, [[vitamin A]]) have an amine component.&lt;ref name=Rosenfeld/&gt;

In 1931, [[Albert Szent-Györgyi]] and a fellow researcher Joseph Svirbely suspected that &quot;hexuronic acid&quot; was actually [[vitamin C]], and gave a sample to [[Charles Glen King]], who proved its anti-[[scurvy|scorbutic]] activity in his long-established [[guinea pig]] scorbutic assay. In 1937, Szent-Györgyi was awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine]] for his discovery. In 1943, [[Edward Adelbert Doisy]] and [[Henrik Dam]] were awarded the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine for their discovery of [[vitamin K]] and its chemical structure. In 1967, [[George Wald]] was awarded the Nobel Prize (along with [[Ragnar Granit]] and [[Haldan Keffer Hartline]]) for his discovery that vitamin A could participate directly in a physiological process.&lt;ref name= Carpenter/&gt;

==In humans==
Vitamins are classified as either [[water]]-soluble or fat-soluble. In humans there are 13 vitamins: 4 fat-soluble (A, D, E, and K) and 9 water-soluble (8 B vitamins and vitamin C). Water-soluble vitamins dissolve easily in water and, in general, are readily excreted from the body, to the degree that urinary output is a strong predictor of vitamin consumption.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18635909&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Fukuwatari T, Shibata K |title=Urinary water-soluble vitamins and their metabolite contents as nutritional markers for evaluating vitamin intakes in young Japanese women |journal=J. Nutr. Sci. Vitaminol. |volume=54 |issue=3 |pages=223–9 |year=2008|pmid=18635909 |doi= 10.3177/jnsv.54.223}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because they are not as readily stored, more consistent intake is important.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlWater-Soluble Vitamins&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ext.colostate.edu/PUBS/FOODNUT/09312.html |title=Water-Soluble Vitamins |accessdate=2008-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many types of water-soluble vitamins are synthesized by bacteria.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16462170&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Said HM, Mohammed ZM |title=Intestinal absorption of water-soluble vitamins: an update |journal=Curr. Opin. Gastroenterol. |volume=22 |issue=2 |pages=140–6 |year=2006 |pmid=16462170 |doi=10.1097/01.mog.0000203870.22706.52 |url=http://meta.wkhealth.com/pt/pt-core/template-journal/lwwgateway/media/landingpage.htm?an=00001574-200603000-00011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fat]]-soluble vitamins are absorbed through the [[intestinal tract]] with the help of [[lipid]]s (fats). Because they are more likely to accumulate in the body, they are more likely to lead to [[hypervitaminosis]] than are water-soluble vitamins. Fat-soluble vitamin regulation is of particular significance in [[cystic fibrosis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18812835&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Maqbool A, Stallings VA |title=Update on fat-soluble vitamins in cystic fibrosis |journal=Curr Opin Pulm Med |volume=14 |issue=6 |pages=574–81 |year=2008 |pmid=18812835 |doi=10.1097/MCP.0b013e3283136787 |url=http://meta.wkhealth.com/pt/pt-core/template-journal/lwwgateway/media/landingpage.htm?an=00063198-200811000-00012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===List of vitamins===
Each vitamin is typically used in multiple reactions, and, therefore, most have multiple functions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kutsky&quot;&gt;Kutsky, R.J. (1973). Handbook of Vitamins and Hormones. New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold, ISBN 0-442-24549-1&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em auto 1em auto&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;|Vitamin generic&lt;br&gt; descriptor name
! style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;|[[Vitamer]] chemical name(s) (list not complete)
! style=&quot;width:75px;&quot;|[[Solubility]]
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;|[[Reference Daily Intake|Recommended dietary allowances]]&lt;br&gt;(male, age 19–70)&lt;ref name=&quot;RDA&quot;&gt;[http://iom.edu/en/Global/News%20Announcements/~/media/Files/Activity%20Files/Nutrition/DRIs/DRISummaryListing2.ashx Dietary Reference Intakes: Vitamins] The National Academies, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;&quot;| Deficiency disease
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;|Upper Intake Level&lt;br&gt; (UL/day)&lt;ref name=&quot;RDA&quot;/&gt;
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;| Overdose disease
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;&quot;| Food sources
|-
! [[Vitamin A]]
| [[Retinol]], [[retinal]], and&lt;br&gt;four [[carotenoid]]s &lt;br&gt;including [[beta carotene]]
| Fat
| '''900&amp;nbsp;µg'''
| [[Night-blindness]], [[Hyperkeratosis]], and [[Keratomalacia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;GOVa&quot;&gt;[http://dietary-supplements.info.nih.gov/factsheets/vitamina.asp Vitamin and Mineral Supplement Fact Sheets Vitamin A]&lt;/ref&gt;
| 3,000&amp;nbsp;µg
| [[Hypervitaminosis A]]
| Orange, ripe yellow fruits, leafy vegetables, carrots, pumpkin, squash, spinach, liver
|-
! [[Thiamine|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Thiamine]]
| Water
| '''1.2&amp;nbsp;mg'''
| [[Beriberi]], [[Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome]]
| N/D&lt;ref&gt;N/D= &quot;Amount not determinable due to lack of data of adverse effects. Source of intake should be from food only to prevent high levels of intake&quot;(see [http://www.iom.edu/Object.File/Master/7/296/0.pdf Dietary Reference Intakes: Vitamins]).&lt;/ref&gt;
| Drowsiness or muscle relaxation with large doses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = Thiamin, vitamin B1: MedlinePlus Supplements| url = http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/patient-thiamin.html|accessdate = 5 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Pork, oatmeal, brown rice, vegetables, potatoes, liver, eggs
|-
! [[Riboflavin|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Riboflavin]]
| Water
| '''1.3&amp;nbsp;mg'''
| [[Ariboflavinosis]]
| N/D
|
|Dairy products, bananas, popcorn, green beans, asparagus
|-
! [[Niacin|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Niacin]], [[niacinamide]]
| Water
| '''16.0&amp;nbsp;mg'''
| [[Pellagra]]
| 35.0&amp;nbsp;mg
| [[Liver]] damage (doses &gt; 2g/day)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor=Hardman, J.G. ''et al.''|title=Goodman and Gilman's Pharmacological Basis of Therapeutics|edition=10th|page=992}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Niacin#Toxicity|other problems]]
|Meat, fish, eggs, many vegetables, mushrooms, tree nuts
|-
! [[Pantothenic acid|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Pantothenic acid]]
| Water
| 5.0&amp;nbsp;mg&lt;ref&gt;Plain type indicates Adequate Intakes (A/I). &quot;The AI is believed to cover the needs of all individuals, but a lack of data prevent being able to specify with confidence the percentage of individuals covered by this intake&quot; (see [http://www.iom.edu/Object.File/Master/7/296/0.pdf Dietary Reference Intakes: Vitamins]).&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Paresthesia]]
| N/D
| Diarrhea; possibly nausea and heartburn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = Pantothenic acid, dexpanthenol: MedlinePlus Supplements|url = http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/patient-vitaminb5.html|accessdate = 5 October 2009|publisher=MedlinePlus}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Meat, broccoli, avocados
|-
! [[Vitamin B6|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Pyridoxine]], [[pyridoxamine]], [[pyridoxal]]
| Water
| '''1.3–1.7&amp;nbsp;mg'''
| [[Anemia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;GOVb6&quot;&gt;[http://dietary-supplements.info.nih.gov/factsheets/vitaminb6.asp Vitamin and Mineral Supplement Fact Sheets Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[peripheral neuropathy]].
| 100&amp;nbsp;mg
| Impairment of [[proprioception]], nerve damage (doses &gt; 100&amp;nbsp;mg/day)
|Meat, vegetables, tree nuts, bananas
|-
! [[Biotin|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Biotin]]
| Water
| 30.0&amp;nbsp;µg
| [[Dermatitis]], [[enteritis]]
| N/D
|
|Raw egg yolk, liver, peanuts, certain vegetables
|-
! [[Folic acid|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;9&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Folic acid]], [[folinic acid]]
| Water
| '''400&amp;nbsp;µg'''
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| [[Megaloblast]] and Deficiency during pregnancy is associated with [[birth defects]], such as [[neural tube]] defects
| 1,000&amp;nbsp;µg
| May mask symptoms of vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; deficiency; [[Folic acid#Overdose risks|other effects]].
|Leafy vegetables, pasta, bread, cereal, liver
|-
! [[Vitamin B12|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Cyanocobalamin]], [[hydroxycobalamin]], [[methylcobalamin]]
| Water
| '''2.4&amp;nbsp;µg'''
| [[Megaloblastic anemia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;GOVb12&quot;&gt;[http://dietary-supplements.info.nih.gov/factsheets/vitaminb12.asp Vitamin and Mineral Supplement Fact Sheets Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
| N/D
| Acne-like rash [causality is not conclusively established].
|Meat and other animal products
|-
! [[Vitamin C]]
| [[Ascorbic acid]]
| Water
| '''90.0&amp;nbsp;mg'''
| [[Scurvy]]
| 2,000&amp;nbsp;mg
| [[Vitamin C megadosage]]
|Many fruits and vegetables, liver
|-
! style=&quot;whitespace:nowrap;&quot;|[[Vitamin D]]
| [[Cholecalciferol]]
| Fat
| 10&amp;nbsp;µg&lt;ref&gt;Value represents suggested intake without adequate sunlight exposure (see [http://www.iom.edu/Object.File/Master/7/296/0.pdf Dietary Reference Intakes: Vitamins]).&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Rickets]] and [[Osteomalacia]]
| 50&amp;nbsp;µg
| [[Hypervitaminosis D]]
|Fish, eggs, liver, mushrooms
|-
! [[Vitamin E]]
| [[Tocopherol]]s, [[tocotrienol]]s
| Fat
| '''15.0&amp;nbsp;mg'''
|align=&quot;left&quot;| Deficiency is very rare; mild [[hemolytic anemia]] in newborn infants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Merck&quot;&gt;[http://www.merck.com/mmhe/sec12/ch154/ch154a.html The Merck Manual: Nutritional Disorders: Vitamin Introduction] Please select specific vitamins from the list at the top of the page.&lt;/ref&gt;
| 1,000&amp;nbsp;mg
| Increased congestive heart failure seen in one large randomized study.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0ISW/is_262/ai_n13675725|work=Townsend Letter for Doctors and Patients|title=Does vitamin E cause congestive heart failure?|first=Alan R.|last=Gaby|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Many fruits and vegetables, nuts and seeds
|-
! [[Vitamin K]]
| [[phylloquinone]], [[menaquinone]]s
| Fat
| 120&amp;nbsp;µg
| [[Bleeding diathesis]]
| N/D
| Increases coagulation in patients taking [[warfarin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Rohde LE, de Assis MC, Rabelo ER |title=Dietary vitamin K intake and anticoagulation in elderly patients |journal=Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care |volume=10 |issue=1 |pages=1–5 |year=2007|pmid=17143047 |doi=10.1097/MCO.0b013e328011c46c}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Leafy green vegetables such as spinach, egg yolks, liver
|-
|}

==In nutrition and diseases==

Vitamins are essential for the normal growth and development of a multicellular organism. Using the genetic blueprint inherited from its parents, a [[fetus]] begins to develop, at the moment of conception, from the nutrients it absorbs. It requires certain vitamins and minerals to be present at certain times. These nutrients facilitate the chemical reactions that produce among other things, [[skin]], [[bone]], and [[muscle]]. If there is serious deficiency in one or more of these nutrients, a child may develop a deficiency disease. Even minor deficiencies may cause permanent damage.&lt;ref&gt;Gavrilov, Leonid A. [http://www.longevitymeme.org/articles/viewarticle.cfm?page=1&amp;article_id=12 Pieces of the Puzzle: Aging Research Today and Tomorrow]&lt;/ref&gt;

For the most part, vitamins are obtained with food, but a few are obtained by other means. For example, microorganisms in the intestine&amp;nbsp;— commonly known as &quot;[[gut flora]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;— produce vitamin K and biotin, while one form of vitamin D is synthesized in the [[skin]] with the help of the natural [[ultraviolet]] wavelength of [[sunlight]]. Humans can produce some vitamins from precursors they consume. Examples include [[vitamin A]], produced from [[beta carotene]], and [[niacin]], from the [[amino acid]] [[tryptophan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RDA&quot;/&gt;

Once growth and development are completed, vitamins remain essential nutrients for the healthy maintenance of the cells, tissues, and organs that make up a multicellular organism; they also enable a multicellular life form to efficiently use chemical energy provided by food it eats, and to help process the proteins, carbohydrates, and fats required for respiration.&lt;ref name= Bender/&gt;

===Effect of cooking on vitamin content===
Shown below is percentage loss of vitamins after cooking averaged for common foods such as vegetables, meat, fish.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
!Vitamin
!C 
! B1 
! B2 
! B3 
! B5 
! B6 
! Folate 
! B12 
! A 
! E 
|-
|Average %loss 
|16 
| 26 
| -3 
| 18 
| 17 
| 3 
| 20 
| ? 
| 11 
| 11 
|} 
It should be noted however that some vitamins may become more &quot;bio-available&quot; – that is, usable by the body – when steamed or cooked. 
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.beyondveg.com/tu-j-l/raw-cooked/raw-cooked-2f.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

Table below shows effects of heat such as heat from boiling, steaming, cooking etc. and other agents on various vitamins. Effect of cutting vegetables can be seen from exposure to air and light. Water soluble vitamins such as B and C seep into the water when boiling a vegetable.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; |- 
!Vitamin  
!Soluble in Water 
!Exposure to Air 
!Exposure to Light 
!Exposure to Heat 
|- 
|[[Vitamin A]] 
| no 
| partially 
| partially 
| relatively stable 
|- 
|Vitamin C 
| very unstable 
| yes 
| yes 
| yes 
|- 
| Vitamin D 
| no 
| no 
| no 
| no 
|- 
| Vitamin E 
| no 
| yes 
| yes 
| no 
|-
|Vitamin K 
| no 
| no 
| yes 
| no 
|-
|Thiamine (B1)
| highly 
| no 
| ? 
| &gt; 100°C 
|- 
|Riboflavin (B2)
| slightly 
| no 
| in solution 
| no 
|- 
|Niacin (B3)
| yes 
| no 
| no 
| no 
|- 
|Pantothenic Acid (B5)
| quite stable 
| ? 
| ? 
| yes 
|- 
|Vitamin B6 
| yes 
| ? 
| yes 
| ? 
|- 
|Biotin (B7)
| somewhat 
| ? 
| ? 
| no 
|- 
|Folic Acid B-9 
| yes 
| ? 
| when dry 
| at high temp 
|-
|Vitamin B-12 
| yes 
| ? 
| yes 
| no 
|}&lt;ref&gt;http://www.beyondveg.com/tu-j-l/raw-cooked/raw-cooked-2e.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

===Deficiencies===
Humans must consume vitamins periodically but with differing schedules, to avoid deficiency. The human body's stores for different vitamins vary widely; vitamins A, D, and B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; are stored in significant amounts in the human body, mainly in the [[liver]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Merck&quot;/&gt; and an adult human's diet may be deficient in vitamins A and D for many months and B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; in some cases for years, before developing a deficiency condition. However, vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; (niacin and niacinamide) is not stored in the human body in significant amounts, so stores may last only a couple of weeks.&lt;ref name=&quot;GOVa&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Merck&quot;/&gt; For vitamin C, the first symptoms of [[scurvy]] in experimental studies of complete vitamin C deprivation in humans have varied widely, from a month to more than six months, depending on previous dietary history that determined body stores.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Pemberton|first1=J.|title=Medical experiments carried out in Sheffield on conscientious objectors to military service during the 1939–45 war|journal=International Journal of Epidemiology|volume=35|issue=3|pages=556–8|year=2006|pmid=16510534|doi=10.1093/ije/dyl020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Deficiencies of vitamins are classified as either primary or secondary. A primary deficiency occurs when an organism does not get enough of the vitamin in its food. A secondary deficiency may be due to an underlying disorder that prevents or limits the absorption or use of the vitamin, due to a &quot;lifestyle factor&quot;, such as smoking, excessive alcohol consumption, or the use of medications that interfere with the absorption or use of the vitamin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Merck&quot;/&gt; People who eat a varied diet are unlikely to develop a severe primary vitamin deficiency. In contrast, restrictive diets have the potential to cause prolonged vitamin deficits, which may result in often painful and potentially deadly [[disease]]s.

Well-known human vitamin deficiencies involve thiamine ([[beriberi]]), niacin ([[pellagra]]), vitamin C ([[scurvy]]), and vitamin D ([[rickets]]). In much of the developed world, such deficiencies are rare; this is due to (1) an adequate supply of food and (2) the addition of vitamins and minerals to common foods, often called fortification.&lt;ref name=&quot;RDA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Merck&quot;/&gt; In addition to these classical vitamin deficiency diseases, some evidence has also suggested links between vitamin deficiency and a number of different disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lakhan|first1=SE|last2=Vieira|first2=KF|title=Nutritional therapies for mental disorders|journal=Nutrition journal|volume=7|pages=2|year=2008|pmid=18208598|pmc=2248201|doi=10.1186/1475-2891-7-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1 = Boy|first1 = E.|last2 = Mannar|first2 = V.|last3 = Pandav|first3 = C.|last4 = de Benoist|first4 = B.|last5 = Viteri|first5 = F.|last6 = Fontaine|first6 = O.|last7 = Hotz|first7 = C.|title = Achievements, challenges, and promising new approaches in vitamin and mineral deficiency control|journal = Nutr Rev|volume = 67|issue =Suppl 1 |pages = S24–30|year = 2009|doi = 10.1111/j.1753-4887.2009.00155.x|pmid = 19453674}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Side-effects and overdose===
In large doses, some vitamins have documented [[Hypervitaminosis|side-effects]] that tend to be more severe with a larger dosage. The likelihood of consuming too much of any vitamin from food is remote, but overdosing ([[vitamin poisoning]]) from vitamin supplementation does occur. At high enough dosages, some vitamins cause side-effects such as [[nausea]], [[diarrhea]], and [[vomiting]].&lt;ref name=GOVa/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Institute of Medicine. Food and Nutrition Board. Dietary Reference Intakes for Vitamin A, Vitamin K, Arsenic, Boron, Chromium, Copper, Iodine, Iron, Manganese, Molybdenum, Nickel, Silicon, Vanadium, and Zinc. National Academy Press, Washington, DC, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; When side-effects emerge, recovery is often accomplished by reducing the dosage. The doses of vitamins differ because individual tolerances can vary widely and appear to be related to age and state of health.&lt;ref name=&quot;Healthier&quot;&gt;[http://www.healthier-kids.com Healthier Kids] '''Section:''' What to take and how to take it.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, overdose exposure to all formulations of vitamins and multivitamin-mineral formulations was reported by 68,911 individuals to the [[American Association of Poison Control Centers]] (nearly 80% of these exposures were in children under the age of 6), leading to 8 &quot;major&quot; life-threatening outcomes and 0 deaths.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last = Bronstein|first = AC|coauthors = et al.|title = 2008 Annual Report of the American Association of Poison Control Centers' National Poison Data System (NPDS): 26th Annual Report|journal = Clinical Toxicology|year = 2009|volume = 47|pages = 911–1084|url = http://www.aapcc.org/dnn/Portals/0/2008annualreport.pdf|format = PDF|doi = 10.3109/15563650903438566|pmid = 20028214|issue = 10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Supplements==
[[Dietary supplement]]s, often containing vitamins, are used to ensure that adequate amounts of nutrients are obtained on a daily basis, if optimal amounts of the nutrients cannot be obtained through a varied diet. Scientific evidence supporting the benefits of some vitamin supplements is well established for certain health conditions, but others need further study.&lt;ref name= Sup&gt;[http://dietary-supplements.info.nih.gov/Health_Information/ODS_Frequently_Asked_Questions.aspx Use and Safety of Dietary Supplements] NIH office of Dietary Supplements.&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, vitamin supplements may have unwanted effects, especially if taken before surgery, with other dietary supplements or medicines, or if the person taking them has certain health conditions.&lt;ref name= Sup/&gt; Dietary supplements may also contain levels of vitamins many times higher, and in different forms, than one may ingest through food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Higdon&quot;&gt;Higdon, Jane [http://lpi.oregonstate.edu/infocenter/vitamins/vitaminE/ Vitamin E recommendations at Linus Pauling Institute's Micronutrient Information Center]&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been mixed studies on the importance and safety of dietary supplementation. A [[meta-analysis]] published in 2006 suggested that Vitamin A and E supplements not only provide no tangible health benefits for generally healthy individuals but may actually increase mortality, although two large studies included in the analysis involved [[tobacco smoking|smokers]], for whom it was already known that [[beta-carotene]] supplements can be harmful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1001/jama.297.8.842 |title=Mortality in Randomized Trials of Antioxidant Supplements for Primary and Secondary Prevention: Systematic Review and Meta-analysis |year=2007 |last1=Bjelakovic |first1=Goran |journal=JAMA |volume=297 |issue=8 |pmid=17327526 |pages=842–57 |last2=Nikolova |first2=D |last3=Gluud |first3=LL |last4=Simonetti |first4=RG |last5=Gluud |first5=C}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1001/jama.298.4.401-a |title=Antioxidant Supplements and Mortality |year=2007 |journal=JAMA |volume=298 |issue=4 |pages=400}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1001/jama.298.4.402 |title=Antioxidant Supplements and Mortality—Reply |year=2007 |journal=JAMA |volume=298 |issue=4 |pages=400}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another study published in May 2009 found that antioxidants such as vitamins C and E may actually curb some benefits of exercise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/12/health/research/12exer.html?em=&amp;pagewanted=print|work=The New York Times|title=Vitamins Found to Curb Exercise Benefits|first=Nicholas|last=Wade|date=12 May 2009|accessdate=9 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; While other findings suggest that evidence of Vitamin E toxicity is limited to specific form taken in excess.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tocotrienols: Vitamin E beyond tocopherols.&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.lfs.2005.12.001 |title=Tocotrienols: Vitamin E beyond tocopherols |year=2006 |last1=Sen |first1=Chandan K. |last2=Khanna |first2=Savita |last3=Roy |first3=Sashwati |journal=Life Sciences |volume=78 |issue=18 |pages=2088–98 |pmid=16458936 |pmc=1790869}}&lt;/ref&gt; A double-blind trial published in 2011 found that vitamin E increases the risk of prostate cancer in healthy men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1001/jama.2011.1437 |title=Vitamin E and the Risk of Prostate Cancer: The Selenium and Vitamin E Cancer Prevention Trial (SELECT) |year=2011 |last1=Klein |first1=Eric A. |journal=JAMA |volume=306 |issue=14 |pages=1549–56 |pmid=21990298 |last2=Thompson Jr |first2=IM |last3=Tangen |first3=CM |last4=Crowley |first4=JJ |last5=Lucia |first5=MS |last6=Goodman |first6=PJ |last7=Minasian |first7=LM |last8=Ford |first8=LG |last9=Parnes |first9=HL}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conflict of interest section of this study reveals that it has ties to the ambitions of the pharmaceutical companies Merck, Pfizer, Sanofi-Aventis, AstraZeneca, Abbott, GlaxoSmithKline, Janssen, Amgen, Firmagon, and Novartis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jama.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1104493 Scroll down to &quot;Conflict of Interest Disclosures&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies without conflicts of interest reported exactly the opposite - that Vitamin E supplementation reduced the risk of prostate cancer,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite PMID|9521168}}&lt;/ref&gt; and increased overall prostate cancer survival.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite PMID|19383902}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Governmental regulation of vitamin supplements===
Most countries place [[dietary supplement]]s in a special category under the general umbrella of ''foods'', not drugs. This necessitates that the manufacturer, and not the government, be responsible for ensuring that its dietary supplement products are safe before they are marketed. Regulation of supplements varies widely by country. In the [[United States]], a dietary supplement is defined under the [[Dietary Supplement Health and Education Act]] of 1994.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fda.gov/opacom/laws/dshea.html Legislation]. Fda.gov (2009-09-15). Retrieved on 2010-11-12.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the [[Food and Drug Administration]] uses the Adverse Event Reporting System to monitor adverse events that occur with supplements.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/GuidanceComplianceRegulatoryInformation/Surveillance/AdverseDrugEffects/default.htm Adverse Event Reporting System (AERS)]. Fda.gov (2009-08-20). Retrieved on 2010-11-12.&lt;/ref&gt; In the European Union, the [[Food Supplements Directive]] requires that only those supplements that have been proven safe can be sold without a prescription.&lt;ref&gt;[http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:32002L0046:EN:''not'' EUR-Lex&amp;nbsp;– 32002L0046&amp;nbsp;– EN]. Eur-lex.europa.eu. Retrieved on 2010-11-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Names in current and previous nomenclatures==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style = &quot;float:right; font-size:90%; margin-left:20px&quot;
|+ Nomenclature of reclassified vitamins
|- class=&quot;hintergrundfarbe6&quot;
! Previous name
! Chemical name
! Reason for name change&lt;ref name=Bennett/&gt;
|-
| [[B vitamins|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Adenine]]
| DNA metabolite; synthesized in body
|-
| [[B vitamins|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;]]
| [[Adenylic acid]]
| DNA metabolite; synthesized in body
|-
| Vitamin F
| [[Essential fatty acid]]s
| Needed in large quantities (does&lt;br&gt; not fit the definition of a vitamin).
|-
| Vitamin G
| [[Riboflavin]]
| Reclassified as [[B vitamins|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]]
|-
| Vitamin H
| [[Biotin]]
| Reclassified as [[B vitamins|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;]]
|-
| Vitamin J
| [[Catechol]], [[Flavin group|Flavin]]
| Catechol nonessential; flavin reclassified as B&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;sub&gt;
|-
| Vitamin L&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;ref name=VitaminL&gt;Davidson, Michael W. (2004) [http://micro.magnet.fsu.edu/vitamins/pages/anthranilic.html Anthranilic Acid (Vitamin L)] [[Florida State University]]. Retrieved 20-02-07.&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Anthranilic acid]]
| Non essential
|-
| Vitamin L&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;ref name=VitaminL/&gt;
| [[Adenylthiomethylpentose]]
| RNA metabolite; synthesized in body
|-
| Vitamin M
| [[Folic acid]]
| Reclassified as [[B vitamins|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;9&lt;/sub&gt;]]
|-
| Vitamin O
| [[Carnitine]]
| Synthesized in body
|-
| Vitamin P
| [[Flavonoids]]
| No longer classified as a vitamin
|-
| Vitamin PP
| [[Niacin]]
| Reclassified as [[B vitamins|Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;]]
|-
| Vitamin S
| [[Salicylic acid]]
| Proposed inclusion&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Rapid Responses to: Aspirin protects women at risk of pre-eclampsia without causing bleeding|author=Kamran Abbasi|journal=British Medical Journal|volume=327|year=2003|page=7424|doi=10.1136/bmj.327.7424.0-h|issue=7424}}&lt;/ref&gt; of salicylate as an essential micronutrient
|-
| Vitamin U
| [[S-Methylmethionine]]
| Protein metabolite; synthesized in body
|}

The reason that the set of vitamins skips directly from E to K is that the vitamins corresponding to letters F-J were either reclassified over time, discarded as false leads, or renamed because of their relationship to vitamin B, which became a complex of vitamins.

The German-speaking scientists who isolated and described vitamin K (in addition to naming it as such) did so because the vitamin is intimately involved in the ''Koagulation'' of blood following wounding. At the time, most (but not all) of the letters from F through to J were already designated, so the use of the letter K was considered quite reasonable.&lt;ref name=Bennett&gt;[http://www.lifeinyouryears.net/everyvitamin.pdf Every Vitamin Page] All Vitamins and Pseudo-Vitamins. Compiled by David Bennett.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =quiz&gt;[http://www.pubquizhelp.34sp.com/sci/vitamin.html Vitamins and minerals&amp;nbsp;– names and facts]&lt;/ref&gt; The table on the right lists chemicals that had previously been classified as vitamins, as well as the earlier names of vitamins that later became part of the B-complex.

==Anti-vitamins==
{{Main|Antinutrient}}
Anti-vitamins are chemical compounds that inhibit the absorption or actions of vitamins. For example, [[avidin]] is a protein in egg whites that inhibits the absorption of [[biotin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Roth KS |title=Biotin in clinical medicine—a review |journal=Am. J. Clin. Nutr. |volume=34 |issue=9 |pages=1967–74 |year=1981|pmid=6116428}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pyrithiamine is similar to thiamine, [[vitamin B1|vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;]], and inhibits the [[enzyme]]s that use thiamine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Rindi G, Perri V |title=Uptake of pyrithiamine by tissue of rats |journal=Biochem. J. |volume=80 |pages=214–6 |year=1961 |pmid=13741739 |pmc=1243973 |issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Food}}

{{colbegin}}
*[[Antioxidant]]
*[[Dietary supplement]]
*[[Dietetics]]
*[[Food composition]]
*[[Health freedom movement]]
*[[Illnesses related to poor nutrition]]
*[[Megavitamin therapy]]
*[[Nutrition]]
**[[Avitaminosis|Vitamin deficiency]]
**[[Dietary mineral]]s
**[[Essential amino acid]]s
**[[Essential nutrient]]s
**[[Nootropics]]
**[[Nutrient]]s
*[[Orthomolecular medicine]]
*[[Pharmacology]]
*[[Vitamin poisoning|Vitamin poisoning (overdose)]]
{{colend}}
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
&lt;!--========================{{No more links}}============================
 |PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia |fdvfgergd
 |is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
 |     |
 | Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED. |
 |See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details. |
 |     |
 |If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or |
 |replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
 |to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) |
 |and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template. |
==={{No more links}}=========--&gt;
{{EB1922 Poster|Vitamine}}
*[http://www.nal.usda.gov/fnic/dga/rda.pdf USDA RDA chart in PDF format]
*[http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/fn-an/nutrition/reference/table/ref_vitam_tbl_e.html Health Canada Dietary Reference Intakes Reference Chart for Vitamins]
*[http://dietary-supplements.info.nih.gov/Health_Information/Vitamin_and_Mineral_Supplement_Fact_Sheets.aspx NIH Office of Dietary Supplements: Fact Sheets]
*[http://dietary-supplements.info.nih.gov/factsheets/dietarysupplements.asp NIH Office of Dietary Supplements. Dietary Supplements: Background Information]
*[http://www.dietscalc.com/ Interactive table based on United States Department of Agriculture Database]
*[http://crdd.osdd.net/raghava/vitapred/ Vitapred] : A web server for predicting vitamin interacting residues in vitamin binding proteins 

{{Vitamin}}
{{Food chemistry}}
{{Nutritional pathology}}
{{Dietary supplement}}

{{Good article}}

[[Category:Essential nutrients]]
[[Category:Nutrition]]
[[Category:Vitamins|*]]</text>
      <sha1>mwa3z3ymwmn84aij43i2i9t5sgpqn8s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Saturday Night Live (season 35)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22729156</id>
    <revision>
      <id>542304563</id>
      <parentid>537821546</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-06T02:15:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>174.111.68.211</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28101">{{Infobox television season
 | season_name      = Saturday Night Live Season 35
 | bgcolor = #ff9200
 | fgcolour = #000000
 | show_name        = ''[[Saturday Night Live]]''
 | image            = [[Image:Saturday Night Live Title Card.jpeg]]
 | caption          = The ''Saturday Night Live'' title card as seen in the opening credits of the 35th season.
 | country          = [[American television|United States]]
 | network          = [[NBC]]
 | first_aired      = September 26, 2009
 | last_aired       = May 15, 2010
 | num_episodes     = 22
 | prev_season      = ''[[Saturday Night Live (season 34)|34]]''
 | next_season      = ''[[Saturday Night Live (season 36)|36]]''
 | episode_list = [[List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of ''Saturday Night Live'' episodes]]
}}
'''''[[Saturday Night Live]]''''' aired its '''thirty-fifth season''' during the 2009–2010 television season on [[NBC]]. This season began on September 26, 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= Megan Fox to host 35th season premiere of SNL  |url= http://www.nydailynews.com/gossip/2009/08/22/2009-08-22_snl.html|date= 2009-08-22|publisher= New York Daily News|accessdate= 2010-02-13 | first=Joanna | last=Sloame}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ended on May 15, 2010.

A total of 22 episodes were broadcast during the show's eight-month-long season, which included a two-week break in February due to the [[2010 Winter Olympics]].  The season was accompanied by three prime-time episodes of ''[[Saturday Night Live Weekend Update Thursday]]'' and three prime-time ''SNL'' [[clip show]]s.

Prior to the start of the season, many cast changes occurred. [[Darrell Hammond]], the last cast member from the 1990s, left the show after a record 14 seasons in the cast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Darrell Hammond Leaving &quot;SNL&quot;&amp;nbsp;— Hammond Retires From &quot;Saturday Night Live&quot;|url= http://www.popcrunch.com/darrell-hammond-leaving-snl-hammond-retires-from-saturday-night-live/|date=2009-10-08|accessdate= 2010-02-13|month= October|publisher= PopCrunch.com|quote= After fourteen seasons, comedian Darrell Hammond has announced his retirement from Saturday Night Live.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Featured players [[Michaela Watkins]] and [[Casey Wilson]] were both let go from the show before the start of the season.&lt;ref name=&quot;ah&quot;&gt;{{cite web| publisher=[[Access Hollywood]] | url= http://www.accesshollywood.com/michaela-watkins-and-casey-wilson-leaving-saturday-night-live-kristen-wiig-to-join-weekend-update_article_2259 | title=Michaela Watkins &amp; Casey Wilson Leaving ''Saturday Night Live'', Kristen Wiig To Join ''Weekend Update''?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To fill their absence the show brought in two new featured players, [[Nasim Pedrad]] and [[Jenny Slate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/09/01/jenny-slate-nasim-pedrad_n_274499.html |title=Jenny Slate &amp; Nasim Pedrad: SNL's New Hires (VIDEO) |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= September 1, 2009|accessdate=2011-03-28 |first=Alex |last=Leo}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Abby Elliott]] and [[Bobby Moynihan]] continued as featured players.

A notable moment of the season was when an [[internet activism|internet campaign]] was created to get actress [[Betty White]] to host an episode of the show. The campaign was started in early 2010 on [[Facebook]] and [[Facebook features#Networks, groups and like pages|the group]] was called &quot;Betty White to Host SNL (please?)!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;whitefacebook&quot; /&gt; The campaign was successful, and White became the [[Saturday Night Live hosts#Oldest guests|oldest person ever to host]] the show. For White's episode, [[Lorne Michaels]] brought back former cast members [[Rachel Dratch]], [[Tina Fey]], [[Ana Gasteyer]], [[Amy Poehler]], [[Maya Rudolph]] and [[Molly Shannon]].   The episode garnered its highest ratings in over a year. with a rating of 5.8 in the 18–49 rating, demographic and with 12.1 million viewers overall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Seidman |first=Robert |url=http://tvbythenumbers.com/2010/05/13/update-betty-white-hosting-turn-on-saturday-night-live-averages-12-1-million-viewers-and-a-4-6-rating-with-adults-18-49/51308 |title=Update: Betty White Hosting Turn on &quot;Saturday Night Live&quot; Averages 12.1 Million Viewers and a 4.6 Rating With Adults 18–49 |publisher=Tvbythenumbers.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This season would also be the last for longtime cast member [[Will Forte]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://popwatch.ew.com/2010/08/26/snl-will-forte-leaving/ Will Forte leaves SNL]&lt;/ref&gt; who had been on the show since 2002. This would also be the only season for featured player [[Jenny Slate]], who was let go after the season ended.

==Cast==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
;Repertory players
*[[Fred Armisen]]
*[[Will Forte]]
*[[Bill Hader]]
*'''[[Seth Meyers]]'''
*[[Andy Samberg]]
*[[Jason Sudeikis]]
*[[Kenan Thompson]]
*[[Kristen Wiig]]
{{col-2}}
;Featured players
*[[Abby Elliott]]
*[[Bobby Moynihan]]
*[[Nasim Pedrad]]
*[[Jenny Slate]]

{{col-end}}

*&lt;small&gt;'''bold''' denotes Weekend Update anchor only&lt;/small&gt;

==Writers==
{{Main|List of Saturday Night Live writers#Season 35}}
Season 35 would prove to be the final season with [[Lonely Island]] member [[Jorma Taccone]] as a writer.

==Episodes==
{{seealso|List of Saturday Night Live episodes}}
&lt;onlyinclude&gt;{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot;
|+ ''Saturday Night Live'' season 35 episodes
|-
!  style=&quot;background:#ff9200;&quot; width=&quot;5%&quot; | &lt;small&gt;No.&lt;small/&gt;
!  style=&quot;background:#ff9200;&quot; width=&quot;5%&quot; | #
!  style=&quot;background:#ff9200;&quot; width=&quot;35%&quot; | Host(s)
!  style=&quot;background:#ff9200;&quot; width=&quot;35%&quot; | Musical guest(s)
!  style=&quot;background:#ff9200;&quot; width=&quot;20%&quot; | Original airdate

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=659
|EpisodeNumber2=1
|OriginalAirDate = September 26, 2009
|RTitle=[[Megan Fox]]
|Aux1=[[U2]]
|ShortSummary=U2 performed &quot;[[Breathe (U2 song)|Breathe]]&quot;, &quot;[[Moment of Surrender]]&quot; and &quot;[[Ultraviolet (Light My Way)]]&quot;.

This episode is newly-hired cast member [[Jenny Slate]]'s first appearance on ''SNL'', and [[Nasim Pedrad]]'s first full episode.

A new opening sequence which mentions SNL's 35 years on-air debuts with this episode.

During the &quot;Biker Chick Chat&quot; sketch, Jenny Slate accidentally says, &quot;You stood up for yourself, and I fuckin' love you for that!&quot; Most of the sketch before and after consisted of everyone saying &quot;Friggin',&quot; &quot;frickin'&quot; or &quot;freakin'&quot;. Slate quickly holds her breath after realizing her mistake.

[[Brian Austin Green]] cameoed in the Transformers Digital Short.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=660
|EpisodeNumber2=2
|OriginalAirDate = October 3, 2009
|RTitle=[[Ryan Reynolds]]
|Aux1=[[Lady Gaga]]
|ShortSummary=Lady Gaga performed &quot;[[Paparazzi (Lady Gaga song)|Paparazzi]]&quot; and a medley of songs including &quot;[[Bad Romance]]&quot;, &quot;[[LoveGame]]&quot; and &quot;[[Poker Face (Lady Gaga song)|Poker Face]]&quot;. As well, she appeared with [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] in [[Deep House Dish]], and in another sketch after her second performance.

[[Elijah Wood]] appeared in the [[SNL Digital Short]].

[[Scarlett Johansson]] (Reynolds' then-wife) appeared in the &quot;Porcelain Fountains&quot; ad portraying the same Lexi character that she played during her two hosting appearances.

[[Darrell Hammond]] appears as [[Governor of California|California Governor]] [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]] during [[Weekend Update]].
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=661
|EpisodeNumber2=3
|OriginalAirDate = October 10, 2009
|RTitle=[[Drew Barrymore]]
|Aux1=[[Regina Spektor]]
|ShortSummary=Regina Spektor performed &quot;[[Eet]]&quot; and &quot;The Calculation&quot;.

[[Justin Long]] appeared as [[Matthew McConaughey]] in a sketch called &quot;Celebrity Ghost Stories&quot;. He summarized the plot of McConaughey's movie, [[Ghosts of Girlfriends Past]].
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=662
|EpisodeNumber2=4
|OriginalAirDate = October 17, 2009
|RTitle=[[Gerard Butler]]
|Aux1=[[Shakira]]
|ShortSummary=Shakira performed &quot;[[She Wolf (Shakira song)|She Wolf]]&quot; and &quot;[[Did It Again (Shakira song)|Did It Again]]&quot;.

[[Dwayne Johnson]] made a cameo reprising his role as &quot;The Rock&quot; Obama in the cold opening.

During the advertisements, outtakes from dress rehearsal from the 1990s and 2000s were shown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Steinberg |first=Brian |url=http://adage.com/madisonandvine/article?article_id=139716 |title=Bud Light Golden Wheat to Be Sole Advertiser on Next 'SNL' &amp;#124; News – Advertising Age |publisher=Adage.com |date=2009-10-15 |accessdate=2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[James Franco]] appeared as himself in the sketch &quot;[[What Up With That]]&quot;.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=663
|EpisodeNumber2=5
|OriginalAirDate = November 7, 2009
|RTitle=[[Taylor Swift]]
|Aux1=Taylor Swift]
|ShortSummary=Taylor Swift performed &quot;[[You Belong with Me]]&quot; and &quot;Untouchable&quot;. 

[[Amy Poehler]] returned to do another &quot;Really?! with Seth and Amy&quot; during [[Weekend Update]]. Poehler also introduced Swift's second performance. 
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=664
|EpisodeNumber2=6
|OriginalAirDate = November 14, 2009
|RTitle=[[January Jones]]
|Aux1=[[The Black Eyed Peas]]
|ShortSummary=Black Eyed Peas performed &quot;[[I Gotta Feeling]]&quot;, &quot;[[Meet Me Halfway]]&quot; and &quot;[[Boom Boom Pow]]&quot;. The last song closed out the show and was played over the goodnights. They also appeared in the [[Today (NBC program)|Today Show]] sketch.

[[Darrell Hammond]] cameoed as [[Lou Dobbs]] on [[Weekend Update]].
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=665
|EpisodeNumber2=7
|OriginalAirDate = November 21, 2009
|RTitle=[[Joseph Gordon-Levitt]]
|Aux1=[[Dave Matthews Band]]
|ShortSummary=Dave Matthews Band performed &quot;[[You and Me (Dave Matthews Band song)|You and Me]]&quot; and &quot;Shake Me Like a Monkey&quot;.

[[Joseph Gordon-Levitt]]'s opening monologue is a song and dance tribute to [[Donald O'Connor]]'s &quot;[[Make 'Em Laugh]]&quot; number in ''[[Singin' in the Rain]]''.

[[Dave Matthews]] cameoed as [[Ozzy Osbourne]] in &quot;The Mellow Show with Jack Johnson&quot;, while [[Bill Hader]] portrayed Matthews.

[[Al Gore]] cameoed in the &quot;[[What Up With That]]&quot; sketch and on [[Weekend Update]], promoting NBC &quot;Green Week&quot; and his new book.

[[Mindy Kaling]] cameoed in &quot;[[What Up With That]]&quot; as the 2nd guest.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=666
|EpisodeNumber2=8
|OriginalAirDate= December 5, 2009
|RTitle=[[Blake Lively]]
|Aux1=[[Rihanna]]
|ShortSummary=Rihanna performed &quot;[[Russian Roulette (song)|Russian Roulette]]&quot; and &quot;[[Hard (song)|Hard]]&quot; and appeared in the [[SNL Digital Short]].

[[Young Jeezy]] performed with Rihanna for her second song.

On this episode's installment of [[Weekend Update]], [[Abby Elliott]] appeared as actress-singer [[Brittany Murphy]], following a report about Murphy's alleged firing from a recent film. This portion of ''Update'' was cut from reruns in light of Murphy's death later that month.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=667
|EpisodeNumber2=9
|OriginalAirDate= December 12, 2009
|RTitle=[[Taylor Lautner]]
|Aux1=[[Bon Jovi]]
|ShortSummary=Bon Jovi performed &quot;[[Superman Tonight]]&quot; and &quot;[[When We Were Beautiful (song)|When We Were Beautiful]]&quot;.

This episode was dedicated to the memory of Heino Ripp, SNL's technical director from 1975 to 1983.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=668
|EpisodeNumber2=10
|OriginalAirDate= December 19, 2009
|RTitle=[[James Franco]]
|Aux1=[[Muse (band)|Muse]]
|ShortSummary=Muse performed &quot;[[Uprising (song)|Uprising]]&quot; and &quot;[[Starlight (Muse song)|Starlight]]&quot;.

[[Mike Tyson]] and [[Jack McBrayer]] appeared during &quot;[[What Up With That]]&quot;.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=669
|EpisodeNumber2=11
|OriginalAirDate= January 9, 2010
|RTitle=[[Charles Barkley]]
|Aux1=[[Alicia Keys]]
|ShortSummary=Alicia Keys performed &quot;[[Try Sleeping with a Broken Heart]]&quot; and &quot;[[Empire State of Mind (Part II) Broken Down]]&quot; and appeared in the [[SNL Digital Short]].

The original east coast airing was delayed 35 minutes due to the [[Dallas Cowboys|Cowboys]]-[[Philadelphia Eagles|Eagles]] NFC Wild Card game running long.

This episode attracted 10.4 million viewers, and was the second highest-rated episode of the season.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tvbythenumbers.com/2010/01/14/charles-barkley-leads-saturday-night-live-to-10-4-million-best-performance-in-14-months/38980|date=2010-01-14 ]{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=670
|EpisodeNumber2=12
|OriginalAirDate= January 16, 2010
|RTitle=[[Sigourney Weaver]]
|Aux1=[[The Ting Tings]]
|ShortSummary=The Ting Tings performed &quot;[[That's Not My Name]]&quot; and &quot;[[Shut Up and Let Me Go]]&quot;.

[[Darrell Hammond]] cameoed as [[Jay Leno]] in the cold open.

[[James Cameron]] cameoed as himself in the [[SNL Digital Short]].
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=671
|EpisodeNumber2=13
|OriginalAirDate= January 30, 2010
|RTitle=[[Jon Hamm]]
|Aux1=[[Michael Bublé]]
|ShortSummary=Michael Bublé performed &quot;[[Haven't Met You Yet]]&quot; and &quot;[[Baby (You've Got What It Takes)]]&quot; and appeared in the &quot;Hamm and Bublé&quot; sketch.

[[Sharon Jones (singer)|Sharon Jones]] sang with Michael Bublé for his second song.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=672
|EpisodeNumber2=14
|OriginalAirDate= February 6, 2010
|RTitle=[[Ashton Kutcher]]
|Aux1=[[Them Crooked Vultures]]
|ShortSummary=Them Crooked Vultures performed &quot;[[Mind Eraser, No Chaser]]&quot; and &quot;[[New Fang]]&quot;. As well, [[Dave Grohl]] appeared in a sketch after Them Crooked Vultures' second performance.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=673
|EpisodeNumber2=15
|OriginalAirDate= February 27, 2010
|RTitle=[[Jennifer Lopez]]
|Aux1=Jennifer Lopez
|ShortSummary=Jennifer Lopez performed &quot;[[Love? (album)|Until it Beats No More]]&quot; and &quot;[[Love? (album)|Starting Over]]&quot;.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=674
|EpisodeNumber2=16
|OriginalAirDate= March 6, 2010
|RTitle=[[Zach Galifianakis]]
|Aux1=[[Vampire Weekend]]
|ShortSummary=Vampire Weekend performed &quot;[[Cousins (song)|Cousins]]&quot; and &quot;[[Giving Up the Gun]]&quot;.

[[Brian Williams]], [[Jack McBrayer]], [[Jane Krakowski]], [[Mehmet Oz]], [[Anthony Anderson]], and [[Jeremy Sisto]] all appeared during the [[SNL Digital Short]], &quot;Zach Drops by the Set&quot;.

[[Paul Rudd]] and [[Frank Rich]] appeared during &quot;[[What Up With That]]&quot;.

Galifianakis shaved his beard before the last sketch of the show and wears a fake beard during the goodnights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nbc.com/saturday-night-live/video/clips/snl-backstage-zach-shaves-his-beard/1207127/ |title=Saturday Night Live – SNL Backstage: Zach Shaves His Beard – Video |publisher=NBC.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=675
|EpisodeNumber2=17
|OriginalAirDate= March 13, 2010
|RTitle=[[Jude Law]]
|Aux1=[[Pearl Jam]]
|ShortSummary=Pearl Jam performed &quot;[[Just Breathe (song)|Just Breathe]]&quot; and &quot;[[Unthought Known]]&quot; and appeared in the &quot;[[Twilight Zone]]&quot; [[Nightmare at 20,000 Feet]] parody.

[[Julian Casablancas]] sang &quot;[[Boombox (The Lonely Island song)|Boombox]]&quot; with [[The Lonely Island]] in the [[SNL Digital Short]].

[[Jerry Seinfeld]] cameoed on [[Weekend Update]] to do &quot;Really?! With Seth and Jerry&quot;.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=676
|EpisodeNumber2=18
|OriginalAirDate= April 10, 2010
|RTitle=[[Tina Fey]]
|Aux1=[[Justin Bieber]]
|ShortSummary=[[Justin Bieber]] performed &quot;[[Baby (Justin Bieber song)|Baby]]&quot; and &quot;[[U Smile]]&quot; and appeared in two sketches. Bieber also appeared in Fey's monologue.

[[Mark Sanchez]] and [[Steve Martin]] made cameo appearances during Fey's monologue.

Fey reprised her impersonation of [[Sarah Palin]] on the fake commercial &quot;The Sarah Palin Network.&quot;

Fey received a [[62nd Primetime Emmy Awards|2010 Emmy Award]] nomination as herself for Guest Actress in a Comedy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Emmy nomination list&quot;&gt;[http://www.emmys.com/sites/emmys.com/files/62ndemmys_noms.pdf Emmy nomination list]&lt;/ref&gt;
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=677
|EpisodeNumber2=19
|OriginalAirDate= April 17, 2010
|RTitle=[[Ryan Phillippe]]
|Aux1=[[Kesha]]
|ShortSummary=Ke$ha performed &quot;[[Tik Tok (song)|Tik Tok]]&quot; and &quot;[[Your Love Is My Drug]]&quot;.

Phillippe promoted the film ''[[MacGruber (film)|MacGruber]]'', the first new ''SNL'' movie in over a decade.  
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=678
|EpisodeNumber2=20
|OriginalAirDate= April 24, 2010
|RTitle=[[Gabourey Sidibe]]
|Aux1=[[MGMT]]
|ShortSummary=MGMT performed &quot;[[Flash Delirium]]&quot; and &quot;[[Congratulations (MGMT album)|Brian Eno]]&quot;.

SNL writer [[John Mulaney]] appeared as himself in a [[Weekend Update]] commentary on girl scout cookies.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=679
|EpisodeNumber2=21
|OriginalAirDate= May 8, 2010
|RTitle=[[Betty White]]
|Aux1=[[Jay-Z]]
|ShortSummary=In early 2010, an online campaign was created on [[Facebook]] to get White to host an episode of the show. The group was called ''Betty White to Host SNL (please?)!''&lt;ref name=&quot;whitefacebook&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.facebook.com/pages/Betty-White-to-Host-SNL-please/266442514828?v=info#!/pages/Betty-White-to-Host-SNL-please/266442514828?v=wall |title=Niet compatibele browser |publisher=Facebook |date= |accessdate=2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The movement was sparked by White's appearance in a [[Snickers]] commercial aired during [[Super Bowl XLIV]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}  Because of this, White is the first person to ever host based on an [[internet]] movement created by fans. The commercial itself aired during one of the commercial breaks.

With this episode, White, at age 88, is the oldest person ever to host the show, surpassing [[Miskel Spillman]], the winner of ''SNL'''s &quot;Anyone Can Host&quot; contest in 1977.&lt;ref name=&quot;usatoday.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/television/news/2010-03-11-bettywhite11_ST_N.htm | publisher=[[USA Today]] | title=Live, from New York, it's ... Betty White hosting 'SNL' | first=Gary | last=Levin | date=March 12, 2010 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the first set, Jay-Z performed a medley of &quot;[[The Black Album (Jay-Z album)|Public Service Announcement]]&quot;, &quot;[[On to the Next One]]&quot;, &quot;[[99 Problems]]&quot;, &quot;[[03 Bonnie and Clyde]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Empire State of Mind]],&quot; featuring back-up singer [[Bridget Kelly]]. During &quot;99 Problems&quot;, Jay-Z's band samples &quot;Points of Authority&quot; by [[Linkin Park]]. For the second set, Jay-Z performed &quot;[[Young Forever]]&quot; with [[Mr Hudson]], which he dedicated to White.

Former SNL cast members [[Rachel Dratch]], [[Tina Fey]], [[Ana Gasteyer]], [[Amy Poehler]], [[Maya Rudolph]] and [[Molly Shannon]] appeared throughout the show. Gasteyer and Shannon reprised their characters from the [[The Delicious Dish]] sketches. Shannon also reprised her character Sally O'Malley during Weekend Update. Rudolph reprised her impression of [[Whitney Houston]] during Weekend Update. Fey and Poehler returned to Update as well, to participate in ''Really!?!''.

This episode was nominated for seven [[62nd Primetime Emmy Awards|2010 Emmy Awards]].

White won an Emmy for Guest Actress in a Comedy for hosting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Emmy nomination list&quot;/&gt;
|LineColor=ff9200
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=680
|EpisodeNumber2=22
|OriginalAirDate= May 15, 2010
|RTitle=[[Alec Baldwin]]
|Aux1=[[Tom Petty and the Heartbreakers]]
|ShortSummary=[[Will Forte]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://artsbeat.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/08/26/will-forte-is-leaving-saturday-night-live/ Will Forte is Leaving Saturday Night Live]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jenny Slate]]'s final episode as cast members.

Tom Petty and the Heartbreakers performed &quot;I Should Have Known It&quot; and &quot;Jefferson Jericho Blues&quot;, two songs from their 2010 album ''[[Mojo (album)|Mojo]]''. [[Tom Petty|Petty]] appeared in the [[SNL Digital Short]].

Steve Martin made a cameo appearance in the opening monologue.
|LineColor=ff9200
}}
|}&lt;/onlyinclude&gt;

==Specials==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot;
|-
! width=&quot;5%&quot; | #
! width=&quot;50%&quot; | Special
! width=&quot;45%&quot; | Original airdate

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=1
|Title= Saturday Night Live Presents: A Very Gilly Christmas
|OriginalAirDate = December 17, 2009
|ShortSummary=Holiday-themed sketches [[clip show|from past episodes]] are aired, including [[Adam Sandler]]'s &quot;The Hanukkah Song&quot;, [[Justin Timberlake]] and [[Andy Samberg]]'s &quot;[[Dick In A Box]]&quot; [[SNL Digital Short|Digital Short]], [[Delicious Dish]] and many more.

[[Alec Baldwin]] and [[Steve Martin]] make guest appearances.

[[Kristen Wiig]] hosts as her character Gilly, with [[Will Forte]], [[Kenan Thompson]], [[Bobby Moynihan]] and [[Abby Elliott]] reprising their roles as the sketch's supporting characters.
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=2
|Title= Saturday Night Live Presents: Sports All-Stars
|OriginalAirDate = January 31, 2010
|ShortSummary=[[Will Forte]] and [[Jason Sudeikis]] host the show as Pete Twinkle and Greg Stink, their recurring [[ESPN Classic]] sports announcer characters.

Sketches featuring appearances by professional athletes including: [[Peyton Manning]], [[Derek Jeter]], [[LeBron James]], [[Michael Jordan]], [[Tom Brady]], [[Charles Barkley]] and others are shown (most of which previously appeared in last year's ''SNL'' [[clip show]] special about sports-related sketches).
}}

{{Episode list/sublist|List of Saturday Night Live episodes|List of Saturday Night Live episodes
|EpisodeNumber=3
|Title= [[Saturday Night Live in the 2000s|Saturday Night Live in the 2000s: Time and Again]]
|OriginalAirDate = April 15, 2010
|ShortSummary= The special featured insight on the show during the 2000s: topics discussed include [[Jimmy Fallon]] and [[Tina Fey]] as the new [[Weekend Update]] anchors after the departure of [[Colin Quinn]], how ''SNL'' became popular for its spoofs on the 2000 [[United States presidential election]], how the show's humor survived the [[9/11]] attacks and the [[anthrax]] scare, [[Will Ferrell]]'s departure at the end of season 27 and the search for a replacement cast member to play George W. Bush, ''SNL'''s shaky years between seasons 28 and 30 due to Jimmy Fallon's and [[Horatio Sanz]]'s cracking up on camera, Jimmy Fallon's departure from the show, Amy Poehler teaming up with Tina Fey for Weekend Update, the hiring of Bill Hader, Andy Samberg, and Kristen Wiig, and ''SNL'' regaining its popularity with the [[Digital Shorts]], its return from the WGA strike of 2007–2008, the introduction of new fan-favorite hosts like Justin Timberlake and Jon Hamm, and the 2008 U.S. Presidential Election.

[[Fred Armisen]], [[Alec Baldwin]], [[Rachel Dratch]], [[Abby Elliott]], [[Jimmy Fallon]], [[Will Ferrell]], [[Tina Fey]], [[Will Forte]], [[Bill Hader]], [[Darrell Hammond]], [[Chris Kattan]], [[Marci Klein]], [[John McCain]],  [[Seth Meyers]], [[Lorne Michaels]], [[Tracy Morgan]], [[Bobby Moynihan]], [[Chris Parnell]], [[Amy Poehler]], [[Maya Rudolph]], [[Andy Samberg]], [[Horatio Sanz]], [[Akiva Schaffer]], [[Molly Shannon]], [[Michael Shoemaker]], [[Jason Sudeikis]], [[Jorma Taccone]], [[Kenan Thompson]], [[Justin Timberlake]], [[Christopher Walken]] and [[Kristen Wiig]] provided comments for the special.
}}
|}

===Saturday Night Live Weekend Update Thursday===
{{Main|Saturday Night Live Weekend Update Thursday}}
The second season of ''Saturday Night Live Weekend Update Thursday'', a [[limited-run series]] based on Saturday Night Live's &quot;''[[Weekend Update]]''&quot; sketch, has aired in conjunction with this season. The show is hosted by [[Seth Meyers]], ''Update''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s current host, and former ''Update'' co-host [[Amy Poehler]]. Like the sketch, the show is a parody of local news broadcasts and satirizes contemporary news stories and figures. As of June 2010, three episodes have aired. An additional three episodes were scheduled to air in spring 2010, but were scrapped.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/04/arts/television/04nbc.html?_r=1&amp;ref=television | title=Return of 'Weekend Update Thursday | publisher=The New York Times | first=Bill | last=Carter | date=May 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Episode number
!Original airdate
!Notes
|-
| {{Anchor|show2009thursday1}} Episode 1
|September 17, 2009
|
*[[Amy Poehler]] appears as a special guest to co-anchor ''Update'' alongside [[Seth Meyers]].
*[[Darrell Hammond]] appears as former [[United States President|president]] [[Jimmy Carter]].
|-
| {{Anchor|show2009thursday2}} Episode 2
|September 24, 2009
|
*[[Amy Poehler]] returns as a special guest to co-anchor ''Update'' alongside [[Seth Meyers]].
*Former ''Saturday Night Live'' cast member [[Darrell Hammond]] appears as [[Bill Clinton]] and [[Megan Fox]] parodies the finale of the soap opera ''[[Guiding Light]]''.
*Newly-hired ''Saturday Night Live'' featured player [[Nasim Pedrad]] appears for the first time in the cold open as [[Kathy Griffin]].
|-
| {{Anchor|show2009thursday3}} Episode 3
|October 1, 2009
|
*[[Darrell Hammond]] appears as [[Dennis Franz]] and [[Maya Rudolph]] appears as [[Oprah Winfrey]].
*This is the first ''Weekend Update Thursday'' episode not to feature a cold open.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}
|}

==MacGruber film==
The first SNL film since 2000's ''[[The Ladies Man (2000 film)|The Ladies Man]]'', ''[[MacGruber (film)|MacGruber]]'' was released on May 21, 2010.  The film, starring ''SNL'' cast members [[Will Forte]] and [[Kristen Wiig]] and former cast member [[Maya Rudolph]], is based on the &quot;[[MacGruber]]&quot; sketches from the show.  It received mixed reviews from critics and, in spite of a wide initial release, was a [[box office bomb]].  After a two-week opening commitment during which it was shown in 2,546 theaters, it was dropped from all but 177 theaters starting in its third week, a drop exceeded since 1982 only by ''[[Meet Dave]]'' and ''[[The Rocker (film)|The Rocker]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title= Biggest Theater Drops| url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/alltime/theaterdrops.htm | publisher= [[Box Office Mojo]] | accessdate=2010-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Saturday Night Live}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Saturday Night Live (Season 35)}}
[[Category:Saturday Night Live seasons|35]]
[[Category:2010 television seasons]]
[[Category:2009 television seasons]]</text>
      <sha1>nih1pto6kizkwwyr7b9rjencc6pqebs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>2006 Pacific typhoon season</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2401432</id>
    <revision>
      <id>540568713</id>
      <parentid>538832193</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-26T09:57:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 7 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q1195307]] ([[User talk:Addbot|Report Errors]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="76608">{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox hurricane season
| Basin=WPac
| Year=2006
| Track=2006 Pacific typhoon season summary.jpg
| First storm formed=January 20, 2006
| Last storm dissipated=December 19, 2006
| Strongest storm name=[[Typhoon Yagi (2006)|Yagi]]
| Strongest storm winds=105
| Strongest storm pressure=910
| Average wind speed=10
| Total depressions=30 &lt;!-- JTWC:4 (1,13,15&amp;17W) CMA:1 PAGASA:2 JMA:22 including Ioke --&gt;
| Total storms=23 official plus 2 unofficial
| Total hurricanes=15
| Total intense=7 (unofficial)
| Fatalities=At least 2,704
| Damages=35800
| Inflated=1
| five seasons=[[2004 Pacific typhoon season|2004]], [[2005 Pacific typhoon season|2005]], '''2006''', [[2007 Pacific typhoon season|2007]], [[2008 Pacific typhoon season|2008]]|}
}}
{{Wikinews category|Hurricane season, 2006}}
The '''2006 Pacific typhoon season''' had no official bounds; it ran year-round in 2006, but most [[tropical cyclone]]s tend to form in the northwestern Pacific Ocean between May and November.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.typhoon2000.ph/garyp_mgtcs/may03sum.txt {{WebCite|url=http://www.webcitation.org/5v6pTB3S4|date =December 19, 2010| accessdate=December 20, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; These dates conventionally delimit the period of each year when most tropical cyclones form in the northwestern Pacific Ocean.

The scope of this article is limited to the Pacific Ocean, north of the equator and west of the [[international date line]]. Storms that form east of the date line and north of the equator are called hurricanes; see [[2006 Pacific hurricane season]]. Tropical Storms formed in the entire West Pacific basin are assigned a name by the [[Japan Meteorological Agency]]. Tropical depressions in this basin have the &quot;W&quot; suffix added to their number. In addition, the [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration]] (PAGASA) assigns names to tropical cyclones (including tropical depressions) that enter or form in the Philippine area of responsibility. These names, however, are not in common use outside of the Philippines.

==Storms==
{{See also|Timeline of the 2006 Pacific typhoon season}}

In storm information below, windspeed advisories differ from the Joint Typhoon Warning Center to the Japan Meteorological Agency as the JTWC uses the U.S. criteria of 1-minute mean to designate maximum sustained winds, while the JMA uses the 10-minute mean wind criteria to designate tropical cyclone maximum sustained winds. This difference generally means that JTWC maximum winds will appear to be higher than the maximum winds described by the JMA for the same cyclone.

===Typhoon Chanchu (Caloy)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon Chanchu16-05-06.jpg
|Track=Chanchu 2006 track.png
|Formed=May 9
|Dissipated=May 19
|10-min winds=95
|1-min winds=125
|Pressure=930
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Chanchu}}
An area of disturbed weather formed around May 5 and moved westward. The [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] released a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]] on May 8, shortly before it upgraded the storm to a Tropical Depression. It became a tropical storm on May 9. The name &quot;Chanchu&quot; was submitted by [[Macau]] and means [[pearl]]. The JTWC then upgraded it to a typhoon on May 10. The storm maintained a westerly track and made two landfalls in the [[Philippines]], causing 32 deaths in the country and $1.9&amp;nbsp;million in damage&lt;!--98.6 million pesos--&gt;, much of it to agriculture.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://today.reuters.co.uk/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=scienceNews&amp;storyID=2006-05-15T080918Z_01_MAN304331_RTRIDST_0_SCIENCE-WEATHER-PHILIPPINES-DC.XML&amp;archived=False |title=http://today.reuters.co.uk/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=science |publisher=Today.reuters.co.uk |date=February 9, 2009 |accessdate=October 19, 2010|archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5v6pVjG1h |archivedate = December 19, 2010|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Chanchu left the Philippines, the JMA upgraded it to a typhoon. Chanchu turned to the north in the [[South China Sea]] and affected hundreds of [[Vietnam]]ese fishermen. Then, it became a super typhoon, only the second ever recorded in the South China Sea, but was one for only less than a day. The only other super typhoon to form in the South China Sea in recorded history is [[Ryan]]{{dn|date=July 2012}} in 1995.&lt;ref name=&quot;jtwc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usno.navy.mil/NOOC/nmfc-ph/RSS/jtwc/atcr/1995atcr/pdf/wnp/19w.pdf |title=upf7221.tmp |format=PDF |accessdate=October 19, 2010|archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5tc56y2PN |archivedate = October 20, 2010|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chanchu is also the most intense typhoon on [[Hong Kong Observatory]]'s record to enter the South China Sea in May. Chanchu necessitated the [[Hong Kong Tropical Cyclone Warning Signals|Strong Wind Signal no. 3]] in both Hong Kong and Macau.&lt;ref name=&quot;hko&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hko.gov.hk/cgi-bin/hko/warndb_e1.pl?opt=91&amp;tcname=CHANCHU&amp;submit=Submit+Query |title=HKO Warnings/Signals Database |publisher=Hko.gov.hk |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;smg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thestandard.com.hk/news_detail.asp?pp_cat=11&amp;art_id=18859&amp;sid=7990894&amp;con_type=1 |title=Hong Kong's First FREE English Newspaper |work=The Standard |location=Hong Kong |location=Hong Kong |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It turned northeastward and made a final landfall along the southeastern seaboard of China on May 18 resulting in at least 25 deaths and a direct economic loss of 7&amp;nbsp;billion [[Chinese yuan|yuan]]. Chanchu became extratropical later that day.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Tropical Storm Jelawat (Domeng)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=03W Jelawat 28 jun 2006 0030Z.jpg
|Track=Jelawat 2006 track.png
|Formed=June 27
|Dissipated=June 29
|10-min winds=40
|1-min winds=45
|Pressure=996
}}
An area of disturbed weather that began as a part of a monsoon trough formed around June 23 east of the Philippines, and moved slowly over the islands. The [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] released a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]] on June 25 as the system moved over the Philippines, and upgraded the system to Tropical Depression 03W the next day. The depression continued to organize as it moved away from the Philippines, and the JTWC upgraded it to Tropical Storm 03W on June 27. The Japan Meteorological Agency designated the storm as Tropical Storm Jelawat shortly after. The name Jelawat was submitted by [[Malaysia]], and is a name for a type of [[carp]].

Jelawat moved generally northwestward over the [[South China Sea]] during the next day, and weakened back to a tropical depression on June 28. The depression made landfall in southern China at 7:40&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[Chinese Standard Time|CST]] on June 29 and dissipated later that day.

The storm dropped heavy rainfall across southern China and [[Haikou]] recorded a rainfall of 309.7&amp;nbsp;mm (12&amp;nbsp;inches) during the storm passage.  A total of 8.6&amp;nbsp;inches (220&amp;nbsp;mm) rain fell in 16 hours in [[Kampung Bundu]], Malaysia. The rainfall killed seven people and left one missing. The flooding from Jelawat ruined 200 square kilometres of farmland and destroyed 190 houses.&lt;ref name=&quot;shanghaidaily&quot;&gt;[http://www.shanghaidaily.com/art/2006/06/30/284709/Deadly_storms_strike_across_China.htm Shanghai Daily | 上海日报&amp;nbsp;– English Window to China News]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Ewiniar (Ester)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Ewiniar 7 July 2006.jpg
|Track=Ewiniar 2006 track.png
|Formed=June 30
|Dissipated=July 10
|10-min winds=100
|1-min winds=130
|Pressure=930
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Ewiniar (2006)}}
On June 29, a persistent tropical disturbance was classified as a tropical depression by the JTWC while east of [[Palau]]. The depression moved northwestward and was upgraded to Tropical Storm 04W by the JTWC on June 30. The JMA designated the storm Tropical Storm Ewiniar at around the same time. The name &quot;Ewiniar&quot; was submitted by the [[Federated States of Micronesia]], and refers to a traditional storm god of [[Chuuk State|Chuuk]].

Ewiniar was responsible for at least 30 deaths in China, which it brushed as a typhoon. The typhoon gradually weakened as it moved over colder waters, and made landfall in South Korea on July 10 as a severe tropical storm. As Ewiniar moved across the country, it passed within {{convert|30|mi|km}} of  [[Seoul]]. No tropical cyclone had come that close to Seoul in recent years.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} The storm brought heavy rain that triggered floods and mudslides in the southern part of the country, killing at least six people.  Ewiniar became extratropical over the [[Sea of Japan]] on the same day.&lt;!-- more info [http://au.biz.yahoo.com/060717/17/szco.html here]. --&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Severe Tropical Storm Bilis (Florita)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=TS Bilis 2006 peak.jpg
|Track=Bilis 2006 track.png
|Formed=July 9
|Dissipated=July 15
|10-min winds=60
|1-min winds=50
|Pressure=970
}}
{{Main|Tropical Storm Bilis}}
A tropical disturbance northeast of [[Yap]] developed sufficient convection to be designated a tropical depression on July 8. The depression strengthened into a tropical storm the next day, and was designated Tropical Storm Bilis by the JMA. The word &quot;Bilis&quot;, submitted by the [[Philippines]], means speed or swiftness. PAGASA operationally treated this storm as a typhoon for a short time on July 13, but it officially remained a tropical storm as it moved west-northwestward toward [[Taiwan]].  After moving over northern Taiwan, Bilis made landfall in [[Fujian]], China at 12:50&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[Chinese Standard Time|CST]] on July 14, weakening into a tropical depression inland the next day. JMA carried the system as a tropical depression until July 17.  Bilis brought very heavy rain, widespread flooding, landslides, and strong winds to the [[Philippines]], Taiwan and areas of mainland China, causing 672 deaths and $4.4&amp;nbsp;billion (2006 US$) in damage.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Kaemi (Glenda)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=06W-Kaemi.jpg
|Track=Kaemi 2006 track.png
|Formed=July 19
|Dissipated=July 26
|10-min winds=85
|1-min winds=75
|Pressure=960
}}
A tropical depression formed on July 18 near the [[Caroline Islands]], it quickly strengthened to tropical storm strength the same day. On July 19, the storm was named Kaemi by the JMA. The correct name Gaemi was submitted by South Korea and is a Korean word for [[ant]]. It strengthened into a severe tropical storm on July 20, and further deepened into a typhoon 24 hours later. Kaemi made landfall in [[Jinjiang, Fujian|Jinjiang]], Fujian at 3:50&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[Chinese Standard Time|CST]] on July 25 as a minimal typhoon.

Heavy rainfall in Taiwan caused flooding and four minor injuries. Rain also fell heavily in the northern Philippines.&lt;ref name=&quot;trmm&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://trmm.gsfc.nasa.gov/publications_dir/kaemi_july06.html |title=Trmm Sees Typhoon Kaemi |publisher=Trmm.gsfc.nasa.gov |date=July 21, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The storm has also killed at least 32&amp;nbsp;people in China, while another 60&amp;nbsp;people are missing. Agricultural losses in Taiwan amounted to NT$73&amp;nbsp;million (US$2.2&amp;nbsp;million).&lt;ref&gt;[http://exploreourpla.net/global-warming/storms/typhoon-kaemi-made-landfall-in-taidong-taiwan-fujian-china.html ] {{Wayback|url=http://exploreourpla.net/global-warming/storms/typhoon-kaemi-made-landfall-in-taidong-taiwan-fujian-china.html|date =20071012103910}}&lt;/ref&gt; Total damages from the storm amounted to $450&amp;nbsp;million.

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Prapiroon (Henry)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon Prapiroon 02 aug 2006 0550Z.jpg
|Track=Prapiroon 2006 track.png
|Formed=August 1
|Dissipated=August 5
|10-min winds=65
|1-min winds=70
|Pressure=970
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Prapiroon (2006)}}
PAGASA named a system east of the [[Philippines]] as Tropical Depression Henry later on the same day that the JMA recognised it as a tropical depression on July 28. The JTWC upgraded this system to a tropical storm on the morning of August 1. [[Hong Kong Observatory]] also did so and issued the Tropical Cyclone Signal No. 1 that same afternoon, and shortly after the JMA upgraded the system to Tropical Storm Prapiroon. The name Prapiroon was submitted by [[Thailand]] and is the name of a Thai rain deity. The JMA upgraded the storm to a severe tropical storm on the morning of August 2. PAGASA ceased advisories on the storm shortly after as it moved out of its area of responsibility. The JTWC and the HKO upgraded Prapiroon to a typhoon at 3&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[UTC]], while the JMA officially upgraded it to a typhoon at 12&amp;nbsp;p.m. UTC (8&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[Hong Kong Time|HKT]]). Prapiroon necessitated the first Tropical Cyclone Signal No. 8 in Macau this year. In Hong Kong, the flag raising ceremony at the Golden Bauhinia Square was cancelled due to strong wind.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.info.gov.hk/gia/general/200608/03/P200608030083.htm |title=Flag raising ceremony cancelled |publisher=Info.gov.hk |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prapiroon made landfall at 7:20&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[Chinese Standard Time|CST]] on August 3.

The strong winds due to the storm resulted in 70% of flights being cancelled, delayed or diverted in the [[Hong Kong International Airport]], the highest since the opening in 1999. However, the airport remained open throughout the storm passage and many flights successfully landed or took off on August 3.  Inbound flights were rerouted to nearby airports and outbound flights were cancelled or postponed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2006/8/2/worldupdates/2006-08-02T130644Z_01_NOOTR_RTRJONC_0_-262076-1&amp;sec=Worldupdates |title=World Updates &amp;#124; The Star Online |publisher=Thestar.com.my |date= |accessdate=2012-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; On landfall in [[Guangdong]] province, China, it forced the evacuation of some 660,000&amp;nbsp;people and caused an estimated 5.4&amp;nbsp;billion Chinese yuan worth of damage. 77&amp;nbsp;people were reported killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2006-08/06/content_4925398.htm |title=Xinhua&amp;nbsp;– English |publisher=News.xinhuanet.com |date=August 6, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also affected [[Hunan]], Guangxi and [[Hainan]]. Prapiroon degenerated into an area of low pressure on August 6.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Maria===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon maria 2006.jpg
|Track=Maria 2006 track.png
|Formed=August 5
|Dissipated=August 10
|10-min winds=70
|1-min winds=60
|Pressure=975
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Maria (2006)}}
JMA identified a tropical depression southwest of [[Minami Torishima]] on August 4 and began issuing advisories. On August 5, the system had sufficiently strengthened to be named Tropical Storm Maria. The name Maria was submitted by the United States and is a common [[Chamorro people|Chamorro]] feminine [[given name|name]].

The JTWC designated this system as a tropical depression later that day before upgrading it to a tropical storm on August 6, while the JMA upgraded it to a severe tropical storm at 6&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[UTC]]. Maria turned to the north, threatening Japan's mainland. JTWC briefly upgraded Maria to a typhoon on August 7, but issued its final advisory two days later as it started to turn extratropical.

In their post season analyses, the JMA upgraded the storm to a 80&amp;nbsp;mph (130&amp;nbsp;km/h) typhoon, while the JTWC downgraded it  to a 70&amp;nbsp;mph (110&amp;nbsp;km/h) tropical storm.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Saomai (Juan)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon Saomai 10 aug 2006 0505Z.jpg
|Track=Saomai 2006 track.png
|Formed=August 5
|Dissipated=August 11
|10-min winds=105
|1-min winds=140
|Pressure=925
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Saomai}}
The JTWC identified a tropical depression near the [[Caroline Islands]] late on August 4 [[UTC]]. The JMA designated it as such at 12&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[UTC]] August 5. Nine hours later, the JTWC upgraded Tropical Depression 08W to a tropical storm, three hours before the JMA named it Saomai. The name is from the [[Vietnamese language|Vietnamese]] &quot;[[:vi:Sao Kim|sao Mai]]&quot;, meaning &quot;Morning Star&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vdict.com/?dictionary=2&amp;word=sao+mai&amp;typings=-1&amp;quickm=0&amp;autoc=0&amp;liststring=&amp;submit2=Lookup |title=Vietnamese Dictionary and Translation |publisher=VDict.com |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; a reference to the planet [[Venus]].

The JTWC designated it a typhoon at 3&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]] August 6. The JMA upgraded Saomai to a Severe Tropical Storm at 6&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]], and as it continued to strengthen, it was upgraded to a typhoon just 12 hours later. Saomai passed into the Area of Responsibility of PAGASA on August 8 and was named Typhoon Juan by PAGASA. On August 8, the storm underwent explosive development, and by August 9 it had become a Category&amp;nbsp;5-equivalent super typhoon.

Saomai made landfall in [[Zhejiang]], China on August 10 with maximum sustained winds of 115 [[knot (unit)|knots]] (1-minute mean), stronger than Chanchu earlier this season. Saomai was responsible for at least 458 deaths, mostly in China, and $2.5&amp;nbsp;billion (2006&amp;nbsp;USD) in damage.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Severe Tropical Storm Bopha (Inday)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=STS Bopha 2006.jpg
|Track=Bopha 2006 track.png
|Formed=August 6
|Dissipated=August 9
|10-min winds=55
|1-min winds=55
|Pressure=980
}}
The JMA identified a tropical depression in the open Pacific on August 5. PAGASA named this storm late on August 5 as it was forecast to enhance the southwest [[monsoon]] and bring rains to the [[Philippines]]. Around 1800&amp;nbsp;UTC, the JTWC declared that the system had developed into a tropical depression and gave it the number 10W.&lt;ref name=&quot;JTWCBT10W&quot;/&gt; JMA upgraded it to Tropical Storm Bopha on August 6. The name Bopha was submitted by [[Cambodia]] and is a flower and girls' name. Around this time, the JTWC also upgraded the system to a tropical storm.&lt;ref name=&quot;JTWCBT10W&quot;/&gt;

The JTWC recognised its existence as a tropical depression at 9&amp;nbsp;a.m. UTC the same day before upgrading it to a tropical storm at 3&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]]. The JMA then upgraded it to a severe tropical storm as it slowly churned westwards at 12&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[UTC]] August 7 before downgrading it 18 hours later. Bopha unexpectedly restrengthened into a severe tropical storm at 3&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[UTC]] August 8, before weakening back to a tropical storm at 12&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]].

Bopha later made landfall on [[Taiwan]] at about 2&amp;nbsp;a.m. local time on August 9. At this time, the JTWC reported that Bopha attained winds of 100&amp;nbsp;km/h (65&amp;nbsp;mph).&lt;ref name=&quot;JTWCBT10W&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Joint Typhoon Warning Center|year=2007|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=Tropical Storm 10W (Bopha) Best Track|url=http://www.usno.navy.mil/NOOC/nmfc-ph/RSS/jtwc/best_tracks/2006/2006s-bwp/bwp102006.txt}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tropical Storm Bopha then weakened into a tropical depression before degenerating into a remnant low on August 10.

The [[Rainband|outer bands]] of Tropical Storm Bopha produced heavy rains over northern [[Luzon]], triggering flooding that destroyed 1,200 homes and killed seven people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Staff Writer|publisher=Earthweek|date=August 11, 2006|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=Tropical Storm Bopha|url=http://www.uclick.com/widgets/ew/060811/ew060811c.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two of the fatalities occurred after a home was destroyed by a landslide in [[Kalinga|Kalinga Province]]. The landslide damaged 20 other homes, a church and a school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Associated Press|work=The China Post |location=Taiwan (ROC) |location=Taiwan (ROC)|date=August 9, 2006|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=Two children killed in RP landslide|url=http://www.chinapost.com.tw/asiapacific/detail.asp?ID=87496&amp;GRP=C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As Severe Tropical Storm Bopha approached the island on August 8, the meteorological agency in Taiwan issued land and sea warnings for most of the region. Residents were warned about the possibility of torrential rains, flooding and mudslides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Yu-huay Sun and Theresa Tang|publisher=Bloomberg News|date=August 8, 2006|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=Taiwan Issues Alert as Tropical Storm Bopha Nears (Update2)|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601080&amp;sid=aB2LPnlPgLpg&amp;refer=asia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the storm was forecast to directly impact the island, all businesses remained open and schools were not closed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Staff Writer|work=The China Post |location=Taiwan (ROC) |location=Taiwan (ROC)|date=August 9, 2006|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=Island prepares for storm Bopha; heavy rain likely|url=http://www.chinapost.com.tw/detail.asp?ID=87434&amp;GRP=A}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Hong Kong, the [[Hong Kong Observatory]] issued Standby Signal number one as Bopha came within {{convert|800|km|mi|abbr=on}} of the city on August 9.  This signal was later discontinued on August 11.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Hong Kong Observatory|publisher=World Meteorological Organization|year=2007|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=HKO Annual Tropical Cyclone Report: STS Bopha 2006|url=http://www.smg.gov.mo/www/cvm/typhoon/annualreport/e_tyrpt2006/e_bopha.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between August 9 and 10, the remnants of Bopha produced moderate rainfall around Hong Kong, peaking at {{convert|45.6|mm|in|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Staff Writer|publisher=Hong Kong Observatory|date=July 31, 2007|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=Tropical Storm Bopha rainfall amounts in Hong Kong|url=http://gb.weather.gov.hk/publica/tc/tc2006/english/table342.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wind gusts up to 110&amp;nbsp;km/h (70&amp;nbsp;mph) were also produced by the storm throughout the city.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Staff Writer|publisher=Hong Kong Observatory|date=July 31, 2007|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=Tropical Storm Bopha Winds in Hong Kong|url=http://gb.weather.gov.hk/publica/tc/tc2006/english/table341.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[storm surge]] of {{convert|0.48|m|ft|abbr=on}} was recorded in Tai Po Kau on August 8.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Staff Writer|publisher=Hong Kong Observatory|date=July 31, 2007|accessdate=August 2, 2009|title=Tropical Storm Bopha storm surge in Hong Kong|url=http://gb.weather.gov.hk/publica/tc/tc2006/english/table343.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Severe Tropical Storm Wukong===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Tropical Storm Wukong 2006-08-12 lrg.jpg
|Track=Wukong 2006 track.png
|Formed=August 13
|Dissipated=August 19
|10-min winds=50
|1-min winds=55
|Pressure=980
}}
{{Main|Tropical Storm Wukong (2006)}}
A tropical depression (11W from the JTWC) formed south of [[Iwo Jima]] on August 12. Early on August 13, as it moved to the north-northwest, the JTWC upgraded it to a tropical storm. The JMA named it Wukong later that day. [[Sun Wukong|Wukong]] was submitted by People's Republic of China, and it is the name of a character in a Chinese epic. Wukong absorbed Tropical Storm Sonamu shortly before landfall in Japan. Wukong then stalled over [[Kyūshū]], before starting to jog to the north-northwest. It was downgraded to a tropical depression on August 20.

In post-operational analysis by the JMA, Wukong was upgraded to a severe tropical storm.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Tropical Storm Sonamu (Katring)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=TS Sonamu 2006.jpg
|Track=Sonamu 2006 track.png
|Formed=August 14
|Dissipated=August 15
|10-min winds=35
|1-min winds=45
|Pressure=992
}}
On August 13, a tropical depression formed south of [[Naha, Okinawa]], and was named Katring by PAGASA and Sonamu by JMA. The name Sonamu was submitted by [[North Korea|DPR Korea]] and signifies a [[pine|pine tree]]. Sonamu began [[Fujiwhara interaction|interacting]] with nearby Tropical Storm Wukong on August 15, with the outflow from the stronger Wukong producing unfavourable shear over the cyclone. The JMA declared the system a tropical depression and stopped issuing advisories on August 16. The JTWC followed shortly after.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Ioke===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon Ioke 28 aug 2006 0130Z.jpg
|Track=Ioke 2006 track.png
|Formed=August 27 (entered basin)
|Dissipated=September 6
|10-min winds=105
|1-min winds=140
|Pressure=915
}}
{{Main|Hurricane Ioke}}
On August 27, [[List of storms in the 2006 Pacific hurricane season#Hurricane Ioke|Hurricane Ioke]], which had formed in the Central Pacific, crossed the [[International Date Line]] and entered the [[Japan Meteorological Agency]]'s Area of Responsibility at around 6&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[UTC]], keeping its name while being reclassified as Typhoon Ioke. Ioke had earlier affected [[Johnston Atoll]]. On August 31 the center of the typhoon passed very close to [[Wake Island]]; 200&amp;nbsp;people were evacuated from there in advance of its approach.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.khnl.com/Global/story.asp?S=5331801 |title=Hickam Airman To Evacuate Hundreds From Wake Island |publisher=Khnl.com |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Typhoon Ioke then passed just to the northeast of [[Minami Torishima]], which had been evacuated ahead of the storm, but as a weakened Category&amp;nbsp;3-equivalent typhoon. Ioke then turned to the northeast, weakening as it started undergoing extratropical transition. The JMA released its final advisory on September 7. The [[Extratropical cyclone|extratropical]] remnants of Ioke moved into the [[Bering Sea]] where it caused severe beach [[erosion]] along the western Alaskan coastline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Angela Hutti|year=2006|title=Storm on the Bering Sea|publisher=KTVA 11|accessdate=September 8, 2006|url=http://www.ktva.com/topstory/ci_4303106}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Shanshan (Luis)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=TyphoonShanshan-NRL16-9-06-modisvis250m.jpg
|Track=Shanshan 2006 track.png
|Formed=September 10
|Dissipated=September 18
|10-min winds=110
|1-min winds=120
|Pressure=919
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Shanshan (2006)}}
Hong Kong Observatory identified a tropical depression about 460&amp;nbsp;kilometres north of Yap on September 9, the same day the JMA recognised it. The JTWC declared the formation of Tropical Depression 14W the next day. On the afternoon of September 10, it entered the PAGASA AOR and was named Luis. Later at 12&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]] on the same day, the JMA upgraded the tropical depression to Tropical Storm Shanshan. The name Shanshan was contributed by Hong Kong and is a girls' [[given name|name]]. Shanshan quickly strengthened and was upgraded into a severe tropical storm on September 11 and a typhoon later that day. Shanshan weakened slightly on September 14, but quickly restrengthened and reached Category&amp;nbsp;4 status on the JTWC's scale. Shanshan passed through the [[Yaeyama Islands]] in the early morning hours of September 16. The JTWC reported that Shanshan was becoming [[extratropical cyclone|extratropical]] early on September 17, as the typhoon weakened to a tropical storm. The JTWC issued its final advisory on Shanshan later that day, and the JMA issued its last advisory on September 19, after Shanshan completed extratropical transition.

As Shanshan neared [[Taiwan]], the [[Central Weather Bureau]] and local officials warned of flooding and high winds. However, as Shanshan turned towards Japan, all warnings were cancelled. South Korean forecasters also issued warnings ahead of an expected landfall, but this did not materialise. Ships were diverted as ports were closed as a precaution, while some other boats were forced to remain docked. In Japan, more than 90,000&amp;nbsp;people were evacuated from [[Yamaguchi Prefecture]].

Over 200&amp;nbsp;people were injured by Shanshan and 11&amp;nbsp;people were killed, mostly in [[Kyūshū]], although two deaths were reported in South Korea. A tornado spawned by the typhoon caused a train derailment in [[Nobeoka, Miyazaki]], Japan which caused no fatalities. Peak gusts on [[Iriomote]] reached 155&amp;nbsp;mph (248&amp;nbsp;km/h). Flights and trains were delayed, while electricity was cut to about 3000 homes in Korea. A ship also sank off [[Ulleungdo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sg.news.yahoo.com/060918/1/43hma.html |title=Yahoo! News |publisher=Sg.news.yahoo.com |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Yagi===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=TyphoonYagi2006.jpg
|Track=Yagi 2006 track.png
|Formed=September 17
|Dissipated=September 25
|10-min winds=105
|1-min winds=140
|Pressure=910
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Yagi (2006)}}
The [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] identified an area of disturbed weather northeast of [[Chuuk State|Chuuk]] on September 13. The disturbance drifted to the north over the next few days, gradually increasing in organization. The JTWC issued a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]] on the disturbance on September 16, and both the JTWC and JMA declared the system a tropical depression early on September 17. The JMA upgraded it to Tropical Storm Yagi later that morning as it moved erratically through the open Pacific Ocean, and the JTWC soon followed suit. The name Yagi was submitted by Japan and means [[Capricornus]] (goat). Yagi was upgraded to a severe tropical storm by the JMA on September 18, and the JTWC designated it a typhoon later that day. The JMA officially upgraded Yagi to typhoon status early on September 19. Yagi was upgraded briefly to a super typhoon by the JTWC from September 21 to 22. On September 23, the JTWC reported that Yagi was becoming [[extratropical cyclone|extratropical]] as it continued to weaken, and issued its final warning the next day. The JMA downgraded Yagi to a severe tropical storm on September 24. It was the third tropical cyclone in the NW Pacific Basin that attained Category&amp;nbsp;5 status in 2006. It started to recurve near [[Chichi-jima]], and never affected major land areas. It became [[extratropical cyclone|extratropical]] near the western [[Aleutian Islands|Aleutians]] on September 25.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Xangsane (Milenyo)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon Xangsane 27 sept 2006.jpg
|Track=Xangsane 2006 track.png
|Formed=September 26
|Dissipated=October 2
|10-min winds=95
|1-min winds=125
|Pressure=935
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Xangsane}}
On September 25, the [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration]] (PAGASA) named an active low pressure area within its area of responsibility Tropical Depression Milenyo. After issuing a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]] earlier, the [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] issued its first warning on Tropical Depression 18W. On September 26 the [[Japan Meteorological Agency]] named this system Xangsane. The name Xangsane was submitted by [[Laos]] and means elephant. Later that day, the JMA upgraded Xangsane to a severe tropical storm. A bout of rapid intensification followed, and all three agencies, the JMA, JTWC and PAGASA all upgraded the storm to a typhoon late on September 26 or early September 27. Xangsane made landfall on [[Samar Island]] as a severe tropical storm.

The typhoon dropped heavy rainfall in the [[Philippines]]. To avoid the storm, transit authorities kept seacraft at several ports in the archipelago, leaving over 3,500 passengers stranded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.news24.com/News24/World/News/0,,2-10-1462_2004589,00.html |title=Thousands trapped by typhoon |work=News24 |deadurl=yes |date=September 27, 2006 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070930235753/http://www.news24.com/News24/World/News/0,,2-10-1462_2004589,00.html |archivedate=September 30, 2007 |accessdate=March 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Xangsane also prompted Philippine officials to close all schools, financial markets, and government offices in and around [[Manila]]. The typhoon killed over 200&amp;nbsp;people in the country, and produced strong winds and rainfall, downing power lines and causing [[mudflow]]s. The strong winds caused moderate crop damage totaling to $7.2&amp;nbsp;million (2006&amp;nbsp;USD).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/asiapcf/10/01/typhoon.vietnam.ap/index.html |work=CNN |deadurl=yes |date=October 1, 2006 |title=Typhoon kills 2 in Vietnam |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20061005192509/http://www.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/asiapcf/10/01/typhoon.vietnam.ap/index.html |archivedate=October 5, 2006 |accessdate=March 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Xangsane made landfall as a typhoon near [[Huế|Hue]] early on October 1. The JTWC stopped issuing advisories soon after, and the JMA downgraded it to a severe tropical storm. Xangsane killed 71 in [[Vietnam]].
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Severe Tropical Storm Bebinca (Neneng)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Bebinca_Oct_5_2006_0415z.jpg
|Track=Bebinca 2006 track.png
|Formed=October 3
|Dissipated=October 6
|10-min winds=50
|1-min winds=35
|Pressure=980
}}
On October 1, a persistent area of low pressure just east of the [[Philippines]] developed into Tropical Depression 19W. The JMA had already been monitoring the storm. It was named Neneng by PAGASA, and later that evening was upgraded to a tropical storm by the Philippine authorities. The JMA and JTWC both designated the storm a tropical storm the next day, and it was named Bebinca by the JMA. Bebinca is a type of [[Macau|Macanese]] milk [[pudding]].

The JTWC downgraded it to a tropical depression briefly between October 4 and 5 as wind shear took its toll. Its low-level circulation then became exposed with dry air entering the system, and both the JMA and JTWC declared the storm as a dissipating tropical depression on October 6. It soon became entrained within the circulation of a storm-force [[extratropical cyclone|extratropical low]], which swept across the [[Honshū]] coastal waters and led to 33&amp;nbsp;people dead or missing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Language icon|ja|Japanese}} http://www.data.jma.go.jp/obd/stats/data/bosai/report/new/iyun_sokuji20061004-09.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; It was upgraded to a severe tropical storm in post analysis.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Tropical Storm Rumbia===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Rumbia Oct 4 2006 0020z.jpg
|Track=Rumbia 2006 track.png
|Formed=October 3
|Dissipated=October 6
|10-min winds=45
|1-min winds=30
|Pressure=985
}}
On October 3, a tropical depression south of [[Minami Torishima]] in high sea-surface temperatures gained enough convection and was designated Tropical Storm Rumbia by the JMA, although the JTWC had not even carried it as a tropical depression. Later that day, the JTWC issued a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]], and began warnings on Tropical Depression 20W the next day. Rumbia slowly began to intensify while moving to the northwest, but on October 6 its low-level circulation became fully exposed, and the JTWC issued a final warning. The JMA followed suit soon after. The remnants of Rumbia later became extremely elongated on October 6, before being absorbed into the large extratropical low of Bebinca.
The name &quot;''Rumbia''&quot; comes from a type of [[palm tree]] known as the [[sago]] palm.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Soulik===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Soulik 14 Oct 06 02Z.jpg
|Track=Soulik 2006 track.png
|Formed=October 9
|Dissipated=October 16
|10-min winds=75
|1-min winds=90
|Pressure=955
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Soulik (2006)}}
On October 9, an area of low pressure was found to have banding convection wrapping into a consolidating low-level circulation centre, and was declared a tropical depression by the JTWC. As the system strengthened further, it was upgraded to Tropical Storm 21W by the JTWC later that day. JMA followed suit and classified the storm as Tropical Storm Soulik. The name Soulik was submitted by the [[Federated States of Micronesia]], and is a traditional title for [[Pohnpei]] chiefs. Soulik continued to intensify through October 10, and the JMA upgraded it to a severe tropical storm. [[Agrihan]] was put under a tropical storm watch, which was later upgraded to a warning. In 18 hours on October 11, 8&amp;nbsp;inches (205&amp;nbsp;mm) of rain was reported on [[Pagan Island]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.weather.unisys.com/hurricane/archive/06101106&lt;/ref&gt; After days of gradual strengthening, it became a typhoon on October 12, stalling over [[Iwo Jima]]. Soulik reached Category&amp;nbsp;2 status on the [[Saffir-Simpson Hurricane Scale]] on October 13 before gradually weakening and moving northeastward rapidly as it became [[extratropical cyclone|extratropical]].
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Cimaron (Paeng)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=TY Cimaron 2006 peak.jpg
|Track=Cimaron 2006 track.png
|Formed=October 27
|Dissipated=November 4
|10-min winds=100
|1-min winds=140
|Pressure=920
}}
An area of disturbed weather developed northwest of [[Chuuk State|Chuuk]] on October 24. The disturbance moved west-northwestward over the next two days and gradually became better organized, and the [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] issued a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]] on the system on October 26. The system was designated Tropical Depression 22W by the JTWC later that day. The system continued to strengthen, and the JTWC upgraded it to a tropical storm on October 27. The [[Japan Meteorological Agency]] later followed suit and designated the system Tropical Storm Cimaron. The name Cimaron was submitted by the [[Philippines]], and is a type of wild [[ox]]. The system quickly intensified, and was upgraded to a severe tropical storm by the JMA later that day. The system continued its quick intensification and was upgraded to a typhoon by both the JTWC and JMA on October 28. Further intensification occurred overnight, and the typhoon had [[rapid deepening|rapidly deepened]] 65 [[Pascal (unit)|hPa]] in 24 hours, from 985&amp;nbsp;hPa to 920&amp;nbsp;hPa, causing the JTWC to upgrade it to a 140-kt super typhoon at 9&amp;nbsp;a.m. UTC on October 29. It made landfall at about 12:30&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]] the same day on Northern [[Luzon]]. There, especially in [[Isabela Province]], it lashed winds as much as 195&amp;nbsp;km/h and gusts as much as 230&amp;nbsp;km/h.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/19181/(Update)-Super-typhoon-Paeng-rips-Isabela-province |title=(Update) Super typhoon ‘Paeng’ rips Isabela province&amp;nbsp;– Nation&amp;nbsp;– Official Website of GMA News and Public Affairs&amp;nbsp;– Latest Philippine News&amp;nbsp;– BETA |publisher=GMANews.TV |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Actually, all or parts of four provinces (Isabela, [[Quirino Province|Quirino]], [[Cagayan]] and [[Aurora Province|Aurora]]) are declared under Signal No. 4 as the typhoon struck the island.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/htmfiles/Paeng_2006.htm |title=Paeng 2006 |publisher=Gmanews.tv |date=October 29, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cimaron then re-intensified after crossing the island, but not to its original strength, and was expected to curve towards [[Hainan Island|Hainan]], instead of moving towards [[Vietnam]] as previously forecast. On November 1, the JTWC upgraded the typhoon back into a Category&amp;nbsp;3-equivalent storm, and forecast that it would make a direct impact on Hong Kong. However, prediction models showed conflicting forecasts, and Cimaron remained quasi-stationary and weakened to a severe tropical storm on November 2. Dry air entrainment caused further weakening, with the JTWC dropping it to a minimal tropical storm at 3&amp;nbsp;p.m. UTC the next day. It weakened further, upwelling itself. The JTWC issued its final warning at 3&amp;nbsp;p.m. UTC on November 4. The JMA continued advisories on Cimaron until 12&amp;nbsp;a.m. UTC on November 6, when it was downgraded to a weak tropical depression.

The typhoon killed at least 19&amp;nbsp;people, many of whom drowned, and left 15 missing in the northern Philippines. It also killed a woman and her child after both are hit by a sheet of galvanized iron in [[Dilasag]], Aurora Province, serving as the first human casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/19190/Typhoon-Paeng-claims-first-casualties |title=Typhoon 'Paeng' claims first casualties&amp;nbsp;– Nation&amp;nbsp;– Official Website of GMA News and Public Affairs&amp;nbsp;– Latest Philippine News&amp;nbsp;– BETA |publisher=GMANews.TV |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further casualties happened as the typhoon passed through Luzon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/19203/Typhoon-Paeng-weakens-but-casualties-rise-3-dead-3-hurt |title=Typhoon 'Paeng' weakens but casualties rise; 3 dead, 3 hurt&amp;nbsp;– Nation&amp;nbsp;– Official Website of GMA News and Public Affairs&amp;nbsp;– Latest Philippine News&amp;nbsp;– BETA |publisher=GMANews.TV |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite these, however, classes in [[Metro Manila]] were still not suspended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/19172 |title=Classes in Metro Manila not suspended despite typhoon&amp;nbsp;– Nation&amp;nbsp;– Official Website of GMA News and Public Affairs&amp;nbsp;– Latest Philippine News&amp;nbsp;– BETA |publisher=GMANews.TV |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also caused at least US$9&amp;nbsp;million in damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/EKOI-6V58Y3?OpenDocument&amp;rc=3&amp;emid=TC-2006-000153-PHL |title=News: Southeast Asia: Typhoon Cimaron&amp;nbsp;– Oct 2006, Toll from typhoon Cimaron rises to 19 in Philippines |publisher=Reliefweb.int |date=November 1, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 90% of the houses were damaged in a coastal town near where Cimaron made landfall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bostonherald.com/international/view.bg?articleid=164856 Error&amp;nbsp;– BostonHerald.com] {{Wayback|url=http://news.bostonherald.com/international/view.bg?articleid=164856|date =20070929150059}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the storm's passage across the Philippines, the [[Swedish International Development Cooperation Agency]] contributed 2.5&amp;nbsp;million [[Swedish krona]] (US$350,000) to aid efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/HMYT-6V5P2H?OpenDocument&amp;rc=3&amp;emid=TC-2006-000153-PHL |title=Contributions: Southeast Asia: Typhoon Cimaron&amp;nbsp;– Oct 2006, Sida support to nearly two million Asians affected by typhoon, Press Releases: Southeast Asia: Typhoon Xangsane&amp;nbsp;– Sep 2006, Sida support to nearly two million Asians affected by typhoon |publisher=Reliefweb.int |date=October 29, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Chebi (Queenie)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon Chebi 2006.jpg
|Track=Chebi 2006 track.png
|Formed=November 9
|Dissipated=November 13
|10-min winds=95
|1-min winds=125
|Pressure=925
}}
An area of disturbed weather developed east of the [[Mariana Islands]] on October 31, and moved west-northwestward over the next week without any increase in organization due to an unfavorable environment, until November 6, when it encountered more favorable conditions, and the [[Japan Meteorological Agency]] declared it a tropical depression on November 8. The [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] issued a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]] on the system later that day, and [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration|PAGASA]] named the system Tropical Depression Queenie shortly after. The JTWC classified it as Tropical Depression 23W early on November 9. According to the JTWC, lack of equatorial outflow prevented rapid intensification of the system. Later that day at 12&amp;nbsp;p.m. UTC, the JMA upgraded it to a tropical storm named it Chebi. The name Jebi, the correct spelling means [[swallow]] in Korean. The JTWC and PAGASA both followed suit later that day. Early on November 10, the JMA upgraded Chebi to a severe tropical storm as it continued to move west towards the [[Philippines]], following a similar track as Typhoon Cimaron earlier in the season.

Just hours later, the JMA upgraded Chebi from severe tropical storm with 10-minute sustained winds of 55&amp;nbsp;knots to a typhoon with winds of 95&amp;nbsp;knots, with a pressure decrease of 40 [[Pascal (unit)|hPa]] over three hours. The JTWC followed suit, upping Chebi from a tropical storm with 1-minute sustained winds of 55&amp;nbsp;knots to a [[Saffir-Simpson Hurricane Scale|Category 4-equivalent]] typhoon at 9&amp;nbsp;a.m. UTC. PAGASA raised Public Storm Warning Signal No. 4 for three provinces in [[Luzon]], making Chebi the second storm (Typhoon Cimaron served as the first one that year.) in as many weeks to force a Signal #4. After [[rapid deepening|rapidly deepening]], Chebi weakened as it approached the Philippines. It made its first landfall near [[Casiguran, Aurora]] early on November 11, crossed the [[Lingayen Gulf]] and its second landfall on [[Barangay]] Lucap, [[Alaminos City]] about 8 hours later.

Encountering dry air entrainment and increased vertical [[wind shear]] in the [[South China Sea]], Chebi began to gradually weaken to a severe tropical storm on November 12. It continued to weaken, turning northwards towards [[Hainan]], and was downgraded to a tropical storm the next day. On November 14, the JMA issued its last advisory on the dissipating tropical depression. The JTWC issued its final warning later that same day as Chebi dissipated under the strong shear.

All told, the typhoon caused further casualties as well as damage caused by the earlier Typhoon Cimaron. After passing through Luzon, it left 1 dead and 10 injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/20754/(Update)-Queenie-leaves-RP-1-dead-10-injured |title=(Update) 'Queenie' leaves RP: 1 dead, 10 injured&amp;nbsp;– Nation&amp;nbsp;– Official Website of GMA News and Public Affairs&amp;nbsp;– Latest Philippine News&amp;nbsp;– BETA |publisher=GMANews.TV |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Aurora Province]], it caused floods, cutting the province's road system,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/20893/Floods-hamper-relief-work-in-Aurora |title=Floods hamper relief work in Aurora&amp;nbsp;– Nation&amp;nbsp;– Official Website of GMA News and Public Affairs&amp;nbsp;– Latest Philippine News&amp;nbsp;– BETA |publisher=GMANews.TV |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as zero visibility, further isolating it from relief efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/20986/Zero-visibility-now-keeping-relief-goods-from-Aurora |title=Zero visibility now keeping relief goods from Aurora&amp;nbsp;– Nation&amp;nbsp;– Official Website of GMA News and Public Affairs&amp;nbsp;– Latest Philippine News&amp;nbsp;– BETA |publisher=GMANews.TV |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Durian (Reming)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon Durian 20061129 0756Z.jpg
|Track=Durian 2006 track.png
|Formed=November 26
|Dissipated=December 5
|10-min winds=105
|1-min winds=135
|Pressure=915
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Durian}}
An area of disturbed weather developed southeast of [[Chuuk State|Chuuk]] on November 24. [[Wind shear]] near the disturbance soon decreased, allowing the depression to organize a little. It was designated a tropical depression by [[Japan Meteorological Agency]] on November 25, and later that day the [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] started issuing warnings on the system as it moved west-northwest towards [[Yap]]. The depression strengthened because it was in an area of high sea-surface temperatures, and there were distinct cloud features of [[anticyclone|anticyclonic]] outflow, according to the JMA. It was upgraded to a tropical storm on the afternoon of November 26 and named Durian. The name Durian refers to a fruit, &quot;[[Durian|Durio zibethinus]]&quot;, and was submitted to the naming list by [[Thailand]].

Moving west to west-northwestward, Durian intensified slowly. It became a severe tropical storm on November 27, and the next day it was named ''Reming'' by [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration|PAGASA]] when it entered the Philippine Area of Responsibility. Later on November 28, both the JMA and JTWC upgraded it to a typhoon as it continued to track towards the [[Philippines]]. A quick bout of intensification occurred on November 29, causing the JMA to upgrade the storm to 100&amp;nbsp;knots in wind intensity, and the JTWC to give it a [[Dvorak technique|Dvorak classification]] of 6.5 (127&amp;nbsp;kt) in a [[satellite]] fix. In 6 hours, Durian intensified from 90 [[knot (unit)|kt]] 1-minute sustained winds to 125&amp;nbsp;kt winds. The JTWC then forecast a direct hit over [[Metro Manila]] later that day when it upgraded the storm to a super typhoon. PAGASA raised Public Storm Warning Signal 4, its highest warning level,  over [[Catanduanes]], [[Albay]], [[Camarines Norte]] and [[Camarines Sur]]. It was the third time in 2006, and the third time in a row, that PAGASA raised Signal #4. Durian began to weaken slightly as it approached land, undergoing an [[eyewall replacement cycle]], but quickly regained peak strength.

PAGASA claimed that the storm made landfall on the morning of November 30 over southern [[Catanduanes]], although the JMA and JTWC did not recognize this landfall. Durian then made another landfall after crossing the [[Lagonoy Gulf]] in northeastern [[Albay]]. After weakening due to interaction with land, Durian was downgraded back to a typhoon by the JTWC. The storm continued to move west, making landfalls on the [[Bondoc Peninsula]] in [[Quezon]], on [[Marinduque]] and finally on [[Oriental Mindoro]] before exiting to the [[South China Sea]].

Encountering dry air entrainment and vertical [[wind shear]], Durian weakened slightly at first, but slowly began to reorganise and restrengthen as it neared [[Vietnam]]. Durian began to turn slightly southwest towards [[Nha Trang]] and [[Ho Chi Minh City]] on December 3. Eventually, Durian began to weaken again, and by December 4, the JMA downgraded it to a severe tropical storm. The storm maintained intensity as it skirted the Vietnamese coast moving southwest. After a brief second stint at typhoon strength, Durian finally made landfall in [[Ben Tre Province]] on December 5. The system rapidly weakened over land, and the JMA downgraded it to a tropical storm. The JMA and JTWC issued their final advisories later that day as Durian emerged into the [[Gulf of Thailand]] as a weak tropical depression. The remnants of Durian then crossed the coast of [[southern Thailand]] as it moved into the [[Bay of Bengal]].

The storm killed at least 720 in the [[Philippines]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/EKOI-6WF8T8?OpenDocument&amp;rc=3&amp;emid=TC-2006-000175-PHL |title=Situation Reports: Southeast Asia: Typhoon Durian&amp;nbsp;– Dec 2006, Philippines: NDCC media update&amp;nbsp;– Typhoon &quot;Reming&quot; (Durian) 13 Dec 2006 |publisher=Reliefweb.int |date=December 13, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The most damage occurred in [[Albay Province]] where the storm created mudslides of volcanic ash and boulders off [[Mayon Volcano]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/YAOI-6WD3GQ?OpenDocument |title=Press Releases: Southeast Asia: Typhoon Durian&amp;nbsp;– Dec 2006, Devastating typhoon hits the Philippines and Vietnam |publisher=Reliefweb.int |date=December 11, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Padang [[barangay]] of [[Legazpi City]] was severely affected with a large portion of the town covered in mud up to houses' roofs.  At least 81&amp;nbsp;people have died and 16&amp;nbsp;people are missing in [[Vietnam]] from the storm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/YAOI-6WA9N3?OpenDocument&amp;rc=3&amp;emid=TC-2006-000175-PHL |title=Press Releases: Southeast Asia: Typhoon Durian&amp;nbsp;– Dec 2006, Viet Nam: NDMP Durian typhoon damage update 8 Dec 2006 |publisher=Reliefweb.int |date=December 8, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Typhoon Utor (Seniang)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Typhoon Utor 13 dec 2006 0305Z.jpg
|Track=Utor 2006 track.png
|Formed=December 7
|Dissipated=December 14
|10-min winds=85
|1-min winds=100
|Pressure=945
}}
{{Main|Typhoon Utor (2006)}}
On December 2, an area of convection was spotted by the [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] southeast of [[Chuuk State|Chuuk]]. Although convection decreased in the next few hours, on December 5 the JTWC once again noted flaring deep convection, and late on December 6 a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]] was issued. On the morning of December 7, both the JTWC and [[Japan Meteorological Agency]]-RSMC Tokyo reported that a tropical depression had formed. Soon after, the depression entered the area of responsibility of [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration|PAGASA]], who named it Seniang. The depression strengthened throughout the day, and the JMA upgraded it to Tropical Storm Utor later that day. The name Utor was submitted by the United States on behalf of the [[Marshall Islands]], and is a [[Marshallese language|Marshallese]] word for [[squall line]].Signal no.3 has been raised in the provinces of [[Cebu]],Leyte,Samar Provinces

On December 8, the JMA upgraded Utor to a severe tropical storm. It intensified further and was upgraded to a typhoon by the JMA on the morning of December 9, with [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration|PAGASA]] and JTWC doing the same. The storm made landfall shortly after noon local time the same day. After crossing the [[Philippines]], Utor took a track similar to Typhoon Chebi in November, first moving northwest then threatening to take aim at Hong Kong. It restrengthened to an 85-kt typhoon, before it slowed as it tracked in a weak steering environment within a weakness in the [[subtropical ridge]]. It then weakened as wind shear increased and dry air entrainment occurred. The JMA downgraded it to a severe tropical storm on December 13, and to a tropical storm the same day. The next day the JTWC downgraded the storm to a tropical storm and issued its last advisory.

The [[ASEAN Summit|2006 ASEAN]] and [[East Asia Summit]], originally scheduled to start December 10, was put back a month due to the storm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.12thaseansummit.org.ph/innertemplate3.asp?category=news&amp;newsid=319 |title=The official site of 12th ASEAN SUMMIT: Cebu, Philippines |publisher=12thaseansummit.org.ph |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/6220492.stm |work=BBC News | title=Philippines postpones Asean talks | date=December 8, 2006 | accessdate=April 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Typhoon Utor killed at least 78 people and left 49 others missing in the Philippines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/VBOL-6WHHZT?OpenDocument&amp;rc=3&amp;emid=TC-2006-000183-PHL |title=Situation Reports: Philippines: Typhoon Utor&amp;nbsp;– Dec 2006, Philippines: NDCC media update&amp;nbsp;– Typhoon &quot;Seniang&quot; (Utor) 15 Dec 2006 |publisher=Reliefweb.int |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Damages from the typhoon were estimated at $1.9&amp;nbsp;million (2006 USD).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/rwb.nsf/db900sid/ACOS-64BSSU?OpenDocument |title=ReliefWeb ť Document ť CWS Situation Report: Typhoon Utor/Philippines |publisher=Reliefweb.int |date=July 6, 2001 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Typhoon Utor was blamed for heavy rains of up to 350&amp;nbsp;mm within 24 hours in southern [[Peninsular Malaysia]], specifically [[Johor]], [[Negeri Sembilan]], [[Melaka]] and [[Pahang]], causing massive floods within the southern region on December 18, 2006, which was considered as the worst in the [[Malaysia]]n southern region history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Segamat-flood01&quot;&gt;[http://thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2006/12/21/nation/16380186&amp;sec=nation Typhoon Utor to blame] The Star Online&lt;/ref&gt; However, there were also reports a few days earlier that adverse weather was not to be blamed on the typhoon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2006/12/14/nation/16311944&amp;sec=nation |title=Seas too choppy for small vessels |publisher=Thestar.com.my |date=December 14, 2006 |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The worst-affected areas were [[Segamat]] and [[Kota Tinggi]], where both towns were totally inaccessible by land after all main roads leading to those towns were all flooded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Segamat-flood02&quot;&gt;[http://thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2006/12/21/nation/20061221072623&amp;sec=nation Segamat and Kota Tinggi folks stranded by floods] The Star Online&lt;/ref&gt; Until December 24, 2006, the floods had claimed 8 lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Segamat-flood03&quot;&gt;[http://www.thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2006/12/24/nation/16409486&amp;sec=nation&amp;focus=1 Relief all round] The Star Online&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tropical Storm Trami (Tomas)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=Trami 2006.jpg
|Track=Trami 2006 track.png
|Formed=December 17
|Dissipated=December 19
|10-min winds=35
|1-min winds=30
|Pressure=1000
}}
On December 16, the [[Japan Meteorological Agency]] started issuing public bulletins on a tropical depression southwest of [[Guam]]. The [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center]] initiated warnings on Tropical Depression 26W the next day, despite having not issued a [[Tropical Cyclone Formation Alert]]. The system was upgraded to a tropical storm by the JMA and named Trami, which is a kind of [[rose]] tree. This name was submitted by [[Vietnam]]. The storm moved west-northwest rapidly towards the [[Philippines]], but struggled against wind shear and an approaching cold front. Entering the PAGASA Area of Responsibility on December 18 as it maintained minimal tropical storm intensity, it was named Tomas. The JTWC issued its final warning later that day, having never upgraded the storm to tropical storm strength, citing no indication of a significant low-level circulation centre. On December 19, the JMA downgraded the storm to a tropical depression and issued its last public bulletin as the storm dissipated over water.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

==Other storms==
These systems were not officially named as tropical storms by the JMA, although the JMA might have monitored them as tropical depressions. They were, however, designated as tropical cyclones by the Philippines (PAGASA), China (CMA), and/or the Joint Typhoon Warning Center (JTWC).

===PAGASA Tropical Depression Agaton===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|WarningCenter=PAGASA
|Image=Tropical Depression Agaton 2006.JPG
|Track=Agaton_(PAGASA)_2006_track.png
|Formed=January 20
|Dissipated=January 27
|10-min winds=30
|Pressure=1000
}}
On January 20, the JMA began monitoring a minor tropical depression located about {{convert|555|km|mi|abbr=on}} east of [[Mindanao]] in the southern Philippines. As it traveled in an erratic northwestward direction, it slowly became better organized. On January 23, the JMA assessed the storm to have attained winds of 55&amp;nbsp;km/h (35&amp;nbsp;mph &lt;small&gt;10-minute winds&lt;/small&gt;). Around the same time, PAGASA began issuing advisories on the system and gave it the local name ''Agaton''.  The depression weakened as it crossed over northern [[Samar Island]] and southern [[Luzon]]. Traveling towards the west, the system failed to strengthen and dissipated on January 27 while located over the [[South China Sea]], about halfway between [[Vietnam]] and [[Borneo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GPJanuary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Gary Padgett|publisher=Typhoon 2000|date=April 25, 2006|accessdate=February 17, 2009|title=Monthly Tropical Weather Summary for January 2006|url=http://www.typhoon2000.ph/garyp_mgtcs/jan06sum.txt| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090224014516/http://www.typhoon2000.ph/garyp_mgtcs/jan06sum.txt| archivedate= February 24, 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===JTWC Tropical Storm 01W (Basyang)===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|WarningCenter=PAGASA
|Image=2006 TS01W peak.jpg
|Track=1-W 2006 track.png
|Formed=March 4
|Dissipated=March 7
|10-min winds=30
|1-min winds=35
|Pressure=996
}}
On March 4, a tropical depression formed out of a wave close to the [[equator]] southeast of [[Palau]]. The [[Joint Typhoon Warning Center|JTWC]] upgraded it to Tropical Storm 01W at 3&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]] the same day. The JTWC downgraded it back to a depression on March 5 due to shear, and it never regained tropical storm strength before dissipating on March 7.&lt;ref name=&quot;nrl&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrlmry.navy.mil/tc_pages/tc_home.html |title=Navy/NRL Tropical Cyclone Page |publisher=Nrlmry.navy.mil |date=September 23, 2010 |accessdate=October 19, 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100922155847/http://www.nrlmry.navy.mil/tc_pages/tc_home.html| archivedate= September 22, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the six years since current naming conventions were introduced, this was the 12th time the JTWC recognised a tropical storm not named by the JMA, after three storms in the [[2001 Pacific typhoon season]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.australiasevereweather.com/cyclones/2002/summ2001.txt ] {{Wayback|url=http://www.australiasevereweather.com/cyclones/2002/summ2001.txt|date =20061106131014}}&lt;/ref&gt; two storms each in [[2000 Pacific typhoon season|2000]], [[2002 Pacific typhoon season|2002]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.typhoon2000.ph/garyp_mgtcs/02sum.txt&lt;/ref&gt; and [[2004 Pacific typhoon season|2004]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.australiasevereweather.com/cyclones/2004/summ2003.txt ] {{Wayback|url=http://www.australiasevereweather.com/cyclones/2004/summ2003.txt|date =20060822224109}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one each in [[2003 Pacific typhoon season|2003]] and [[2005 Pacific typhoon season|2005]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.australiasevereweather.com/cyclones/2006/summ2005.htm |title=Northern Hemisphere 2005 Tropical Cyclone Season Review |publisher=Australiasevereweather.com |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===CMA Tropical Depression 03===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|WarningCenter=CMA
|Image=TD03.jpg
|Formed=July 3
|Dissipated=July 4
|10-min winds=30
|Pressure=998
}}
On July 3, China Meteorological Administration identified a tropical depression about 200&amp;nbsp;km south of [[Sanya]], Hainan. The depression moved northwest and made landfall at 7:10&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[Chinese Standard Time|CST]] in Hainan on the same day. The storm's lowest pressure was around 998&amp;nbsp;hPa.&lt;ref&gt;http://weather.unisys.com/hurricane/archive/06070400&lt;/ref&gt; On the next morning, it entered Gulf of Tonkin and strengthened slightly. Eventually, the depression made its second landfall near Guangxi/Vietnam border around noon and rapidly weakened over land.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Non-NMHS Tropical Depression===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|WarningCenter=Other
|Image=99w.jpg
|Formed=July 21
|Dissipated=July 22
|10-min winds=25
|Pressure=1002
}}
Guangdong Regional Meteorological Centre, not a National Meteorological and Hydrological Service (for China, this is the CMA) identified a tropical depression about 300&amp;nbsp;km south of Xisha on July 21.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mb.hainan.gov.cn/gov/text/qxxx211530081.txt ] {{Wayback|url=http://mb.hainan.gov.cn/gov/text/qxxx211530081.txt|date =20071118193623}}&lt;/ref&gt; The system remained weak and dissipated on the next morning.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===JTWC Tropical Depression 13W===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=2006 13W NONAME landfall.jpg
|Track=13-W 2006 track.png
|Formed=August 24
|Dissipated=August 25
|1-min winds=30
|Pressure=1000
}}
In the afternoon of August 23, the [[China Meteorological Administration]] declared the formation of a tropical depression near [[Hainan]]. [[Hong Kong Observatory]] followed later that afternoon. The depression necessitated Tropical Cyclone Signal No.1 in Hong Kong and [[Macau]], which means that the centre of a tropical cyclone is within {{convert|800|km|mi|abbr=on}} of the respective [[Special Administrative Region of the People's Republic of China|Special Administrative Regions]], and may later affect them. The depression made landfall at Guangdong at 5:55&amp;nbsp;a.m. [[Chinese Standard Time|CST]] on August 25 and dissipated later that morning.

The JTWC designated the system as a Tropical Depression at 9&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]] August 24, but only issued two warnings on the system.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===JTWC Tropical Depression 15W===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=15W 2006 peak.jpg
|Track=15-W 2006 track.png
|Formed=September 12
|Dissipated=September 13
|1-min winds=30
|Pressure=1000
}}
[[Hong Kong Observatory]] identified a tropical depression about 360&amp;nbsp;kilometres east-northeast of Xisha on September 12 and issued [[Hong Kong Tropical Cyclone Warning Signals|Standby Signal No.1]] accordingly. The tropical depression also necessitated the issuance of the Standby Signal No. 1 in Macau at 2&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]] on the same day. The JTWC designated it as a tropical depression, 15W, at 9&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[UTC]] September 12. The JMA had earlier already identified it as a tropical depression. As it strengthened and edged closer to the coastal areas of [[Guangdong]], the Strong Wind Signal No. 3 was issued both in Hong Kong and Macau on September 13. It made landfall in western [[Guangdong]] around 11:30&amp;nbsp;p.m. [[Chinese Standard Time|CST]] that night and dissipated inland.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===JTWC Tropical Depression 17W===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|Image=17W 35 kt 2006-09-24 0530.jpg
|Track=17-W 2006 track.png
|Formed=September 23
|Dissipated=September 25
|1-min winds=30
|Pressure=1000
}}
The China Meteorological Administration (CMA) and Hong Kong Observatory both identified a tropical depression in the southern [[South China Sea]] on September 22. The system was organized enough to be classified as Tropical Depression 17W by the JTWC the next day. The JTWC briefly upgraded it to a tropical storm on September 24. It weakened under heavy vertical wind shear and the JTWC issued its final advisory on Tropical Depression 17W before landfall in [[Vietnam]]. The storm passed just south of Hainan and brought heavy rain to the area. The maximum rainfall recorded was 143&amp;nbsp;mm. CMA kept it as a tropical storm until it made landfall in Vietnam in the morning of September 25. In the six years since current naming conventions were introduced, this was the 13th time the JTWC recognised a tropical storm not named by the JMA. This was also the 3rd time that CMA recognised a tropical storm not named by the JMA, after one storm in the 2000 Pacific typhoon season, zero in 2001, 2002 and 2003,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.typhoon.gov.cn/history/2002_cd/dh/symain1.htm ] {{Wayback|url=http://www.typhoon.gov.cn/history/2002_cd/dh/symain1.htm|date =20051110232551}}&lt;/ref&gt; one in 2004.

In the post-season analysis supplied by the JTWC, it was determined that 17W never reached tropical storm intensity, thus it was downgraded to a tropical depression.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===PAGASA Tropical Depression Ompong===
{{Infobox Hurricane Small
|Basin=WPac
|WarningCenter=PAGASA
|Image=Ompong 2006 cropped.jpg
|Track=Ompong_(PAGASA)_2006_track.png
|Formed=October 12
|Dissipated=October 13
|10-min winds=30
|Pressure=1000
}}
On October 12, a tropical disturbance that had been meandering in the [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration|Philippine Area of Responsibility]] was designated Tropical Depression Ompong by PAGASA. The depression slowly moved westward toward the [[Philippines]], but wind shear from Typhoon Soulik prevented any intensification. The depression degenerated into an area of low pressure early the next day.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

==Storm names==
Within the North-western Pacific Ocean, both the [[Japan Meteorological Agency]] (JMA) and the [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration]] assign names to tropical cyclones that develop in the Western Pacific, which can result in a tropical cyclone having two names.&lt;ref name=&quot;Padgett Dec 99&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Monthly Tropical Cyclone summary December 1999|accessdate=August 28, 2012|deadurl=no|author=Padgett, Gary|publisher=Australian Severe Weather|url=http://www.australiasevereweather.com/cyclones/2000/summ9912.htm|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6AFtYwMYc|archivedate=August 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Japan Meteorological Agency's RSMC Tokyo&amp;nbsp;— Typhoon Center assigns international names to tropical cyclones on behalf of the [[World Meteorological Organization]]'s Typhoon Committee, should they be judged to have 10-minute sustained windspeeds of 65&amp;nbsp;km/h, (40&amp;nbsp;mph).&lt;ref name=&quot;TC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Typhoon Committee Operational Manual 2012|url=http://www.wmo.int/pages/prog/www/tcp/documents/TCP-23EDITION2012.pdf|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6AFsQCYxB|publisher=World Meteorological Organization|archivedate=August 28, 2012|pages=37–38|format=PDF|date=February 21, 2012|author=the Typhoon Committee}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration assigns names to tropical cyclones which move into or form as a tropical depression in their area of responsibility located between 135°E and 115°E and between 5°N-25°N even if the cyclone has had an international name assigned to it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Padgett Dec 99&quot;/&gt; The names of significant tropical cyclones are retired, by both [[List of retired Philippine typhoon names|PAGASA]] and the [[List of retired Pacific typhoon names (JMA)|Typhoon Committee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TC&quot;/&gt; Should the list of names for the Philippine region be exhausted then names will be taken from an auxiliary list of which the first ten are published each season. Unused names are marked in {{tcname unused}}.

===International names===
{{See also|Lists of tropical cyclone names|Tropical cyclone naming}}
Tropical Cyclones are named from the following lists by the [[Regional Specialized Meteorological Centre]] in [[Tokyo]], [[Japan]], once they reach tropical storm strength.&lt;ref name=&quot;Padgett Dec 99&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Monthly Tropical Cyclone summary December 1999|accessdate=April 20, 2008|publisher=Australian Severe Weather|author=Gary Padgett|url=http://www.australiasevereweather.com/cyclones/2000/summ9912.htm| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080517145245/http://www.australiasevereweather.com/cyclones/2000/summ9912.htm| archivedate= May 17, 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Names are contributed by members of the [[ESCAP/WMO Typhoon Committee]]. Each of the 14 nations or territories submitted 10 names, which are used in alphabetical order, by the English name of the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMA Names&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Tropical Cyclone names|accessdate=April 20, 2008|publisher=JMA|url=http://www.jma.go.jp/jma/jma-eng/jma-center/rsmc-hp-pub-eg/tyname.html| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080402004254/http://www.jma.go.jp/jma/jma-eng/jma-center/rsmc-hp-pub-eg/tyname.html| archivedate= April 2, 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 

{| style=&quot;width:100%;&quot;
|
* [[Typhoon Chanchu|Chanchu (0601)]]
* Jelawat (0602)
* [[Typhoon Ewiniar (2006)|Ewiniar (0603)]]
* [[Tropical Storm Bilis|Bilis (0604)]]
* Kaemi (0605)
* [[Typhoon Prapiroon (2006)|Prapiroon (0606)]]
|
* [[Typhoon Maria (2006)|Maria (0607)]]
* [[Typhoon Saomai|Saomai (0608)]]
* Bopha (0609)
* [[Tropical Storm Wukong (2006)|Wukong (0610)]]
* Sonamu (0611)
* Ioke (0612)
|
* [[Typhoon Shanshan (2006)|Shanshan (0613)]]
* [[Typhoon Yagi (2006)|Yagi (0614)]]
* [[Typhoon Xangsane|Xangsane (0615)]]
* Bebinca (0616)
* Rumbia (0617)
* [[Typhoon Soulik (2006)|Soulik (0618)]]
|
* Cimaron (0619)
* Chebi (0620)
* [[Typhoon Durian|Durian (0621)]]
* [[Typhoon Utor (2006)|Utor (0622)]]
* Trami (0623)
|}

One storm, [[Hurricane Ioke]], entered the Western North Pacific from the Central North Pacific, retaining its name assigned by the [[Central Pacific Hurricane Center]]. It was given the international typhoon number ''0612'' by the JMA.

===Philippines===
The [[Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration]] uses its own naming scheme for tropical cyclones in their area of responsibility. PAGASA assigns names to tropical depressions that form within their area of responsibility and any tropical cyclone that might move into their area of responsibility. Should the list of names for a given year prove to be insufficient, names are taken from an auxiliary list, the first 10 of which are published each year before the season starts. The names not retired from this list will be used again in the 2010 season. This is the same list used in the 2002 season, except for ''Glenda'', which replaced ''Gloria''. Names that were not assigned are marked in {{tcname unused}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;pagasa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pagasa.dost.gov.ph/genmet/rpnames.html |title=Philippine Tropical Cyclone Names |publisher=Pagasa.dost.gov.ph |date=January 7, 2008 |accessdate=October 19, 2010|archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5XDefwm3z |archivedate = April 20, 2008|deadu (02W)rl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| style=&quot;width:90%;&quot;
|
* Agaton
* Basyang (02W)
* [[Typhoon Chanchu|Caloy (0601)]]
* Domeng (0602)
* [[Typhoon Ewiniar (2006)|Ester (0603)]]
|
* [[Tropical Storm Bilis|Florita (0604)]]
* Glenda (0605)
* [[Typhoon Prapiroon (2006)|Henry (0606)]]
* Inday (0609)
* [[Typhoon Saomai|Juan (0608)]]
|
* Katring (0611)
* [[Typhoon Shanshan (2006)|Luis (0613)]]
* [[Typhoon Xangsane|Milenyo (0615)]]
* Neneng (0616)
* Ompong
|
* Paeng (0619)
* Queenie (0620)
* [[Typhoon Durian|Reming (0621)]]
* [[Typhoon Utor (2006)|Seniang (0622)]]
* Tomas (0623)
|
* {{tcname unused|Usman}}
* {{tcname unused|Venus}}
* {{tcname unused|Waldo}}
* {{tcname unused|Yayang}}
* {{tcname unused|Zeny}}
|}
{| style=&quot;width:90%;&quot;
&lt;center&gt;
'''Auxiliary list'''&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
|
* {{tcname unused|Agila}}
* {{tcname unused|Bagwis}}
|
* {{tcname unused|Chito}}
* {{tcname unused|Diego}}
|
* {{tcname unused|Elena}}
* {{tcname unused|Felino}}
|
* {{tcname unused|Gunding}}
* {{tcname unused|Harriet}}
|
* {{tcname unused|Indang}}
* {{tcname unused|Jessa}}
|}

===Retirement===
{{See also|List of retired Pacific typhoon names (JMA)|List of retired Philippine typhoon names}}
The names ''Chanchu'', ''Bilis'', ''Saomai'', ''Xangsane'' and ''Durian'' were retired by the ESCAP/WMO Typhoon Committee. The names ''Sanba'', ''Maliksi'', ''Son Tinh'', ''Leepi'' and ''Mangkhut'' were chosen to replaced ''Chanchu'', ''Bilis'', ''Saomai'', ''Xangsane'' and ''Durian'' respectively.

The Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration (PAGASA) announced that the names ''Milenyo'' and ''Reming'' would be retired due to extensive damage and loss of life. The names ''Mario'' and ''Ruby'' were chosen to replaced ''Milenyo'' and ''Reming'' respectively.

==See also==
{{Portal|Tropical cyclones}}
* [[List of Pacific typhoon seasons]]
* [[2006 Pacific hurricane season]]
* [[2006 Atlantic hurricane season]]
* [[2006 North Indian Ocean cyclone season]]
* South-West Indian Ocean cyclone seasons: [[2005-06 South-West Indian Ocean cyclone season|2005–06]], [[2006-07 South-West Indian Ocean cyclone season|2006–07]]
* Australian region cyclone seasons: [[2005-06 Australian region cyclone season|2005–06]], [[2006-07 Australian region cyclone season|2006–07]]
* South Pacific cyclone seasons: [[2005-06 South Pacific cyclone season|2005–06]], [[2006-07 South Pacific cyclone season|2006–07]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons|2006 Pacific typhoon season}}
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kd4wqNYKIyk Satellite movie of 2006 Pacific typhoon season]
*[http://www.jma.go.jp/en/typh/ Japan Meteorological Agency]
*[http://www.typhoon.gov.cn/en/index.php?style1=0 China Meteorological Agency]
*[http://www.prh.noaa.gov/guam/cyclone.php National Weather Service Guam]
*[http://www.hko.gov.hk/contente.htm Hong Kong Observatory]
*[http://www.smg.gov.mo/www/e_index.php Macau Meteorological Geophysical Services]
*[http://web.kma.go.kr/eng/wea/wea_03_01.jsp Korea Meteorological Agency]
*[http://www.pagasa.dost.gov.ph/ Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration]
*[http://www.cwb.gov.tw/V6e/typhoon/ty.htm Taiwan Central Weather Bureau]
*[http://www.usno.navy.mil/JTWC Joint Typhoon Warning Center]

{{2006 Pacific typhoon season buttons}}
{{TC Decades|Year=2000|basin=Pacific|type=typhoon}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2006 Pacific Typhoon Season}}
[[Category:2006 Pacific typhoon season| ]]</text>
      <sha1>7klvg7x890n9a2dbih2sj2l6xt8mwgx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Florence County, Wisconsin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>90976</id>
    <revision>
      <id>542946093</id>
      <parentid>539687094</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-09T01:16:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.148.95.37</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Demographics */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6393">[[Image:FlorenceCountyWisconsinCourtHouse.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Florence County Courthouse and Jail|Florence County Courthouse]]]]
{{Infobox U.S. County
| county          = Florence County
| state           = Wisconsin
| seal            = 
| founded year    = 
| founded date    = 
| seat         = [[Florence (CDP), Wisconsin|Florence]]
| largest city wl = 
| area_total_sq_mi         = 497
| area_total_km2         = 1288
| area_land_sq_mi    = 488
| area_land_km2    = 1264
| area_water_sq_mi   = 9
| area_water_km2   = 24
| area percentage = 1.90%
| census yr       = 2000
| pop             = 5088
| density_sq_mi      = 10
| density_km2      = 4
| time zone       = Central
| UTC offset      = -6
| DST offset      = -5
| footnotes       = 
| web             = www.florencewisconsin.com
| named for       = 
}}

'''Florence County''' is a [[county (United States)|county]] located in the [[U.S. state]] of [[Wisconsin]].  As of 2000, the population was 5,088.  Its [[county seat]] is [[Florence (CDP), Wisconsin|Florence]]{{GR|6}}.

Florence County is part of the [[Iron Mountain, Michigan|Iron Mountain]], [[Michigan|MI]]&amp;ndash;WI [[Iron Mountain micropolitan area|Micropolitan Statistical Area]].

==Geography==
According to the [[United States Census Bureau|U.S. Census Bureau]], the county has a total area of {{convert|497|sqmi|1}}, of which {{convert|488|sqmi|1}} is land and {{convert|9|sqmi|1}} (1.90%) is water.

===Adjacent counties===
*[[Iron County, Michigan]] - north
*[[Dickinson County, Michigan]] - east
*[[Marinette County, Wisconsin]] - southeast
*[[Forest County, Wisconsin]] - south, west

===Major highways===

{|
|
*[[Image:US 2.svg|20px|alt=|link=]] [[U.S. Route 2 in Wisconsin|U.S. Highway 2]]
*[[Image:US 141 (WI).svg|20px|alt=|link=]] [[U.S. Route 141|U.S. Highway 141]]
*[[Image:WIS 70.svg|20px|alt=|link=]] [[Highway 70 (Wisconsin)|Highway 70]]
*[[Image:WIS 101.svg|20px|alt=|link=]] [[Highway 101 (Wisconsin)|Highway 101]]
*[[Image:WIS 139.svg|20px|alt=|link=]] [[Highway 139 (Wisconsin)|Highway 139]]
|}

===National [[protected area]]===
*[[Nicolet National Forest]] (part)

==Demographics==
[[Image:USA Florence County, Wisconsin age pyramid.svg|thumb|left|2000 Census Age Pyramid for Florence County.]]	
{{USCensusPop	
| 1900=	3197
| 1910=	3381
| 1920=	3602
| 1930=	3768
| 1940=	4177
| 1950=	3756
| 1960=	3437
| 1970=	3298
| 1980=	4172
| 1990=	4590
| 2000=	5088
| 2010= 4423
| estimate=4440
| estyear=2011
| footnote=[http://www.census.gov/population/cencounts/wi190090.txt WI Counties 1900-1990]
}}
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 5,088 people, 2,133 households, and 1,441 families residing in the county.  The [[population density]] was 10 people per square mile (4/km²).  There were 4,239 housing units at an average density of 9 per square&amp;nbsp;mile (3/km²).  The racial makeup of the county was 98.17% [[Race (United States Census)|White]], 0.16% [[Race (United States Census)|Black]] or [[Race (United States Census)|African American]], 0.43% [[Race (United States Census)|Native American]], 0.28% [[Race (United States Census)|Asian]], 0.02% [[Race (United States Census)|Pacific Islander]], 0.14% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 0.81% from two or more races.  0.45% of the population were [[Race (United States Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Race (United States Census)|Latino]] of any race. 25.6% were of [[German people|German]], 11.6% [[Swedish people|Swedish]], 8.4% [[Polish people|Polish]], 8.2% [[Italian people|Italian]], 6.6% [[French people|French]], 5.9% [[English people|English]], 5.4% [[French Canadian]] and 5.2% [[Irish people|Irish]] ancestry.

There were 2,133 households out of which 27.50% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 58.60% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 6.00% had a female householder with no husband present, and 32.40% were non-families. 27.90% of all households were made up of individuals and 12.50% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 2.35 and the average family size was 2.87.

In the county, the population was spread out with 22.90% under the age of 18, 5.30% from 18 to 24, 27.10% from 25 to 44, 27.30% from 45 to 64, and 17.50% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 42 years. For every 100 females there were 104.30 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 101.50 males.

==Towns==
Florence County is one of only two counties in Wisconsin with no incorporated communities, the other being [[Menominee County, Wisconsin|Menominee County]].
*[[Aurora, Florence County, Wisconsin|Aurora]]
*[[Commonwealth, Wisconsin|Commonwealth]]
*[[Fence, Wisconsin|Fence]]
*[[Fern, Wisconsin|Fern]]
*[[Florence (town), Wisconsin|Florence]]
*[[Homestead, Wisconsin|Homestead]]
*[[Long Lake, Florence County, Wisconsin|Long Lake]]
*[[Tipler, Wisconsin|Tipler]]

==Unincorporated communities==
*[[Aurora (community), Florence County, Wisconsin|Aurora]]
*[[Commonwealth (community), Wisconsin|Commonwealth]]
*[[Fence (community), Wisconsin|Fence]]
*[[Fern, Wisconsin|Fern]]
*[[Florence (CDP), Wisconsin|Florence]]
*[[Hematite, Wisconsin|Hematite]]
*[[Long Lake (community), Florence County, Wisconsin|Long Lake]]
*[[Pulp, Wisconsin|Pulp]]
*[[Ridgetop, Wisconsin|Ridgetop]]
*[[Spread Eagle, Wisconsin|Spread Eagle]]
*[[Tipler (community), Wisconsin|Tipler]]
*[[Tyran, Wisconsin|Tyran]]

==See also==
*[[National_Register_of_Historic_Places_listings_in_Wisconsin#Florence_County|National Register of Historic Places listings in Florence County, Wisconsin]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.florencewisconsin.com/ Florence County website]
*[http://www.exploreflorencecounty.com/ Florence County WI Tourism &amp; Economic Development]

{{Geographic Location
|Centre    = Florence County, Wisconsin
|North     = [[Iron County, Michigan]]
|Northeast = 
|East      = [[Dickinson County, Michigan]]
|Southeast = [[Marinette County, Wisconsin|Marinette County]]
|South     = [[Forest County, Wisconsin|Forest County]]
|Southwest = 
|West      = [[Forest County, Wisconsin|Forest County]]
|Northwest = 
}}

{{Florence County, Wisconsin}}
{{Wisconsin}}

{{coord|45.85|-88.40|display=title|type:adm2nd_region:US-WI_source:UScensus1990}}

[[Category:Wisconsin counties]]
[[Category:Florence County, Wisconsin| ]]
[[Category:Iron Mountain micropolitan area]]</text>
      <sha1>jgppv32p7l9uos7dqgctwe3v1ggra8j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Artists Rifles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>673854</id>
    <revision>
      <id>542587023</id>
      <parentid>540222036</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-07T14:15:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 3 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q1778759]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13063">{{About|the British regiment|the album by the indie group Piano Magic|Artists' Rifles (album)}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=Artists Rifles
|image=[[File:Artists Rifles Badge.jpg|150px]]
|caption=Cap badge of the Artists Rifles.
|dates=1859–1945&lt;br /&gt; 1947–present
|country= United Kingdom
|allegiance=
|branch=Territorial Army
|type=Light Infantry and Officer Training (prior to 1947), then Special Forces
|role=Reconnaissance and long range patrols (current)
|size=
|command_structure=
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=
|motto=
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=Boer War, World War I
|anniversaries=
|decorations=8 VCs, 56 DSOs, 893 MCs, 26 DFCs, 15 AFCs, 6 DCMs, 15 MMs, 14 MSMs, 564 MIDs (World War I)
|battle_honours='''Boer War''': South Africa 1900–01.&lt;br /&gt;
'''The Great War''': Ypres 1917, Passchendaele, Somme 1918, St. Quentin, Bapaume 1918, Arras 1918, Ancre 1918, Albert 1918, Drocourt-Quéant, Hindenburg Line, Canal du Nord, Cambrai 1918, Pursuit to Mons, France and Flanders 1914–18
|disbanded=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|commander2=
|commander2_label=
|commander3=
|commander3_label=
|notable_commanders=Henry Wyndham Phillips and Frederic Leighton
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label=}}
The '''Artists Rifles''' is a volunteer [[regiment]] of the [[British Army]].{{refn | group = &quot;nb&quot; | Originally the regiment was designated as the '''Artists' Rifles''' until the apostrophe was officially dropped from the full title in 1937, as it was so often misused.&lt;ref name = &quot;Website&quot;&gt;{{Citation | url = http://artistsriflesassociation.org/regiment-artists-rifles.htm | title = Regiment | publisher = Artists Rifles Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}  Raised in London in 1859 as a volunteer light infantry unit, the regiment saw active service during the [[Boer Wars]] and [[World War I]], earning a number of battle honours. However, it did not serve outside Britain during [[World War II]], as it was used as an officer training unit at that time. The regiment was disbanded in 1945. In 1947 it was re-established to resurrect the [[Special Air Service| Special Air Service Regiment]].{{Sfn | Gregory | 2006, 297}}  Today, the full title of the Regiment is '''21 Special Air Service Regiment (Artists) (Reserve)'''.

== History ==

=== Formation and 19th century ===
[[File:Old Drill Hall, Duke's Road - geograph.org.uk - 777806.jpg|thumb|left|190px|Old Drill Hall, Duke's Road, built 1888, headquarters of the 20th Middlesex (Artists) Rifle Volunteer Corps]]
The regiment was formed in 1859, part of the widespread [[volunteer Force (Great Britain)|volunteer movement]] which developed in the face of potential [[France|French]] invasion after [[Felice Orsini]]'s attack on [[Napoleon III]] was linked to [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|Britain]].{{Sfn | Gregory | 2006, xvi}}  The group was organised in [[London]] by Edward Sterling, an art student, and comprised various professional painters, musicians, actors, architects and others involved in creative endeavours. It was established on 28 February 1860 as the '''38th Middlesex (Artists) Rifle Volunteer Corps''', with headquarters at [[Burlington House]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Website&quot; /&gt; Its first commanders were the painters [[Henry Wyndham Phillips]] and [[Frederic Leighton, 1st Baron Leighton|Frederic Leighton]]. The unit's badge, designed by J.W. Wyon, shows the heads of the Roman gods [[Mars (mythology)|Mars]] and [[Minerva]] in profile.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.artistsriflesassociation.org/images/Mars-Minerva.jpg | title = Mars-Minerva | format = image | format = [[JPEG]] | publisher = Artists Rifles Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1880, the corps became the '''20th Middlesex (Artists) Rifle Volunteer Corps''', with headquarters at Duke's Road, off [[Euston Road]], London (now [[The Place]],  home of the Contemporary Dance Trust). It formed the 7th Volunteer Battalion of the Rifle Brigade from 1881 until 1891 and the 6th Volunteer Battalion from 1892 to 1908. During this period, the Artists Rifles fought in the [[Boer Wars]] as part of the City Imperial Volunteers.{{Sfn | Gregory | 2006, 80}} Following the formation of the [[Territorial Force]], the Artists Rifles was one of twenty-eight volunteer battalions in the London and [[Middlesex]] areas that combined to form the new [[London Regiment]]. It became the '''28th (County of London) Battalion''' of the London Regiment on 1 April 1908.{{Sfn | Gregory | 2006, 96}}

=== 20th century ===
[[Image:NashOverTheTop.jpg|thumb|280px|left|''Over The Top'', 1918, oil on canvas, by [[John Nash]]. The 30 December 1917 Welsh Ridge counter-attack, during which the 1st Battalion Artists Rifles left their trenches and pushed towards [[Marcoing]] near [[Cambrai]]. Of the eighty men, sixty-eight were killed or wounded during the first few minutes. ]]

The Artists Rifles was a popular unit for volunteers. It had been increased to twelve companies in 1900 and was formed into three sub-battalions in 1914, and recruitment was eventually restricted by recommendation from existing members of the battalion. It particularly attracted recruits from [[Independent school (UK)|public schools]] and [[University|universities]]; on this basis, following the outbreak of the [[World War I|First World War]], a number of enlisted members of the Artists Rifles were selected to be officers in other units of the [[7th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|7th Division]].&lt;ref name=Website/&gt; This exercise was so successful that, early in 1915, selected Artists officers and NCOs were transferred to run a separate Officers Training Corps, the remainder being retained as a fighting unit. Over fifteen thousand men passed through the battalion during the war, more than ten thousand of them becoming officers.{{Sfn | Higham | 1922, xviii}}  The battalion eventually saw battle in France in 1917 and 1918. Casualties suffered by both members of this battalion and amongst officers who had trained with the Artists Rifles before being posted to other regiments were 2,003 killed, 3,250 wounded, 533 missing and 286 prisoners of war.&lt;ref name=Website/&gt; Members of the Regiment won eight Victoria Crosses, fifty-six Distinguished Service Orders and over a thousand other awards for gallantry.{{Sfn | Higham | 1922, xviii}}

In the early 1920s, the unit was reconstituted as an infantry regiment within the [[Territorial Army (United Kingdom)|Territorial Army]], as the '''28th County of London Regiment'''. In 1937, this regiment became part of the '''Prince Consort's Own [[Rifle Brigade (Prince Consort's Own)|Rifle Brigade]]'''.{{Sfn | Gregory | 2006, 253}}

The regiment was not deployed during the [[World War II|Second World War]], functioning again as an Officers Training Corps throughout the war.&lt;ref name=Website/&gt;

It was disbanded in 1945, but reformed in the Rifle Brigade in January 1947 and transferred to the [[Army Air Corps (United Kingdom)|Army Air Corps]] in July as the '''21st [[Special Air Service]] Regiment (Artists Rifles)'''.{{Sfn | Gregory | 2006, 297}}  The number 21 SAS was chosen to perpetuate two disbanded wartime regiments 1 SAS and 2 SAS, with the 1 and the 2 being reversed into 21. 21 SAS was active during the [[Malayan Emergency]] and in many subsequent conflicts. In 1952, members of the Artists Rifles who had been involved in special operations in Malaya formed 22 SAS, the modern [[special forces]] regiment - the only time a Territorial Army unit has been used to form a unit in the Regular Army.&lt;ref&gt;James G. Shortt, pages 16-17 &quot;The Special Air Service&quot;, ISBN 0  85045 396 8&lt;/ref&gt;

For much of the [[Cold War]], 21 SAS's role was to provide [[Stay-behind|stay-behind parties]] in the event of a [[Warsaw Pact]] invasion of western Europe (as part of the Corps Patrol Unit alongside 23 SAS and the [[Honourable Artillery Company]]).{{Sfn | Ballinger | 1992}}{{Rp| needed = yes|date=August 2012}}

== Current role and structure ==
[[File:The Artists' Rifles HQ - geograph.org.uk - 777821.jpg|thumb|right|Terracotta doorway at the former Artists' Rifles HQ]]
21 SAS consists of:
* 'HQ' Squadron ([[Regent's Park]])
* 'A' Squadron (Regent's Park)
* 'C' Squadron (Basingstoke/Cambridge)
* 'E' Squadron (Newport/Exeter)

The regiment's current role is to provide depth to the [[United Kingdom Special Forces]] (UKSF) group. 21 SAS is tasked to the highest level and can operate in difficult and often changing circumstances, sometimes in absence of guidance and within situations that have significant operational and strategic importance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.army.mod.uk/specialforces/10551.aspx | title = Army | contribution = Special forces | place = [[United Kingdom|UK]] | publisher = [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|MoD]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Support Squadron provides support staff to UKSF(R) activities including personnel such as drivers from the [[Royal Logistic Corps|RLC]], [[Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers|REME]] weapon technicians, combat medics, [[Intelligence Corps (United Kingdom)|Intelligence Corps]] personnel and Ops room staff.

== Battle honours ==
&lt;small&gt;See [[Special Air Service]] for their battle honours&lt;/small&gt;
* '''Boer War''': [[Second Boer War|South Africa 1900–01]].
* '''The Great War''' (3 battalions): Ypres 1917, [[Battle of Passchendaele|Passchendaele]], Somme 1918, St. Quentin, Bapaume 1918, Arras 1918, Ancre 1918, Albert 1918, Drocourt-Quéant, Hindenburg Line, Canal du Nord, Cambrai 1918, Pursuit to Mons, France and Flanders 1914–18.&lt;ref name=Website/&gt;

== War memorial ==
The unit's war memorial in the entrance portico of the [[Royal Academy]] at [[Burlington House]] commemorates the 2003 men who gave their lives in the Great War with a second plaque to those who died in World War II.

== Victoria Cross ==
The following members of the regiment were awarded the [[Victoria Cross]] in the Great War:
*2nd Lt [[Rupert Price Hallowes]]
*2nd Lt [[Arthur James Terence Fleming-Sandes]]
*Capt The Rev [[Edward Noel Mellish]]
*Lt [[Geoffrey St George Shillington Cather]]
*Lt [[Eugene Paul Bennett]]
*2nd Lt [[George Edward Cates]]
*Lt [[Donald John Dean]]
*Lt Col [[Bernard William Vann]]

== See also ==
::See also [[:Category:Artists' Rifles officers]] and [[:Category:Artists' Rifles soldiers]]

* [[Volunteer Force (Great Britain)]]
* [[Rifle Brigade (Prince Consort's Own)|Prince Consort's Own Rifle Brigade]]
* [[Bear Grylls]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist | group = &quot;nb&quot; | 30 em}}

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{Citation | last = Ballinger | first = Adam | year = 1992 | title = The Quiet Soldier | publisher = Chapmans | ISBN = 978-1-85592-606-6}}.
* {{Citation | last = Gregory | first = Barry | year = 2006 | title = A History of The Artists Rifles 1859–1947 | publisher = Pen &amp; Sword Books | place = Barnsley | ISBN = 978-1-84415-503-3}}.
* {{Citation | last = Hacking | first = Juliet | year = 2000 | title = Princes of Victorian Bohemia | publisher = National Portrait Gallery}}.
* {{Citation | last = Higham | first = S Stagoll | origyear = 1922, Howlett &amp; Son | title = Artists Rifles: Regimental Roll of Honour and War Record 1914–1919 | edition = 3rd | place = London | year = 2006 | publisher = Naval &amp; Military Press | ISBN = 978-1-84734-129-7}}.
* {{Citation | last = Winter | first = JM | year = 1977 | title = Britain’s ‘Lost Generation’ of the First World War | journal = Population Studies | volume = 31 | number = 3 | page = 459}}.

== External links ==
* {{Citation | url = http://www.army.mod.uk/rolefinder/role/188/sas-soldier-reserves/ | title = To enquire about joining 21 SAS(R) contact recruit enquiries}}.
* {{Citation | url = http://www.artistsriflesassociation.org/ | title = Artists Rifles Association}}.
* {{Citation | url = http://www.scribd.com/full/12459452?access_key=key-2i2kwkw92tjhjeyip7ym | title = A Presentation of Some Works of Art Produced by Some Members of the Artists Rifles | publisher = Cli | place = GS}}.
* {{Citation | url = https://www.facebook.com/TheArtistsRifles | title = Facebook page: The artists of The Artists Rifles}}.
* {{Citation | url = http://pinterest.com/patrickbaty/artists-of-the-artists-rifles/ | title = Pinterest board: The artists of The Artists Rifles}}.
* {{Citation | url = https://twitter.com/artistsrifles | title = Twitter feed: The artists of The Artists Rifles}}.
* {{Citation | url = http://www.army.mod.uk/specialforces/11260.aspx | contribution = Supporting Squadrons to UKSF  | title = Army: Special forces | place = [[United Kingdom|UK]] | publisher = [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|MoD]]}}.

[[Category:British art]]
[[Category:Special forces of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Territorial Army (United Kingdom)]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1859]]
[[Category:Infantry regiments of the British Army]]
[[Category:Regiments of the British Army in World War I]]
[[Category:London Regiment]]
[[Category:1859 establishments in the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>iefgcxeohbxtd85l2zzc8ty0fyvtuu4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Anna (1951 film)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11796087</id>
    <revision>
      <id>541639834</id>
      <parentid>527516360</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-02T03:28:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 3 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q1080924]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3792">{{Infobox film
| name           = Anna
| image          = Anna1951.jpg
| image size     =
| caption        =
| director       = [[Alberto Lattuada]]
| producer       = [[Dino De Laurentiis]]&lt;br&gt;[[Carlo Ponti]]
| writer         = [[Giuseppe Berto]]&lt;br&gt;[[Franco Brusati]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ivo Perilli]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dino Risi]]&lt;br&gt;[[Rodolfo Sonego]]
| narrator       =
| starring       = [[Silvana Mangano]]&lt;br&gt;[[Raf Vallone]]&lt;br&gt;[[Vittorio Gassman]]&lt;br&gt;[[Gaby Morlay]]&lt;br&gt;[[Patrizia Mangano]]  	
| music          = [[Nino Rota]]
| cinematography = [[Otello Martelli]]
| editing        = [[Gabriele Varriale]]
| distributor    =
| released       = {{start date|1951|12|20|df=y}}
| runtime        = 107 minutes
| country        = Italy
| language       = Italian
| budget         =
}}
'''''Anna'''''  is a 1951 [[Cinema of Italy|Italian]] [[drama film]] directed by [[Alberto Lattuada]] and starring the same trio as ''[[Bitter Rice]]'': [[Silvana Mangano]] as Anna, the [[sin]]ner who becomes a [[nun]]; [[Raf Vallone]] as Andrea, the rich man who loves her; and [[Vittorio Gassman]] as Vittorio, the wicked waiter who sets Anna on a dangerous path.

Silvana Mangano's real sister, Patrizia Mangano, acts as Anna's sister on the film. [[Sophia Loren]] has got a small uncredited role as a nightclub assistant. Future film directors [[Franco Brusati]] and [[Dino Risi]] cowrote the script.

The film features the songs ''[[Non Dimenticar]]'' and ''El Negro Zumbon'' .

==Plot==
A man (Vallone) suffers a car accident. He's taken to hospital, where Sister Anna (Mangano) takes care of him. The man is the reason Anna became a nun. She remembers the days she was leading a life of sin as a night club singer.

==Reception==
''Anna'' is one of the greatest successes of [[Cinema of Italy|Italian cinema]]. ''El Negro Zumbon'' became a classic in Italy and Spain. [[Nanni Moretti]] paid a tribute in ''[[Caro diario|Dear Diary]]'', in which the song is shown on a TV, and the opening of the song is featured in ''[[Cinema Paradiso]]''.

==Trivia==
In the original Italian version, the voices of many actors in the film are dubbed:
*Silvana Mangano: [[Lydia Simoneschi]], the queen of Italian dubbing, who also dubbed her in [[Bitter Rice]], [[Outlaw Girl]], [[Mambo (film)|Mambo]] and [[Ulysses (1955 film)|Ulysees]]; Simoneschi is particularly known for having dubbed [[Bette Davis]], [[Ingrid Bergman]], [[Jennifer Jones]], [[Vivien Leigh]] in ''[[Gone with the wind (film)|Gone with the wind]]'' and so on
*Vittorio Gassman: [[Gualtiero De Angelis]], the official Italian voice for [[James Stewart]], [[Dean Martin]] or [[Cary Grant]]
*Raf Vallone: [[Mario Pisu]], best known for having dubbed all of the [[Fred McMurray]]'s Disney films (except for [[The Shaggy Dog]])
*Gaby Morlay: [[Tina Lattanzi]], the official Italian voice for [[Greta Garbo]], [[Joan Crawford]] and Disney villains (until 1959)
*Tina Lattanzi herself appears in the film as Andrea's mother and she is dubbed by [[Giovanna Scotto]]!
*Other very known voices we can hear in this film are: [[Emilio Cigoli]] ([[Gregory Peck]], [[John Wayne]], [[Clark Gable]]), [[Giuseppe Rinaldi]] ([[Rock Hudson]], [[Jack Lemmon]], [[Paul Newman]]), [[Rosetta Calavetta]] ([[Marilyn Monroe]] from approximately 1954, [[Doris Day]], [[Lana Turner]]), [[Miranda Bonansea]] ([[Marilyn Monroe]] until approximately 1954, [[Shirley Temple]], [[June Allyson]])

== External links ==
* {{IMDb title | id = 0043287 | title = Anna}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anna (1951 Film)}}
[[Category:Films set in Italy]]
[[Category:Films set in Milan]]
[[Category:1951 films]]
[[Category:Italian films]]
[[Category:Film scores by Nino Rota]]
[[Category:Italian-language films]]
[[Category:1950s drama films]]
[[Category:Black-and-white films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Alberto Lattuada]]</text>
      <sha1>olsgc02pa0vma1pbgwc28x7cpuk4yfi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Salvatore Ruggiero</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19651164</id>
    <revision>
      <id>541766459</id>
      <parentid>537771586</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-02T18:46:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dimadick</username>
        <id>24198</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13063">'''Salvatore Frank Ruggiero Sr.'''  pronounced (roo-JEH-roh) (July 20, 1945 – May 1982), also known as &quot;Sal the [[Sphinx]]&quot;, &quot;Sal Quack Quack&quot; and &quot;Sally&quot;, was a [[Gambino crime family]] mob associate and [[drug trafficker]] who was the younger brother of [[Angelo Ruggiero]] and ringleader of &quot;The Pleasant Avenue Connection&quot; which was a precursor to the [[Pizza Connection Trial]] drug smuggling operation. He became a fugitive in the late 1970s. He was a passenger on an aircraft that crashed on May 6, 1982; his body was recovered on May 14.

==Biography==

Salvatore Frank Ruggiero was born in [[East New York, Brooklyn]], to a first generation Italian immigrant John Ruggiero Jr. from Torre de Ruggiero in [[Catanzaro]], [[Calabria]], [[Italy]] and an [[Italian-American]] woman named Mary Dellacroce who lived in [[Howard Beach, Queens]]. Mary was the biological sister of Gambino crime family [[underboss]] [[Aniello Dellacroce]]. It is unknown if his father John Jr. was a member of organized crime and served under [[Albert Anastasia]] or [[Carlo Gambino]]. Salvatore became involved in criminal activity at a young age and joined the powerful Fulton-Rockaway Boys gang member like his older brother Angelo Ruggiero and [[John Gotti]]. He was a sphinx compared to his brother Angelo. It is suggested by John Volkman and Ernest Cummings that Salvatore remained quiet and subdued because he had no hope of ever getting a word in with his brother Angelo around. He preferred to invest his energies in a mad quest for speed. Despite two serious injuries suffered in accidents on stolen motorcycles, Salvatore loved anything that he could propel at great velocity. Said to be a maniac behind the wheel of an automobile, he taught himself to drive at the age of thirteen, and like to roar around deserted areas of Brooklyn in stolen cars.

Angelo looked up towards his brother in awe at his skill of criminal enterprising, who tried in vain to emulate him. Unlike his brother Angelo, Salvatore exercised regularly and maintained a muscular physique while his brother chain smoked and had eating binges often. Salvatore later married an [[airline stewardess]] named Stephanie who bore him a son, Salvatore Ruggiero Jr., on January 8, 1972 who lives in [[Marlboro, New Jersey]]. The son followed his father and uncle into organized crime. Salvatore is the paternal uncle of Gambino crime family mob associates Angelo Ruggiero Jr. and John Ruggiero Jr. 

His uncle [[Aniello Dellacroce]] had an affair with the wife of the Gambino crime family capo [[Ernest Grillo Jr.]]. She bore Dellacroce two illegitimate children, Shannon Connelly and Sean Connelly. Ernest Grillo Jr. is the son of Gambino crime family mob associate and DeMeo crew associate, [[Danny Grillo]].

==Ending his obsession with speed==

By 1975, resulting from several serious injuries that led to hospitalization in the [[intensive care unit]], Salvatore was cured of his [[impulse control disorder]] that was the root cause of his addiction to high speed. Then, too, he had very little time for such pursuits, for Salvatore was a very busy millionaire &quot;businessman&quot; (as he preferred to call himself). He was dealing in heroin that made him one of the largest and wealthiest dealers in [[New York]] that included [[Gerlando Sciascia]], [[Alphonse Indelicato]], [[Cesare Bonventre]] and others who would later be indicted in the [[Pizza Connection Trial]].

Salvatore was not close to his uncle and remained distant to his younger brother, and strived to be more than a street-level hood which Angelo would later become. Despite his long friendship with John Gotti, Salvatore did not seem consumed with the ambition to become a major Mafia powerhouse as did his brother, Angelo, and their mutual friend. He built criminal business relationships with [[Gene Gotti]], [[John Carneglia]], mob criminal attorney [[Michael Coiro]], Joseph Guagliano, Anthony Moscatiello, Oscar Ansourian, Edward Lino, Mark Reiter, William Robert Cestaro, Salvatore Greco, Joseph Lo Presti, Vincent Lore, Anthony Gurino and Caesar Gurino, Instead, he appeared content to stay on the fringes of the Gambino crime family organization and the Bergin crew as some sort of vague associate, although no one seemed quite certain what he did. He had graduated from street thuggery and became a multimillionaire, selling a range of drugs, from major shipments of marijuana, to heroin and cocaine.

Wanted on several charges, he had become a fugitive, hiding out with his wife, Stephanie under various aliases in [[New Jersey]], [[Florida]], [[Pennsylvania]] and [[Ohio]]. Salvatore could afford life on the run. He secretly owned hideouts in [[Fort Lauderdale, Florida]] and the [[Poconos]] and traded heavily in stocks and bonds under other names. He also owned a diner, a greeting card store, and other investment property purchased through a company called Ozone Holding, named after [[Ozone Park, Queens]]. He owned four cars including a [[Mercedes Benz]] and ten watches worth $12,000 each. He was living in a leased home in [[New Jersey]] while another mansion on Tortoise Lane in [[Franklin Lakes, New Jersey]] was being built for him through a company run by Anthony and Caesar Gurino, owners of Arc Plumbing Corporation, the mobsters who gave John Gotti and Angelo Ruggiero no-show jobs. His prime heroin supplier was [[Gerlando Sciascia]]. He secretly controlled a [[Liberia]] based corporation, Vimi Steamship Limited in 1981. The vagueness was deliberate, for Salvatore by 1970 was deeply involved in heroin trafficking, and by La Cosa Nostra regulations, that was strictly forbidden. So the fiction had to be maintained: Ruggiero moved heroin while officially neither his capo Carmine Fatico, nor John Gotti, nor Carlo Gambino knew anything about it. All the while, Fatico accepted a share of the heroin sales' proceeds from Sal, with the facade further maintained by both men's bland insistence that the money was the result of some successful transport truck hijackings from [[John F. Kennedy International Airport]].

==Death==

On May 6, 1982 a [[Gates Learjet]] 23 N100TA took off from [[Teterboro, New Jersey]], at 10:28 a.m., which was a good day for flying. The pilot, George Morton had been told, when he checked conditions earlier in the day, that there was no hazardous weather on the horizon and it looked like clear flying through to [[Orlando, Florida]]. On board the Learjet, which was owned by IBEX Corporation, Morton was joined by a stand-in pilot, Sherri Day and two passengers- a husband and wife who were described by IBEX management as business associates being flown to a meeting in Orlando. Salvatore was interested in purchasing a [[McDonald's]] franchise chain restaurant in [[Magic Kingdom]], Disney World. Morton flew the jet while Day handled the radio communications. For more than an hour, the flight was uneventful. Then, from over the Atlantic Ocean, Day radioed the Jacksonville, Florida air traffic control center requesting landing status. An air traffic controller instructed the pilot to lower its altitude from Flight Level 410 to Flight Level 390. The Learjet however, did not immediately start its descent. A minute and a half later, Day made another brief transmission, which was unintelligible. At noon, the crew of a fishing boat spotted a huge water geyser on the surface of the Atlantic, twelve miles southeast of [[Savannah, Georgia]]. The captain sped to the scene and found debris scattered across the surface finding bits of skin from the fuselage and pieces of the Learjet's interior, but no survivors. Ninety minutes after the crash, the [[National Transportation Safety Board]] was notified. 

That same day, a team of three investigators was dispatched from [[Washington, D.C.]] On May 13, a search team, using [[sonar]] equipment, began an underwater scan of the crash site. Visibility underwater was poor and it was not until late in the afternoon the next day that the main wreckage was found, fifty-five feet below the surface, scattered over seventy-five feet of the ocean floor. George Morton's body and those of the two passengers were recovered from the wreckage. All had suffered multiple traumatic injuries. Day's body was never found. After examining the debris, the NTSB was unable to determine the cause of the crash. The weather was almost ideal for flying, for another pilot said he had encountered no difficulties in the area at about the same time. An explosion was eliminated as a possible cause, as was an onboard fire. The pilot and co-pilot were both certified and the jet had been well maintained. 

&quot;The National Transportation Safety Board determined that the probable cause for the accident was an uncontrolled descent from cruise altitude for undetermined reasons from which a recovery was not, or could not be, effected&quot;, the official Aircraft Accident report concluded. The NTSB investigation could not help solve the mystery of why the Learjet plunged into the Atlantic Ocean, but it did end the longstanding fugitive from justice, Ruggiero. 

Until his body was identified in a morgue, Ruggiero had been listed as a fugitive from justice, a member of the Gambino crime family, a large scale heroin trafficker and a key customer of [[Vito Rizzuto]]'s drug operation. When the Learjet carrying Salvatore nose dived into the Atlantic Ocean, Salvatore had been on the run for six years. Being a fugitive had not slowed his drug-dealing activities; at the time of his death, he had yet another shipment of heroin, taken on credit from [[George Sciascia]], stored in his house awaiting resale.

==Personal toll on Angelo==

After Angelo was notified of his brother's death, he, along with Gene Gotti and John Carneglia, went to Salvatore's hideout in [[Franklin Lakes, New Jersey]], searching for a yet-to-be-sold shipment of heroin and cash. A few months earlier however, hoping to catch up with his elusive brother and to gain evidence to indict John Gotti, the FBI's Gambino Squad had thoroughly wired Angelo's home. Not only was his telephone line bugged, but microphones were placed in his kitchen, den and dining room. Federal agents were able to record Angelo's attorney Micheal Coiro, offering condolences to Angelo on the death of his brother, and then saying, &quot;Gene found the heroin.&quot; 

The talk of heroin in the wake of Salvatore's death and the connection to a Gotti family relative seized the attention of the investigating FBI agents. The investigation into Angelo suddenly held promise in leading to indictments of major family operatives. Angelo was known as a constant chatter-box, providing a running commentary on everything going on around him. Everyone who visited him had to endure endless gossip, complaints and general indiscretions. The death of his brother Salvatore, hit Angelo hard and he was often overheard on FBI wiretaps in his Cedarhurst, New York home wistfully speaking of his brother to Gerlando Sciascia and Joseph LoPresti, his two drug trafficking partners. 

Unlike his brother Salvatore who became a multi-millionaire from his successful large scale drug trafficking operation, Angelo would never rise above a wealthy street-level mobster. 
He later told Joseph LoPresti, &quot;You know I lost my brother. I said to myself: &quot;I'll have to get drunk&quot;. I had two vodkas... I went in my room, I closed the door and I cried....&quot; The bugs also overheard Angelo saying how difficult it was accepting his brother's death because the body was in &quot;fuckin pieces.&quot; He added: &quot;If he would have been shot in the head and [they] found him in the streets- that's part of our life, I could accept that.&quot;

A memorial service was held in Howard Beach at Mary Dellacroce's house. Afterward Angelo said his late younger brother, &quot;... had a pretty good, nice sendoff. I mean my whole fucking family [and]... all the wiseguys in the family (Gambino crime family) were there.&quot; Angelo who had scheduled a secret rendezvous with Salvatore for that day made arrangements for the welfare of his brother's child Salvatore Ruggiero Jr.

==References==

* ''Goombata: The Improbable Rise and Fall of John Gotti and His Gang'' by John Cummings and Ernest Volkman
* ''Mob Star: The Story of John Gotti'' by Jerry Capeci and Gene Mustain
* ''The Sixth Family: The Collapse of the New York Mafia and the Rise of Vito Rizzuto'' (2006), by Lee Lamothe and Adrian Humphreys, John Wiley &amp; Sons Canada Ltd., ISBN 0-470-83753-5
* http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19820506-0

{{Gambino crime family}}{{American Mafia}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Ruggiero, Salvatore
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = July 20, 1945
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1982
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Ruggiero, Salvatore}}
[[Category:1945 births]]
[[Category:1982 deaths]]
[[Category:American drug traffickers]]
[[Category:Gambino crime family]]
[[Category:American mobsters]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents]]</text>
      <sha1>eziwv9y1h06ua6ldeevn859fxbeig5j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Protocol (natural sciences)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9190286</id>
    <revision>
      <id>541591298</id>
      <parentid>533236996</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-01T21:25:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 3 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q367158]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8104">{{sisterlinks|wikt=protocol|b=Biology Laboratory Techniques|q=no|s=no|commons=no|n=no|v=no|species=no}}{{Refimprove|date=December 2008}}In the [[natural sciences]] a '''protocol''' is a predefined written procedural method in the design and implementation of [[experiments]].  Protocols are written whenever it is desirable to standardize a laboratory method to ensure successful [[Reproducibility|replication]] of results by others in the same laboratory or by other laboratories. Detailed protocols also facilitate the assessment of results through [[peer review]].  In addition to detailed procedures and lists of required equipment and instruments, protocols often include information on safety precautions, the calculation of results and reporting standards, including statistical analysis and rules for predefining and documenting excluded data to avoid bias. Protocols are employed in a wide range of experimental fields, from [[social science]] to [[quantum mechanics]]. Written protocols are also employed in manufacturing to ensure consistent quality.

== Overview ==
Formal protocols are the general rule in fields of applied science, such as environmental and medical studies that require the coordinated, standardized work of many participants. Such predefined protocols are an essential component of [[Good Laboratory Practice]] (GLP)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fda.gov/ICECI/EnforcementActions/BioresearchMonitoring/NonclinicalLaboratoriesInspectedunderGoodLaboratoryPractices/ucm072706.htm|title=1987 Final Rule - Good Laboratory Practice Regulations|date=1987-09-04|publisher=DHHS, Food and Drug Administration|accessdate=2009-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Good clinical practice|Good Clinical Practice]] (GCP)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ich.org/LOB/media/MEDIA482.pdf|title=Guideline for Good Clinical Practice|date=1996-06-10|publisher=International Conference on Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for the Registration of Pharmaceuticals for Human Use|accessdate=2009-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; regulations. Protocols written for use by a specific laboratory may incorporate or reference [[standard operating procedure]]s (SOP) governing general practices required by the laboratory. A protocol may also reference applicable laws and regulations that are applicable to the procedures described.  Formal protocols typically require approval by a laboratory official before they are implemented for general use.

Manufacturing protocols are required by current [[good manufacturing practice]] (cGMP) for manufacture of [[food]]s, [[pharmaceutical]]s, and [[medical device]]s.

In a [[clinical trial]], the protocol is carefully designed to safeguard the health of the participants as well as answer specific research questions. A protocol describes what types of people may participate in the trial; the schedule of tests, procedures, medications, and dosages; and the length of the study. While in a clinical trial, participants following a protocol are seen regularly by research staff to monitor their health and to determine the safety and effectiveness of their treatment. Since 1996, clinical trials conducted are widely expected to conform to and report the information called for the in the [[Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials|CONSORT]] Statement, which provides a framework for designing and reporting protocols. Though tailored to health and medicine, ideas in the CONSORT statement are broadly applicable to other fields where experimental research is used. Clearly defined protocols are also required by research funded by the [[National Institutes of Health]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/info/understand | title = Understanding Clinical Trials | accessdate = 2012-04-21 | work = ClinicalTrials.gov | publisher = National Institute of Health}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Safety ==
Safety precautions are a valuable addition to a protocol, and can range from requiring goggles to provisions for containment of microbes, environmental hazards, toxic substances, and volatile solvents. Procedural contingencies in the event of an accident may be included in a protocol or in a referenced SOP.

==Procedures==
Procedural information may include not only safety procedures but also procedures for avoiding contamination, calibration of equipment, equipment testing, documentation, and all other relevant issues. These procedural protocols can be used by skeptics to invalidate any claimed results if flaws are found.

==Equipment==
Equipment testing and documentation includes all necessary specifications, calibrations, operating ranges, etc. Environmental factors such as temperature, humidity, barometric pressure, and other factors can often have effects on results. Documenting these factors should be a part of any good procedure.

==Calculations, Statistics and Bias==
Protocols for methods that produce numerical results generally include detailed formulae for calculation of results.  Formula may also be included for preparation of reagents and other solutions required for the work. Methods of [[statistics|statistical analysis]] may be included to guide interpretation of the data. 

Many protocols include provisions for avoiding bias in the interpretation of results. [[Approximation error]] is common to all measurements. These errors can be absolute errors from limitations of the equipment or propagation errors from approximate numbers used in calculations. [[Sample bias]] is the most common and sometimes the hardest bias to quantify. Statisticians often go to great lengths to ensure that the [[Sample (statistics)|sample]] used is representative. For instance political polls are best when restricted to likely voters and this is one of the reasons why web polls cannot be considered scientific. The [[sample size]] is another important concept and can lead to biased data simply due to an unlikely event. A sample size of 10, i.e. polling 10 people, will seldom give valid polling results.  [[Standard deviation]] and [[variance]] are concepts used to quantify the likely relevance of a given [[sample size]]. The [[mass media]] and the public often use ''[[average]]'' and ''[[arithmetic mean|mean]]'' values interchangeably, which can lead to dubious and even misleading arguments. The [[placebo effect]] and [[observer bias]] often require an experiment to use a [[double blind]] protocol and a [[control group]].

==Blinded protocols==
A protocol may require blinding to avoid bias.  

: A [[single blind]] protocol requires that the experimenter does not know the identity of samples or animals during the testing and calculations.  It is appropriate when no human subjects are involved.

: A [[double blind]] protocol comes into play when human subjects are tested and requires insuring neither the experimenter nor experimental subjects have knowledge of the identity of the treatments or the results until after the experiment is complete.

An experimenter may have latitude defining procedures for blinding and controls but may be required to justify those choices if the results are published or submitted to a regulatory agency. When it is known during the experiment which data was negative there are often reasons to rationalize why that data shouldn't be included. Positive data are rarely rationalized the same way.

== Reporting ==
A protocol may specify reporting requirements.  Reporting requirements would include all elements of the experiments design and protocols and any environmental factors or mechanical limitations that might affect the validity of the results.

==See also==
*[[Blocking (statistics)]]
*[[Design of experiments]]
*[[Double blind]]
*[[Estimation]]
*[[Estimation theory]]
*[[Margin of error]]
*[[Milwaukee protocol]]
*[[Observational error]]
*[[Propagation of error]]
*[[Random error]]
*[[Randomized controlled trial]]
*[[Sample (statistics)]]
*[[Sample size]]
*[[Sampling error]]
*[[Scientific control]]
*[[Standard deviation]]
*[[Statistical population]]
*[[Survey sampling]]
*[[Systematic error]]
*[[Protein methods]] and [[Nucleic acid methods]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Natural sciences]]</text>
      <sha1>arlv26oxloxaelmkf3cq21ji7qj03km</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
<page>

    <title>Chris Farley</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>144218</id>
    <revision>
      <id>543662865</id>
      <parentid>543662713</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-12T17:43:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>92.61.200.25</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Death and funeral */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20557">{{Infobox person
| image = Chris Farley.jpg
| caption = Farley featured in a [[BBC]] promotional photo for ''[[Saturday Night Live]]''.
| alt = A close-up of Farley smiling at the camera
| name = Chris Farley
| birth_name = Christopher Crosby Farley
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1964|02|15|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Madison, Wisconsin]], U.S.
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1997|12|18|1964|02|15|mf=y}}
| death_place = [[John Hancock Center]], [[Chicago]], Illinois, U.S.
| death_cause = [[Cocaine intoxication]] and [[morphine]] [[overdose]] 
| resting_place = Resurrection Catholic Cemetery, Madison, Wisconsin
| occupation = Comedian, actor
| nationality = American
| alma_mater = [[Marquette University]]
| influences = [[John Belushi]]
| notable_works = ''[[Saturday Night Live]]''
| years_active = 1989–1997
| parents = Tom Farley, Sr.&lt;br&gt;Mary Anne Farley
| relatives = [[John P. Farley]] (brother)&lt;br&gt;[[Kevin Farley]] (brother)
}}

'''Christopher Crosby &quot;Chris&quot; Farley ''' (February 15, 1964&amp;nbsp;– December 18, 1997) was an American comedian and actor. Farley was best known for his loud, energetic comedy style and physical comedy, and was a member of [[Chicago]]'s [[The Second City|Second City Theatre]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.secondcity.com/?id=history/alumni/chicago |title=Chicago Alumni |publisher=The Second City |date= |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Saturday Night Live cast|cast member]] of the [[NBC]] [[sketch comedy]] show ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' between 1990 and 1995. Farley and [[Chris Rock]] were introduced as two of the show's new cast members in early 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;whs&quot;/&gt; Similar to his idol, [[John Belushi]], Farley died of a [[Speedball (drug)|speedball]] overdose at the age of 33. On August 26, 2005, Farley was posthumously awarded the 2,289th star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]], which is located in front of [[I.O. West|iO West]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Chris Farley Gets Posthumous Star&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.breitbart.com/news/2005/08/26/D8C7P4M01.html |title=Chris Farley Gets Posthumous Star |publisher=Breitbart.com |date=1964-02-15 |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Farley was born in [[Madison, Wisconsin]]. His father, Thomas &quot;Tom&quot; Farley, Sr., owned an oil company, and his mother, Mary Anne (née Crosby), was a housewife.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://movies.yahoo.com/movie/contributor/1800018622/bio |title=Chris Farley Biography&amp;nbsp;— Yahoo! Movies |publisher=Movies.yahoo.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.filmreference.com/film/65/Chris-Farley.html|title=Chris Farley Biography (1964-1997)|publisher=filmreference.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had four siblings: Tom Jr., [[Kevin Farley|Kevin]], [[John P. Farley|John]], and Barbara. His cousin, Jim, is a vice president at [[Ford Motor Company]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/freep/access/1793009141.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Jul+18%2C+2009&amp;author=GREG+GARDNER&amp;pub=Detroit+Free+Press&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=A.9&amp;desc=Rising+star+assigned+new+duties+at+Ford|title=Rising star assigned new duties at Ford|first=Greg|last=Gardner|newspaper=[[Detroit Free Press]]|date=2009-07-18|accessdate=2011-09-04}} {{registration required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/20/business/20ford.html?pagewanted=4&amp;n=Top/News/Business/Companies/Toyota%20Motor%20Corporation|title=A Star at Toyota, a Believer at Ford|last=Vlasic|first=Bill|date=2008-04-20|publisher=New York Times|page=4|accessdate=2008-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Farley's family are traditionally [[Irish American]], and Farley attended numerous Catholic schools in his hometown, including [[Edgewood High School of the Sacred Heart]]. According to [[Joel Murray]], a fellow Second City cast member, Farley would &quot;always make it to Mass&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thechrisfarleyshow.com/chicago.html|title=Chris Farley|publisher=The Chris Farley Show|accessdate=2011-09-04|archivedate=http://wayback.archive.org/web/*/http://www.thechrisfarleyshow.com/chicago.html|archiveurl=2009-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of his summers were spent as a camper and counselor at [[Red Arrow Camp]], near [[Minocqua, Wisconsin]].

Farley graduated from [[Marquette University]] in 1986, with a concentration in [[Communication studies|communications]] and [[theater]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marquette.edu/about/allfamous.shtml |title=Marquette University&amp;nbsp;— Famous Faces |publisher=Marquette.edu |date=2003-02-12 |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; After college, he worked with his father at the Scotch Oil Company in Madison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thebiographychannel.co.uk/biography_story/557:166/1/Chris_Farley.htm |title=Chris Farley Biography |publisher=The Biography Channel |date= |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; He got his start in professional comedy at the Ark Improv Theatre in Madison, and at the [[I.O.|Improv Olympic]] theater in Chicago. He then performed at [[Chicago|Chicago's]] [[The Second City|Second City Theatre]], initially as part of Second City's touring group. He was eventually promoted to their main stage. While working at Second City, Farley befriended his ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' colleague [[Lorne Michaels]].&lt;ref name=&quot;whs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/highlights/archives/2008/05/farley_exhibit.asp |title=Wisconsin Historical Society |publisher=Wisconsinhistory.org |date= |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==

===''Saturday Night Live''===
Along with [[Chris Rock]], Farley was one of two new ''Saturday Night Live'' cast members announced in the spring of 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;whs&quot;/&gt; On ''SNL'', Farley frequently collaborated with his fellow cast members [[Adam Sandler]], [[Chris Rock]], [[Rob Schneider]], and [[David Spade]], among others. This group came to be known as the &quot;[[Bad Boys of SNL]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0500191/ The Bad Boys of Saturday Night Live (1998)(TV)]&lt;/ref&gt; Popular characters performed by Farley included himself on [[The Chris Farley Show]], a talk show in which Farley quite often &quot;interviewed&quot; the guest, got very nervous and asked simple-minded or irrelevant questions, such as what their favorite rock band was; [[Matt Foley]], an over-the-top [[motivational speaker]] who constantly reminded other characters that he &quot;lived in a van, down by the river&quot;;&lt;ref name=&quot;dada&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://nymag.com/arts/books/reviews/47039/|title=Dada’s Boy|last=Anderson|first=Sam|date=2008-05-16|publisher=New York|accessdate=2008-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Todd O'Connor of [[Bill Swerski's Superfans]], a group of stereotypical Chicagoans who constantly shouted [[Chicago Bears|&quot;da Bears!&quot;]];,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/highlights/archives/2008/05/farley_exhibit.asp|title=New Exhibit: Chris Farley Remembered|publisher=wisconsinhistory.org|accessdate=2008-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; a [[Chippendale's dancers|Chippendale's dancer]], in a famous sketch that paired him with guest host [[Patrick Swayze]];&lt;ref name=cnn&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2008/SHOWBIZ/books/05/07/chris.farley/|title='Chris Farley Show' stuffed with gossip|last=Goldblatt|first=Henry|publisher=CNN.com|accessdate=2008-06-08 | date=2008-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; one of the &quot;[[Gap Girls]]&quot;, who hung out together at a local mall; a stereotypical [[lunch lady]], to the theme of ''Lunchlady Land'' performed by [[Adam Sandler]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Crawford|first=Bill|title=Adam Sandler: America's Comedian|publisher=Macmillan|year=2000|page=75|isbn=0-312-26282-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Bennett Brauer]], a ''[[Weekend Update]]'' commentator who often divulged his personal and hygienic problems via [[air quotes]]. Some of these characters were brought to ''SNL'' from his days at Second City. Farley also performed impersonations of [[Tom Arnold (actor)|Tom Arnold]], who gave Farley's eulogy at his private funeral; [[Andrew Giuliani]], [[Jerry Garcia]], [[Meat Loaf]], [[Norman Schwarzkopf, Jr.|Norman Schwarzkopf]], [[Dom DeLuise]], [[Roger Ebert]], [[Carnie Wilson]], [[Newt Gingrich]], [[Mindy Cohn]], [[Mama Cass]], [[Hank Williams, Jr.]], and [[Rush Limbaugh]] were among the celebrities and real-life figures he portrayed.&lt;ref name=wisconsin&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/museum/artifacts/archives/003176.asp|title=Chris Farley's Black Sheep Jacket|publisher=wisconsinhistory.org|accessdate=2008-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Off-screen, Farley was well known for his pranks in the offices of ''Saturday Night Live''. This would refer to Sandler and Farley making late-night prank phone calls from the ''SNL'' offices in [[Rockefeller Center]], with Sandler speaking in an old woman's voice and Farley [[farting]] into the phone and [[mooning]] cars from a limousine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://nymag.com/arts/tv/features/47548/index6.html|title=Comedy Isn’t Funny|last=Smith|first=Chris|date=1995-03-15|publisher=New York|page=7|accessdate=2008-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://nymag.com/arts/tv/features/47548/index7.html|title=Comedy Isn’t Funny|last=Smith|first=Chris|date=1995-03-15|publisher=New York|page=8|accessdate=2008-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sandler told [[Conan O'Brien]] on ''[[The Tonight Show with Conan O'Brien|The Tonight Show]]'' that [[NBC]] fired him and Farley from the show in 1995.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sandler fired&quot;&gt;[http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/2010/01/21/2010-01-21_youre_not_alone_conan_obrien_adam_sandler_says_nbc_fired_him_and_chris_farley_fr.html &quot;You're not alone, Conan O'Brien: Adam Sandler says NBC fired him and Chris Farley from 'SNL'&quot;] Joe Dziemianowicz, ''New York Daily News'', January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Film career===

During his tenure on ''SNL'', Farley had roles in the comedy films ''[[Wayne's World (film)|Wayne's World]]'', ''[[Coneheads (film)|Coneheads]]'', ''[[Airheads]]'', and uncredited in ''[[Billy Madison]]''. He also appeared in the [[Red Hot Chili Peppers]] music video for &quot;[[Soul to Squeeze]]&quot; which was a song featured on the ''Coneheads'' soundtrack.

After Farley and most of his fellow cast members were released from their contracts at ''Saturday Night Live'' following the [[Saturday Night Live (season 20)|1994–1995 season]], Farley began focusing on his film career. His first two major films co-starred his fellow ''SNL'' colleague and close friend [[David Spade]]. Together, the duo made the films ''[[Tommy Boy]]'' and ''[[Black Sheep (1996 film)|Black Sheep]]''. These were a success at the domestic [[box office]], earning around $32 million each and gaining a large [[cult following]] on [[home video]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=blacksheep.htm |title=Box Office Mojo data for '&amp;#39;Black Sheep'&amp;#39; |publisher=Boxofficemojo.com |date=1996-03-15 |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=tommyboy.htm |title=Box Office Mojo data for '&amp;#39;Tommy Boy'&amp;#39; |publisher=Boxofficemojo.com |date=1995-05-16 |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; They established Farley as a relatively [[bankable star]] and he was given the title role of ''[[Beverly Hills Ninja]]'', which finished in first place at the box office on its opening weekend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=weekend&amp;id=beverlyhillsninja.htm |title=Box Office Mojo data for '&amp;#39;Beverly Hills Ninja'&amp;#39; |publisher=Boxofficemojo.com |date=1997-01-17 |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, drug and alcohol problems interfered throughout Farley's film work, and production of his final film, ''[[Almost Heroes]]'', was held up several times so Farley could attend rehab.&lt;ref name=nypost&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nypost.com/seven/12162007/entertainment/that_was_awesome__816891.htm?page=0|title=That Was Awesome!|last=Tucker|first=Reed|date=2007-12-16|publisher=New York Post|accessdate=2008-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; After his premature death on December 18, 1997, his final completed films, ''Almost Heroes'' and ''[[Dirty Work (1998 film)|Dirty Work]]'', were released [[List of works published posthumously|posthumous]]ly.

===Unfinished projects===
Farley was the original choice to voice the [[Shrek (character)|title character]] of the [[Dreamworks Animation|DreamWorks]] animated film ''[[Shrek]]'', but died just before recording was finished. It's said approximately 80-90% of his lines were recorded, but none of these recordings have surfaced. He was replaced by one of his ''SNL'' colleagues, [[Mike Myers (actor)|Mike Myers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dada&quot; /&gt; He was also planning a [[Matt Foley]] film with Spade.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} By the time of his death, Farley had also been in talks to co-star [[Vince Vaughn]] in the film ''The Gelfin'' and also to star in a biopic film about [[Roscoe Arbuckle|Fatty Arbuckle]].&lt;ref&gt;The Chris Farley Show, by Tom Farley, Jr. and Tanner Colby&lt;/ref&gt; Farley had also been in talks for the lead in an adaptation of the novel ''[[A Confederacy of Dunces]]''.

==Death and funeral==
[[File:Farleygrave.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Farley's grave in 2010]]
By early 1997, a visible decline in Farley's health was frequently noted in the press. Following his final guest appearance on ''SNL'' on October 25, 1997,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saturday-night-live.com/snl/reviews/97-98/farley.html|title=Chris Farley/The Mighty Mighty Bosstones episode reviews|publisher=saturday-night-live.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Farley's hoarse voice and flushed skin were the subject of public scrutiny.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://snltranscripts.jt.org/97/97d.phtml|title=Saturday Night Live Transcripts|publisher=snltranscripts.jt.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Shales|first=Tom|coauthors=Miller, James Andrew|title=Live from New York: An Uncensored History of Saturday Night Live|publisher=Back Bay|year=2003|pages=492, 493|isbn=0-316-73565-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the final years of his life, Farley had sought treatment for obesity and drug abuse on seventeen separate occasions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,281398,00.html|title=The Last Temptation of Chris|last=Nashawaty|first=Chris |publisher=ew.com|accessdate=2008-06-07|date=1998-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 18, 1997, Farley was found dead by his younger brother, [[John P. Farley|John]], in his apartment in the [[John Hancock Center]] in Chicago.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR111791888.html?categoryid=25&amp;cs=1|title=Comic Farley dies|last=Petrikin|first=Chris|date=1997-12-19|publisher=Variety|accessdate=2008-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; An autopsy later revealed that Farley had died of a cocaine and morphine overdose early that morning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6D81630F930A35752C0A96E958260|title=Chris Farley's Death Laid to Drug Overdose|date=1998-01-03|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=2008-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advanced [[atherosclerosis]] was cited as a &quot;significant contributing factor&quot;.&lt;ref name=nypost /&gt; Farley's death is often compared to that of his ''SNL'' idol [[John Belushi]], who also died at age 33 of an accidental drug [[overdose]] consisting of cocaine and heroin.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn&quot; /&gt;

Farley's private funeral was held at Our Lady Queen of Peace Catholic Church in his hometown of Madison, Wisconsin five days after his death. Over five hundred people attended his funeral, many of the comedians who had worked with him on ''Saturday Night Live'' and on film including [[Lorne Michaels]], [[Phil Hartman]] (who would die five months later), [[Adam Sandler]], [[Dan Aykroyd]] (who wore a leather jacket over his suit, same as he did at Belushi’s funeral), [[John Goodman]], [[Tom Arnold (actor)|Tom Arnold]], [[Chris Rock]], [[George Wendt]], and [[Rob Schneider]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.onlineathens.com/1997/122497/1224.a3farley.html |title=Athens Daily News&amp;nbsp;— Fellow comedians weep for Chris Farley |publisher=Onlineathens.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Notably absent was Farley's former ''SNL'' castmate and close friend [[David Spade]], who was later quoted as saying that he declined to attend Farley's funeral because he &quot;could not be in a room where Chris was in a box.&quot;&lt;ref name=wisconsin /&gt; However, Spade did appear on the special 25th anniversary episode of ''Saturday Night Live'' by holding back his tears to call for a moment of remembrance for Farley. Farley was entombed at the Resurrection Catholic Cemetery.

==Legacy==
On August 26, 2005, Farley was posthumously awarded the 2,289th star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]], which is located in front of [[I.O. West|iO West]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Chris Farley Gets Posthumous Star&quot;/&gt; In his memoir ''[[Gasping for Airtime]]'', [[Jay Mohr]] recalled a moment involving Farley and his ''SNL'' idol [[Phil Hartman]]. In the show's cast's goodbye song-and-dance performance to Hartman, the final scene featured Farley and Hartman embracing each other as the latter sang &quot;Goodbye&quot; to the camera.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mohr|first=Jay|title=Gasping for Airtime: Two Years in the Trenches of Saturday Night Live|publisher=Hyperion|year=2004|pages=292, 293|isbn=1-4013-0006-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The authorized biography of Farley, ''[[The Chris Farley Show]]'', was written by his brother Tom, Jr. and Tanner Colby.

==Filmography==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable plainrowheaders&quot;
|+Film
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Year
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Title
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Role
! scope=&quot;col&quot; class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | Notes
|-
|1992
|''[[Wayne's World (film)|Wayne's World]]''
|Security Guard
|
|-
|1993
|''[[Coneheads (film)|Coneheads]]''
|Ronnie the Mechanic
|
|-
|1993
|''[[Wayne's World 2]]''
|Milton
|
|-
|1994
|''[[Airheads]]''
|Officer Wilson
|
|-
|1995
|''[[Billy Madison]]''
|Bus Driver
|Uncredited&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Farley|first1=Tom|last2=Colby|first2=Tanner|title=The Chris Farley Show: A Biography in Three Acts|year=2006|publisher=Viking Adult|isbn=1-616-80458-0|page=337}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1995
| ''[[Tommy Boy]]''
|Thomas &quot;Tommy&quot; Callahan, III.
|[[MTV Movie Awards]] Best On-Screen Duo &lt;small&gt;(Shared with [[David Spade]])&lt;/small&gt;
|-
|1996
|''[[Black Sheep (1996 film)|Black Sheep]]''
|Mike Donnelly
|Nominated&amp;nbsp;— [[MTV Movie Awards]] Best Comedic Performance
|-
|1997
|''[[Beverly Hills Ninja]]''
|Haru
|Nominated&amp;nbsp;— [[MTV Movie Awards]] Best Comedic Performance
|-
|1998
|''[[Almost Heroes]]''
|Bartholomew Hunt
|Released posthumously
|-
|1998
|''[[Dirty Work (1998 film)|Dirty Work]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://articles.latimes.com/1998/jun/15/entertainment/ca-60022 | title= Macdonald's 'Dirty Work' Needs a Laugh Transplant | work = [[Los Angeles Times]] | date= June 15, 1998 | first= David | last = Kronke | accessdate = August 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Jimmy
|Uncredited; released posthumously
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable plainrowheaders&quot;
|+Television
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Year
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Title
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Role
! scope=&quot;col&quot; class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | Notes
|-
|1990–1995
|''[[Saturday Night Live]]''
|Various characters
|100 episodes
|-
|1992
|''[[The Jackie Thomas Show]]''
|Chris Thomas
|1 episode
|-
|1993
|''[[The Larry Sanders Show]]''
|Himself
|1 episode
|-
|1993
|''[[Roseanne (TV series)|Roseanne]]''
|Man in Clothing Store
|1 episode
|-
|1994
|''Tom''
|Chris
|1 episode
|-
|1997
|''[[All That]]''
|Chef Farley
|1 episode
|}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography}}
{{wikiquote}}
* {{IMDb name|394}}
* [http://maximonline.com/slideshows/index.aspx?slideId=3709&amp;imgCollectId=194&amp;src=jb203 Maxim Rated Top SNL performer]
* [http://www.jesterjournal.com/ChrisFarleyShow.htm Review of Chris Farley biography]
* {{Find a Grave|2467}}
*[http://www.chrisfarleyfoundation.org/ Chris Farley Foundation]

{{Authority control|VIAF=22351712}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Farley, Chris
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Farley, Christopher Crosby
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Actor, comedian
|DATE OF BIRTH= February 15, 1964
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Madison, Wisconsin]], U.S.
|DATE OF DEATH= December 18, 1997
|PLACE OF DEATH= [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]], U.S.
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Farley, Chris}}
[[Category:1964 births]]
[[Category:1997 deaths]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in Illinois]]
[[Category:Actors from Chicago, Illinois]]
[[Category:Actors from Wisconsin]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:American Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Burials in Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Cocaine-related deaths in the United States]]
[[Category:Deaths by heroin overdose in the United States]]
[[Category:Drug-related deaths in Illinois]]
[[Category:IO Theater]]
[[Category:Marquette University alumni]]
[[Category:People from Madison, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Second City alumni]]
[[Category:20th-century actors]]</text>
      <sha1>emtwx2gqebpwd8iunnqhdc41spt5smw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
